Ears.
Awareness.
One of the most important things to understand about man is that man is asleep.
He doesn't wake up, even when he thinks he's awake.
His awakening is very fragile.
His awakening is so tiny that it shouldn't even be taken into account.
His wakefulness amounts to only a pretty but completely empty name.
You sleep at night.
You sleep by day.
From birth to death you keep moving from one pattern of sleep to another.
But you never truly wake up.
Don't fool yourself that you are waking up just because you open your eyes.
Until the inner eyes have opened.
Until you have learned to see.
To see who you really are.
Don't think that you are awake.
This is the greatest illusion in which man lives.
If you assume you're already awake, there can be no question of making an effort to actually wake up.
To be continued...