Hello.
Now we're going to extract electricity from space.
On any metal object you can get electricity.
Here I have a shovel.
I have a light bulb too, 75 watts.
And I have a device.
The device is very simple.
It consumes 11 volts, 150 milliamps.
Come over, show it.
Film it.
Did you show the device?
Show it.
There.
The device consumes, as you saw, one and a half watts.
Now we're going to light up the bulb.
The bulb is burning pretty well.
Where does the excess energy come from?
The basis?
Again.
The bulb?
Yes, again for now.
There, burning well, enough.
If you connect it directly, the bulb, naturally, as we've been taught all our lives, connect it like this, the bulb definitely won't light up.
That one and a half watts of energy won't light a 75-watt bulb.
We take energy from space.
And the secret of how we take it from space is a separate question.
Can you show the device close up.
Show this one.