First, we power this screwdriver from a traditional power source.
At the moment the power consumption is 79 watts and 102 volt-amps.
I clamp the chuck.
128 watts and 162 volt-amps.
Clamping the chuck.
That's how much consumption jumps per amp, practically.
OK, now we clamp the chuck.
Now we power it from our conceptual power supply.
From the conceptual power supply.
Can the RPMs go down?
Yes, we reduce the RPMs.
A bit.
It'll die.
Equivalently we reduce, drop the RPMs.
So at idle we lock in 9.1 watts.
9.6.
And 50... 50... 36 volt-amps.
Now we load it.
8.8 watts, it even dropped a bit.
And also 36 volt-amps.
35.4.
Now to the instruments.
Well, on these instruments not much to see.
Here we have an AC ammeter at the input.
Go on, give it some load.
It was visible that the load on the conceptual power supply has no effect.
Again.
No effect.
The needle doesn't move.
We're not locking in any amps.
The device is off.
And the voltage on the supply battery.
OK, all set.
Same screwdriver of ours.
Yeah.
Can I turn it on?
Yes, you can turn it on.
Go on, whoever's brave.
Spin it.
Idle time.
Voltage is steady, right?
The voltage didn't drop at all.
OK, now...
Let's make it 0.5.
Let's make it 0.5 and load it in this mode.
There it is.
There.
The effect is that there's no growth in consumption at all.
Now the voltage.
Oh, everything's in place, it's holding.
This is exactly the motor control system for electric vehicles.
From the battery.
A little bit longer, to make it work.
Hold it under load.
I'm afraid we won't save it.
These jumps were when it was completely jamming.
It seized up completely.
This is a kind of electric motor control system.
Voltage.
Let's go.
We're holding it carefully.
Like this, almost 0.5.
0.5 amps.
OK, what can I say.
The DC instrument shows about 25 volts.
That's exactly why they don't burn out.
They don't burn out, as long as it's working in this mode.
And we have to repeat the experiment now with power from an AC source.
We need to look at it now, when there's no effect on it, and how to bring it up.
Then we'll do it from a battery, that's what I was clamping.
And what does the voltmeter show?
Nothing, I only have the battery directly.
OK, go ahead, clamp it.
About 3.
3, right?
Yes.
Yes, you can see a jump.
There they expect it.
So, here's what we have.
A device for converting, let's say, electrical current to power motors.
Here's a motor designed to operate at 220 volts.
DC, from a blender.
Currently it's running on a 9V-style battery.
9-volt nominal voltage.
Current 0.6 amps.
Approximately.
So, at this moment the motor isn't doing any work besides spinning itself.
Well, and overcoming friction in the bearings, aerodynamics.
The motor is heating up a little.
We... in some time it'll discharge.
Naturally.
So, what are we doing?
We're simulating that this little motor is doing some work.
Easy on the camera, mainly.
I'm slowing it down.
Notice the ammeter.
It shows 0.6 amps.
You can see everything fine, actually.
When the camera goes back and forth, it looks really bad.
So, right now it's drawing 0.6 amps, no load.
We're loading it, loading the motor.
That is, the motor, for example, now drives the wheels of an electric vehicle.
Spins them.
But the consumed current doesn't change.
What does this mean, in simple terms?
It means that the current is spent solely on the control processes in the system.
And the motor draws the energy itself from outside.
So we're dealing with an open system.
Right now I'm clamping the motor with my hand.
A specific torque appears on the shaft, which should clearly cause a rise in current.
It turns out that at this moment this motor will discharge this battery in the same time whether it's working at idle or working under load.
That's it.