Fall has come, heating season is starting, and we decided to make an interesting construction, at the same time test the idea of whether pump-less heating of such a radiator is possible.
Pump-less means without an additional pump.
Last night we prepared all the parts for assembling a small boiler.
We'll heat with electricity, this kind of heating element.
Now we'll weld everything together.
This, say, will be the outputs to the radiator.
All the doubts are that the passage for water is of too small cross-section for normal water circulation through the radiator.
So now we'll assemble and check whether it works or not.
At the store we got a small expansion tank.
Cost not cheap, 600 rubles.
No choice.
This is a valve that'll trigger if water pressure in the system exceeds a dangerous mark.
Well, and metal "american" connectors, so it's easy to hang this boiler on this radiator.
Weld it, start it, test it and see if you can do it this way or not.
Although the plumbers assured us this won't work.
Let's try.
Started welding the lower hole where the heating element will be inserted.
To not damage the thread, we poured in pebbles.
Our helper is ready to help or break.
Welded the bottom cover.
Here's what we got.
The heating element will fit into this threaded hole.
Now moving to welding the top cover.
The top cover is needed for pouring water and we'll add an outlet for excess air to drain from the boiler.
We gave it a dome shape so air doesn't accumulate in corners.
Now we'll weld the thread here and move to assembling the boiler.
This way we aligned the passage axis with the radiator, tacked our transitions to the radiator in place.
Now we'll remove the metal "american" connectors and weld around just like this hole.
Now only put on the plugs, check how it holds water.
And go to testing.
Welded the hole and actually by the marking it slightly didn't match.
Visible in this part the metal slightly protrudes here.
But that's no problem, now every millimeter of passage matters.
A magic file will help us, it quickly fixes all the unevenness.
Let's go.
Our construction takes shape.
Welded the hole, cleaned up the outlets with a file, and now you can understand what we planned.
Just need to put the covers on top.
Our covers are also welded, now we'll civilize them a bit.
This goes on top, this on the bottom.
Basically that's all, nothing complicated.
The main thing is these holes matched up cleanly.
Why we tacked them to the radiator, so after all the assembly this thing easily fits, for the place.
Moving on.
With the help of simple tools we pack our boiler.
We already screwed on a tap for filling water and exiting excess air.
Here installed a transition washer for our heating element.
And now using this wrap-up we'll pack the heating element.
It'll go here to its permanent place.
Everything's pretty simple, as long as it works.
Installation finished.
Here's the finished product.
Wire, everything in place.
Vent, explosion valve, fill tap, expansion tank and the heating element itself with wire.
Now we'll measure how many liters of water fit in the system and in how much time this 1.5 kilowatt heating element warms our radiator.
And whether it warms at all, will it be warm.
First 5 liters went in.
Pour more cheerfully.
Water flows well.
Come on, cheerfully.
You can hear something bubbling.
Glad about something.
Let's see if water comes from here or not.
OK, the valve filled a bit.
OK, the valve will drip.
OK, more cheerfully, pour.
Such an interesting battery.
First 5 liters the system ate.
Going second.
Water dives in.
OK, we'll determine how much fits in this radiator and in the container we welded.
10 liters poured.
Now starting to pour from a 1.5 liter bottle and waiting for water to start coming from the air valve.
There, first drops there.
So, system is filled.
Pash, pull out the funnel.
We observe, full water system.
Now can close our air valve.
No air left in the system.
In total, what's left in the bottle.
Close the tap and there's the bottle.
Apparently 10.5 liters of water in the system.
Maybe a bit less than half, but let's count from consumption at 10.5 liters of water in the system.
Moving to field tests.
Installed a thermometer.
Outside now 18 degrees.
Here we'll start the countdown.
Well, turning on.
Let's go.
Yes.
Now we'll observe how long it takes for our system to heat this thing.
Thermometer let it show us correct readings.
And stopwatch time.
This will be here.
Waiting.
Here we'll look by time.
Almost 3 minutes.
A minute and a half ago we felt time, that here warming is observed.
Movement of warm water started in these places.
At this distance you can already feel warmth from the system.
Almost to the middle.
Now we'll observe.
I think the system will work.
Warmth came.
Already noticeably here so nicely, when outside such weather.
Heating going.
At the same time breaking in the system.
Now of course no cold, but in wind conditions.
We'll see.
If this radiator heats well, then the room will be warm too.
Waiting. At the 8th minute we started observing temperature rise.
Warmth came from above.
Already noticeably the side channels from the radiator fully warmed up.
And so somewhere about 15 cm from the top now warm water has noticeably started going down.
And the reactor itself is already getting hot.
Now looking.
Almost 10 minutes ticked by.
That is, we see the system seems to give noticeable signs of life because it's warm.
Can already warm hands.
Warmth practically descends to the middle.
This is good, guys.
So maybe we won't need a pump.
Fourteenth minute of experiment.
Already burning the hand.
Temperature, we see, went up.
Here already noticeable heat convection.
Warm air rises.
By feeling, the warm water reached the bottom of the radiator fully.
And looks like the system will work.
Because in the open air now it's windy.
Feeling of warmth pretty clear.
Our experiment time and temperature.
We already got over 30 degrees at output in conditions.
That's how our thermometer is mounted.
But on hand here much more.
Burns the fingers.
This radiator of such dimensions, 1.20 m, is designed for 26 square meters of living space.
Right, temperature can be seen going.
Here it's already uncomfortable to hold, burns.
So, 22 minutes of experiment.
Temperature rises.
Here already specifically burning.
Thermometer doesn't want to give us.
And we notice that the whole radiator over its entire length gives a uniform flow of warmth.
And warmth went to the very corner heating.
That is at the farthest point we observe radiator heating.
This means it works over the whole length.
Warm, pleasant.
Time passes, temperature grows.
And here can't hold anymore.
Then when our heating element turns off, we measure temperature on the radiator surface in different places.
Put this same thermometer and look.
Half hour of work.
Here better not touch.
Burns awesome.
Temperature grows.
Here all the warmth goes over the whole plane of the radiator.
And this part already noticeably warming up too.
Looks like our experiment goes well.
10.5 liters of water the system heated in half hour, already can't grab it.
Next, thermometer is poorly attached, doesn't transmit full temperature.
Now we'll move to temperature measurements on the radiator surface.
I think in the farthest corner.
This is the measurement most interesting to us.
Simply we install it, will stand in air flow.
Wait a bit and find out what's happening here.
Outside good wind.
Walks 18-degree temperature.
So, experiment time 36 minutes.
And so we recently set our thermometer.
And as we see, temperature relentlessly rises in the farthest corner of the radiator.
Now air temperature it gives off 50 degrees in this place.
We understand here, in this area, it's much hotter.
Fingers can't take it.
And most interesting, our system on top is very hot, and below temperature, can hold.
This means one thing — that water movement in the system exists, circulation exists, and the radiator really gives heat to air.
If this weren't, this whole cylinder would be heated to same temperature.
37 minutes.
I think we'll test it for an hour, that's for sure.
These readings really really please us.
Try to transmit by camera.
Here haze of warm air above the radiator.
Comes out wonderfully.
You can see how it streams.
If you look at plants, they're kind of blurred slightly.
That is warmth goes in full growth.
System works.
What's our time?
Time 40 minutes of experiment in the far corner.
54 degrees we already have.
System still warms up outside.
We're interested in its warming.
We'll track in this place.
Here significantly hotter.
Want to say that this radiator looks great aesthetically.
Generally, not like bi-metal.
No ribs that you have to laboriously clean dust from with a cloth.
Here everything's nice, can wipe the surface.
Thanks to manufacturers.
Same surface on back too.
And the ribbing inside gives off such a flow of warm air.
Let's see who made it.
Good product.
And pleases that welding doesn't leak anywhere.
Here our helper burns his fingers.
It's very hot, better not touch.
Moving further in our experiment.
While we chatted, temperature went up more.
Think above 60, maybe even 70, we'll catch up.
45th minute, going 46th.
We reached on our thermometer the mark 60 degrees.
System works stably.
Good.
At the 50th minute we heard thermosensor trigger in this cylinder.
Click.
Power was disconnected.
This means the thermosensor caught temperature inside the cylinder 80 degrees.
And it turns out, that slightly above 60 degrees when power disconnected in the far end of radiator and 80 degrees here.
It comes out difference of 20 degrees.
Normal state between heating element and the place where maximum heat output is obtained in the far corner that interests us.
In outdoor conditions, wind blowing, most likely this balance will be maintained.
80 in heating cylinder and 60 at far corner of radiator.
And so it's pretty comfortable.
Warmth goes very well.
So, our historic moment.
Approaching an hour.
Now boiler was wound to max 85 degrees and we heard a click.
Power disconnected and now observing here, what in far corner.
Here we have 64 degrees.
Summing up our experiment.
85 degrees water temperature in cylinder, air temperature in far corner of radiator is 64-65 degrees at output.
In windy weather conditions outside.
That is, we see temperature conditions.
We have 18 degrees warmth outside.
This corresponds, if this radiator stood in room.
15-18 degrees not heated.
We turned it on and there with same conditions temperature would quickly rise.
By the way, now visible the temperature continues to slowly rise.
Think our experiment is successful.
Then we'll check it in winter conditions, how it'll work.
And here excellent flow of warm air.
So, what did we make it from?
The tube was... How much, Pash, did we take tube?
114 tube.
Chinese heating element.
1.5 kW with temperature regulator.
Can set as desired.
And a bit of attachments.
Cost of this construction came to 5000 rubles.
This radiator 600 rubles.
Expansion tank, valve 180 rubles.
Adapters here 420 rubles.
Approximately, if look at everything, wiring, all other stuff, electrodes about 2000 rubles.
Cost price of boiler itself with attachments, all this.
By the way, also took valve.
Well and radiator, consider 7000 rubles for 26 square meters of space.
Such a product.
Temperature measurement.
What's happening here?
Can say, hour-five minutes of work.
Ten and a half liters of water.
1.5 kilowatt heating element.
Observing.
Our temperature went up.
Well, can say a bit sun came out now.
Discount this too.
But 70 degrees of hot air in far corner we boldly got.
And temperature continues to grow.
Recommend for repetition.
And a small ending.
Were pleasantly surprised, set up, seemingly, thermometer to the boiler itself.
Temperature the same.
That is, what can be said about this Thermoking radiator?
That, regardless of whether it's close to the boiler, in the middle or far corner, temperature output over the whole length of this radiator is the same.
Air exits with same temperature.
Convection works great.
No such temperature difference that say here would be hot, here cooler, here cold.
Over whole surface of this radiator air temperature at output is the same.
Super!
Our time is one nine.
Ending our experiment.
Here another interesting moment.
Just an hour twenty practically.
At hour turned it off.
Another 20 minutes we can observe that temperature for us doesn't fall particularly strongly.
Radiator continues to give off.
Moreover over whole surface measured equally.
Really cool thing.
Now of course will drain water.
Will need to install it, but I think a couple-three hours from it will still come noticeable warmth.
In case, say, if turned off light, for some time won't be without warmth.
Still 10.5 liters of water in system have reserve.
And here not bad.
Fingers still burning.