Greetings everyone.
Today I'll tell about the methodology for determining the push-pull operating frequency for this coil.
So wave processes happen in it, heating of this coil happens without load presence.
That is, so current really ramps up in the system.
Now we'll test it and see at what frequencies we always work, and what frequencies are actually needed.
For this we need this auxiliary instrument, ferrite ring mark 1500-2000, can be higher, doesn't matter.
Wind 8-10 turns, resistance not needed, we don't track exact phasing.
We just need to know current amplitude in this system.
Meaning of how this works.
When electric current moves through a conductor, or charges are in place but spin rotation happens, around the conductor magnetic field forms.
When this ring is put on, magnetic field is captured and on these turns converts it to voltage potential, which we track on oscilloscope.
To track current movement in this coil, we'll need coil leads, short between each other physically, galvanically, and already see when this coil works on half-wave.
Where do we start?
Put ring on any of leads, short,
make good contact and connect oscilloscope.
Phasing isn't important.
Common and probe itself.
From instruments we'll also need signal generator and oscilloscope.
Signal generator output connects directly to coil inductor itself.
And next will look what's happening on instruments.
Now we see,
feed 5 kHz for starters.
Feed sine signal,
amplitude on.
Range our peak-to-peak amplitude is 10 volts.
And now we'll sweep frequency and observe oscillogram, what's happening.
Now passing usual operating frequency, where from about 10 to 45-50 kHz.
Where practically everyone works.
And we see that being in 25 kHz zone makes no sense because current amplitude is minimal at this frequency.
Going further.
Passed 60 kHz and already see amplitude starts to grow.
Looking further.
Look what range passed.
Amplitude now 0.2 volts per division.
Nothing remarkable visible yet.
Going further.
Amplitude doesn't change much.
Can speed up process not by 1 kHz but by 10 kHz.
Look, already went to 500 kHz and amplitude didn't shift significantly.
And only starting from 800 kHz we see some jump in amplitude growth.
Amplitude grows, grows.
Reached maximum around 910 kHz.
Accordingly push-pull can't work at such frequency.
We have one variant — work in multiplicity to this frequency.
Say, if here 910 kHz, we can work at 91 kHz.
Now we'll check what else might be interesting at this frequency.
If we lay hand on coil at this frequency, we can check how for this frequency surrounding objects affect this coil.
We're interested in moment so frequencies are stable.
Looking.
Now I'll lay hand on coil and we'll observe amplitude.
Laid hand, visible amplitude grows.
Lay here in reverse turns zone.
Amplitude grows.
Now pass further by frequency.
980 kHz.
Amplitude grows too.
1000 kHz.
Also small growth.
1100 kHz.
Growth minimum.
Window of possibilities comes out somewhere from 850 to 1100 kHz operation.
We determined first range, and now can record it.
Recording.
830-1100 kHz.
This is our window in multiplicity to which we'll try to work on push-pull.
Next will determine if there's some high-frequency component for current in this system at which current growth will be observed even higher.
Going by frequency.
Passing range and no special amplitude growth observed.
Looking for moment when there'll be clear jump.
Step 10 kHz, quite acceptable.
At 3800 even amplitude drop.
Here, look, fixed moment.
Starting at 3910 kHz we have sharp amplitude rise.
Now searching more smoothly.
Growing, growing.
Good growth, can even set sweep to half-volt per division.
Also see growth.
1 volt per division.
And here, drop starts approximately at 4650 kHz.
Maximum amplitude 4620-630.
This is our second maximum.
Recording it.
4620-4630 kHz.
Look at hand influence at this frequency.
Usually at such high frequencies there'll already be observed losses.
Visible these frequencies aren't so stable, but amplitude is maximum.
This is normal process.
Let's see, maybe we can find something further.
Next amplitude decrease.
Run more, step of 100 kHz.
Here some maximum still small.
Found at 7600.
Frequencies already high, this doesn't interest us anymore.
And further at 11 MHz.
Such high frequency in our systems already unreachable, not needed.
At it very unstable results.
Say, 8800, amplitude not so big.
And influence very strong if touching coil.
In reality we determined two operating frequencies where current is maximum.
One of them stable.
Course of our next actions.
Now we need to find such frequency in multiplicity, in this range.
Which by spectrum analysis would fall into this strong frequency.
And at that, like the tenth harmonic, it would excite some of the frequencies in this range.
Next we'll need to switch oscilloscope to spectrum analyzer mode.
So-called FFT mode, fast Fourier transform.
And check spectrogram of this signal.
That is, our window of possibilities is from 83 to 110 kHz operation in multiplicity.
Switch oscilloscope to spectrum analyzer mode.
Here it is, FFT mode.
And what to know about measurements this way.
This way you can't measure signal harmonics that will be shown in spectrum as graphs in decibels.
With sine signal.
Now I'll show moment.
Now 83 kHz fed to input.
And if we look,
in such mode device shows only central frequency that's fed on sine.
In this case will be 83 kHz.
Now we'll bring sweep to division.
We're interested in division sweep for spectrum analyzer in area of 50 kHz per division.
Can now disable first output,
so it doesn't disturb us.
And now can observe spectral picture.
Now remind, signal generator is in sine mode.
What do we see here?
In center of scale intersection the frequency is.
And if we place central peak in decibels in central area, we'll know its frequency.
Here, in particular, place center and see our 83 kHz.
Now I'll show where it's displayed.
On this device for me displayed in lower left corner.
Here they are, 83 kHz, clearly in center.
And we see that what we feed to input in sine mode, device determines.
To excite harmonics, we need to feed signal with steep edge.
Meaning switch signal generator to square wave.
Switching.
Now see our picture changed.
Can observe in multiplicity step of frequencies with some spectrum range.
And now further search methodology.
We determined our highest current amplitude is in area 4620-4630 kHz.
And we now in this range from 83 to 110 kHz will be interested in such frequency that'll give highest signal in decibels at these frequencies.
Looking for our frequency.
4000...
600...
Here we have 630.
More precisely set.
Here they are our 4630 MHz.
That is we understand in center.
Now need by selecting these frequencies in our window of possibilities to place spectrogram peak in scale center.
And start searching by frequencies.
Very smoothly.
Going in tenths of Hz.
And here we see, first hit.
Observing.
4630 at 84.2 kHz.
Recording.
84.2.
Going further.
There.
Want to draw attention.
84.2.
Visible harmonics come out here too.
We're interested in cleaner spectrum when there are no side harmonics.
There.
Picture approximately should be like that.
Here another hit.
At 87.4 kHz.
But also see there are side peaks.
Recording.
87.4 kHz.
Going further.
And here very good frequency we found.
Exact hit without strong side harmonics corresponds to 90.8 kHz.
Can go further.
Another hit.
94.5 kHz.
Also good frequency.
Note them.
Recording.
And noting frequencies where no strong side harmonics.
Moving further.
Another hit.
But here we already see powerful side harmonics.
Skipping.
Also see at 103 kHz side harmonics.
Also side harmonics at 107.7 kHz powerful.
And window of possibilities for us up to 110 kHz.
We passed it.
Already further interests us.
Now can say we have two most likely operating frequencies.
This is 90.8 kHz and 94.5 kHz.
At which coil excitation happens at this powerful frequency.
Now look which of these frequencies will fall into our range 830-110 kHz.
Collapse spectrogram and look what's happening.
And see, this is our first that we excite.
Say, now it corresponds to 111 kHz.
Setting our 90.8 kHz.
And can also see maximum excitation in this high-frequency zone.
And here's one of peaks.
Now we'll examine it.
Here our frequency.
First 90.8 kHz.
And went to look.
Here's second peak 276 kHz.
Looking for high in amplitude.
And here we see, one of peaks that hit at frequency 90.8 kHz, hits us exactly at 1 MHz.
And see this also fits very well into our window of possibilities.
That is exciting at this frequency the coil, we give acceleration both by first frequency component, stable, and by second.
And now look at frequency 94.5 kHz.
Switching.
94.5.
And looking.
Highest peak also hits here.
But greatest stability, if we recall, was near 910 kHz.
And maximum gain when we laid hand on coil.
And maximum gain in amplitude when amplitude measurement was.
That is, we can now determine that this frequency 90.8 kHz suits us maximally for push-pull operation, based on spectrogram.
Marking it.
This is the search methodology.
Now for verification can switch to our 90.8 kHz frequency, collapse spectrogram and look also by highest peaks in decibels.
Setting and see really 1 MHz exactly.
And can switch to another high peak.
Here, highest.
This is our 4630.
Here this peak.
Meaning we found our frequency correctly.
Also can do one more check of these frequencies we found out in practice.
By similarity of beat pictures at various frequencies.
Now square wave is sent at frequency 91 kHz.
Also continue to watch on current sensors.
This is signal we feed.
Creates such oscillations, if look at them in coil.
Will watch the beats.
Collapsing sweep and
see interesting pictures.
Now check similarity of these pictures, these oscillograms' appearance at another multiplicity frequency.
Feed frequency on signal generator at 910 kHz.
Now oscilloscope shows envelope amplitude.
And see amplitude grew, but actually beats preserved.
And have same form.
Examined...
Now sweep is time 5 microseconds per division.
And send to input our basic strong frequency, which is 4630 kHz.
Amplitude off the chart.
Returning and see here already known and familiar fish.
That is we hit basic strong frequency for this coil.
This can be observed when ramping up with square signal, can switch to sine signal.
Amplitude will decrease but beats will be preserved.
Here visible at different sweeps.
Picture preserved up to
sine on basic carrier.
And same, if signal has sufficient strength, oscilloscope will show envelope form, that is sine on these fish.
Can measure also its frequency.
Switch to cursor measurement mode.
Press pause.
First cursor set.
Second.
We can see that frequency of our beats in this coil is 32.47 Hz.
Which also testifies that this isn't mains pickup of 50 Hz, but quite real processes happening in this coil.
In practice I also verified this result.
Frequency 91 kHz was fed here.
And this coil started warming up very well without load presence at this frequency.
Which testifies that warming happens in this zone.
Practically by feel, didn't measure with thermometer, but about 45-50 degrees.
Warming with consumption about 3 amps on push-pull.
Heating of this coil happens without load.
Clear current movement on conductor length.
Which is what we generally need.
On push-pull you can't do as such LC resonance.
I'll show this later.
That is you can't feed 91 kHz directly to inductor.
What happens?
Of course this can be tried, but everyone did this.
Very interesting moment happens.
If we feed here frequency equal to keys' operating frequency, actually we get such moment.
Now I'll draw.
Say, this is our push-pull frequency.
And we have signal during transistors' operation, which we ramp up in each half-cycle of operation.
When here, at this point, the Tesla triggers, the strike will happen practically near maximum, we'll get what many saw from own experience, push-pull power keys
blowing.
So this doesn't happen, our push-pull is driven into another mode.
As I drew earlier, and many people had questions why I drew this picture, which I showed in another video clip, where I have incident wave, as I drew, and have
reflected wave.
And they're in phase.
Were many questions why drawn this way.
Like wrong.
We all know from classics that reflected wave returns with 180-degree shift.
All true.
This is reflected wave by voltage.
By current we don't consider this moment.
That is if we do by current reflected wave in oscillating circuit with 180-degree shift, this will be equivalent to turning two magnets toward each other with same-named poles.
General gain of such powerful magnetic field won't be observed.
That's exactly why in push-pull we achieve that incident and reflected wave are in phase.
Physically this is visible if we hang current sensor in inductor's oscillating circuit.
And on one trace will observe such picture that both our wave went and the reverse one that returns.
It'll also copy this wave in phase, will be practically such picture.
They'll go in phase, only with smaller amplitude.
This is achieved on push-pull by selecting capacitance between capacitance hung on inductor's oscillating circuit and between capacitance hung on output of our gradient coil grenade.
And what happens?
Push-pull works at low frequency.
But when we look with oscilloscope, it'll show us frequency higher than main signal frequency.
Therefore in my case I found out my frequency is 91 kHz.
This means I need push-pull to actually work 2 times lower, can drive 3 times lower.
Get this picture.
In practice I even got 3 waves in phase.
That's how visible on current sensor in one phase.
When this happens we get powerful total addition of magnetic field.
And if we then collapse sweep, division time, we can see very interesting pictures in form of so-called fish.
What's such trick needed for?
We already discussed if Tesla strikes basic, first harmonic, transistors fly out.
But if we have such picture, then when Tesla works on free oscillation, here at this point we have sharp current amplitude rise.
When we look on current transformer, we see this picture I showed in video.
Influence of Tesla transformer on current in oscillating circuit.
There current amplitude jumps up, sine becomes much bigger.
At that overall consumption we measure from power source going to push-pull power, decreases.
Current amplitude grows, and system consumption decreases.
In numbers in practice, say, if in normal mode without Tesla push-pull ate consumption 3 amps at 24 volts, then with Tesla operation increase, one particular case, it consumes 1 amp at
same 24 volts power.
Such interesting feature.
In subsequent videos will look at how this happens, how it works.
Good luck everyone in experiments.