Hi everyone.
In this video I'll tell how to make a pyrotechnic product for New Year holidays.
Similar to those sold in retail.
We'll be making rockets.
And for which we'll need three main ingredients.
First of which is potassium nitrate.
On sale can be bought as crushed white-colored crystals.
Potassium nitrate can be bought in plant supply stores.
For plant protection.
Or in stores selling fertilizers.
In this case a half-kilogram package was bought.
From Buyskie Fertilizers brand.
Or can be bought in smaller 25-gram packaging.
Next main ingredient is sorbitol.
Also is in form of soft white crystals.
Sorbitol is a substance that replaces sugar for diabetics.
Bought in pharmacies.
Usually sold by weight in half-kilograms.
Such quantity enough for many experiments.
Well, third ingredient is sulfur.
In nature occurs as bright yellow crystals.
Buy as crushed yellow powder.
Sulfur is bought in pet stores.
In veterinary stores.
Sold as additive to feed for cattle or birds.
In this case such packaging.
In description read so sulfur is pure without impurities.
Or in such packaging can find.
Next, when these substances are bought.
Look at degree of drying of substances.
Visually substances should be wet.
If needed, these powders are additionally dried on radiator.
After drying of our three components possibly will need additional grinding of potassium nitrate and sulfur.
If component was before with moisture impurity and moisture evaporated, lumps may form.
Substance lumps we crush with wooden object until uniform powder forms.
With sorbitol such actions don't need to be done because sorbitol in rocket fuel preparation will melt to fluid mass and remaining components will be added to it.
After grinding of substances move to their weighing.
For this we'll need some household scales capable of weighing substances to tenths of gram.
In this case such scales capable of precisely weighing weight of objects up to 200 grams and showing to hundredths.
This quite suits us.
With help of scales we measure out our components in ratio 60 grams potassium nitrate, 30 grams sorbitol and 10 grams sulfur.
Such amount of mixed substances later enough for us to fill two such rocket engines to full working state.
Next move to responsible moment, this is making rocket engine body.
On how you make it will depend flight characteristics of your future pyrotechnic product.
For making body we'll need plastic mandrel from water pipe with outer diameter 20 mm, drill diameter 2.5 mm, some metal object with polished surface, in this case piece of old screwdriver 10 cm
long.
And under outer diameter of this metal pin drill is selected, in this case outer diameter 4 mm.
Material of body is A4 paper, for making one blank we'll need 8 sheets of paper.
Done by winding paper onto plastic mandrel, align paper ends and make full rotation.
After making full rotation, draw your attention that rotation is done without glue, otherwise it'll be very hard to extract guide mandrel.
After that we smear remaining surface of sheet with PVA glue fully using brush, prior under all this need to lay oilcloth or polyethylene so as not to smear with glue
working table surface.
Wind paper, this way wind 8 layers, smear each layer with glue, after which we get paper tube, extract body of mandrel and from one end form star from paper.
This way, when there are 8 layers, paper will be much thicker, but due to that it's impregnated with glue, it'll also be pliable, after which star rays are placed one on top of another in a circle and
compressed.
And after this, as you folded, this all wrapped with thread.
Same manipulation we do with opposite side, fold and wrap.
In result you'll get such blank.
When we wrapped with thread, all this smeared with PVA glue, good impregnate each side, and get blank.
Blank subsequently after drying cut with utility knife into two halves.
In result we see from one blank get two bodies.
Drying of this body done on radiator or directly on heating boiler not less than 12 hours.
After glue dries, whole blank acquires rigidity.
If knock on it, sound like metal object knocking on bone.
Body acquires rigidity and strength.
Now weigh body without rocket fuel.
Body weight in this case is 16 grams.
After blank was divided into two bodies, move to drilling hole for gas exit that'll raise our pyrotechnic product.
Into sky this hole is called nozzle.
For which we'll need drill that with help of thinner drill we drill hole strictly vertically in center, after which we widen it with drill equal to outer diameter of rod.
Next prepare our body for fuel pouring.
For this into drilled hole rod is inserted.
Rod should enter tightly, not wobble.
And see that after its insertion rod is in center of rocket engine body.
Also can note that rod height made so for us about one and a half centimeters left to body edge of engine.
Rod height will determine for us level of fuel pouring in rocket engine.
Next these one and a half centimeters will be sealed.
Move to fuel preparation.
Cooking better on electric stove, but when none, cook on minimum fire.
And with help of metal object, in this case using fire diffuser.
First, nitrate poured into ceramic or metal container needs to be well heated for 4-5 minutes so whole container is hot and powder inside it.
If this isn't done, then later when adding nitrate fuel will quickly thicken.
Heat nitrate, then set aside.
After use metal little cup, can metal glass, jar, whoever has what at hand.
And pour into it pure sorbitol.
Sorbitol needs to be brought to melting.
Set, now can add fire and bring sorbitol to melting.
After 5 minutes of heating turn off strong fire.
See sorbitol melted.
White mass forms.
Further melting done with stirring until full dissolution of all particles.
Liquid mass forms.
Now when all fully melted, move to pouring nitrate into sorbitol melt.
Nitrate previously heated for us.
Pour nitrate, distribute over surface evenly.
And after some heating on slow fire, do mixing.
For those cooking first time, recommend keeping water container nearby so in case of ignition cooking fuel container can be quickly lowered into water.
White mass forms, like semolina, uniform.
Mix well and only after uniform mass formed, add sulfur, because sulfur leads to fuel thickening.
Add it to composition at very last case.
Distribute sulfur and do mixing.
At that fire continues to burn at minimum and warms our container.
Uniform homogeneous mass forms, like this, already yellow-colored.
That's it, fuel ready.
After this can turn off fire completely and time comes to pour fuel into rocket engine.
Look for convenient stand, rod is in center and move to pouring.
Fuel hot, so flows easily.
Engine fully filled.
Slightly tap on its walls and fuel evenly settles inside body.
During fuel cooling in rocket engine body some shrinkage of it happens.
Here visible central metal rod that's there.
Now about 5 minutes at tapping on body fuel thickens.
Visible rod still slightly mobile.
Will need about 5-10 more minutes for fuel to acquire needed consistency and internal pin can be removed.
While fuel hardens in first body, periodically heat remaining amount on low fire and do its stirring so as not to let fuel thicken.
Visible has thicker mass, so it needs to be periodically reheated to then also pour into next prepared body.
Fuel temperature need to keep so sulfur doesn't go into molten state.
That is, it should stay in form of fine dispersion of powder in fuel composition.
This important for its characteristic.
And also in this fuel composition for more colorful effects can introduce powders of various metals.
For example, if introduce several grams of magnesium in composition, there'll be silver-white tail behind rocket.
Same color can add aluminum, copper will add greenish color.
That is, with this can experiment and each will find interesting effect.
We heated fuel to initial state, now it can also be poured into body of second engine.
Composition quite thickened, now can move to removing rod from body.
Pull out carefully, rod will exit with tension.
For this it should be polished.
Did extraction and we have channel formed in center.
Example of how such fuel burns in open air.
Rocket fuel by data given at start of video with sulfur addition has one distinctive feature from rocket fuel that doesn't have sulfur added.
Ordinary rocket fuel where 60 grams potassium nitrate and 40 grams sorbitol are cooked, it hardens long, about day needed for hardening.
Plus has not such mechanical properties as fuel with sulfur added.
Sulfur also participates in rocket fuel burning with formation of bigger gas amount.
And sulfur very well strengthens the fuel itself.
It transforms into structure resembling stone.
Audible if knock with metal object, and quite strongly fuel doesn't crack, no cracks form, that is good mechanical properties.
This very important so in body where fuel poured there are no voids, because voids or fuel cracking during engine operation can lead to anomalous burning and
body rupture.
We don't need this so we follow manufacturing technology.
Fuel with sulfur added hardens in 10 hours to this state.
After 10 hours this engine ready for use.
Can install it on pyrotechnic product.
In manufacturing process question may arise, why central channel is formed in rocket engine fuel.
Now analyze this on example of this drawing.
Schematically shown engine in cross-section.
These are paper walls, paper cork and visible fuel with central channel.
Analyze burning process.
When igniting fuel it burns along whole length of central channel.
During burning central channel diameter constantly grows and fuel burns toward walls, and gas escapes through nozzle.
This way we provide big diameter of burning fuel surface, fast its burning and as result formation of big pressure of exhaust gases.
This way our pyrotechnic product gains very big speed.
And able to rise to much greater height compared to engine that's filled with fuel without central channel.
Second plus of such design is that burning fuel in central channel protects engine body walls from burning temperature and also protects it from pressure of exhaust
gases.
So main working zone for us is rocket engine nozzle.
So to rocket engine nozzle big requirements in plan of manufacturing.
It should be very well glued and wrapped with thread.
This is main part of rocket engine.
Now I'll show engine that's properly worked.
Managed to find our model.
See that it was in operation.
And can pay attention to nozzle.
Visible that form didn't change, nozzle isn't torn, thread remained intact.
Small burning zone during operation.
Walls also remained strong, they don't push through from hand force.
That is, engine worked stably without destruction of integrity of its construction.
Now I'll show example of engine that was in operation but in it central channel didn't form.
This engine to this point was filled with fuel.
And can pay attention to what happened to nozzle.
Thread burned, there are burns in several places.
And the nozzle itself is torn from pressing gases.
Can observe that tube easily crumples, which means walls strongly thinned during rocket fuel burning.
After this demonstration I'll show video of how launch of this pyrotechnic product was done and what it led to.
Move to forming rocket engine cork.
This part has special requirements since on it very big pressure from exhaust gases is exerted.
And pressure is of such force that if your cork is poorly made, it'll just knock it out and rocket either won't fly at all or fly to insignificant height.
Part is very responsible, so it needs to be well fixed to body.
For cork to glue well to body, need to remove first layer of paper that wasn't impregnated with glue when we rolled body on mandrel of plastic tube.
This layer of paper is removed and bent over surface of fuel itself.
This layer will protect channel in rocket engine fuel from glue getting in.
This way it's scraped off and lowered on fuel surface to layer that's quality glued.
This needs to be done, otherwise this paper that holds badly may just be torn off by gas pressure.
Together I'll show with cork.
Small video where clearly visible the moment when cork is poorly made.
Paper well pressed and hole made to depth about 3 mm, after which into hole fuse is placed.
This way we form fuse ignition time at the moment when fuel burned to greater degree and burning reached directly walls.
After which fuse ignition happens.
It burns for one and a half seconds, passing through cork, after which ignition of ejection charge happens.
For forming cork body we'll need porous fabric, medical bandage works well and water-based glue.
For starts, well smear with glue walls and surface of rocket engine fuel.
For
this use wooden stick.
Need to smear whole surface and very well so bandage impregnates and quality glues.
Bandage
cut into strips about 10 cm and immerse into body.
Next material should be well compacted, at that the fuse itself needs to be pressed to body wall.
Then impregnation of first layer happens over surface.
Impregnate very well so whole fabric filled with glue.
This provides quality adhesion and gluing of surface to rocket engine body.
Fuse for igniting should be taken thicker.
If fuse from pyrotechnic products is thin, then better lay it 2-3 pieces in one bundle.
First layer well impregnated.
Introduce second bandage layer.
After introducing second layer do interesting operation.
Start forming sewing with help of wire or thread.
For this at depth of second layer surface hole made with help of awl.
Next circle outlined along which sewing height will go.
Along contour hole made approximately every 8 mm.
Next move to sewing with help of wire.
Wire is pulled through hole and laid with intersection in center.
With transition to one hole and transferred to next opposite.
This way we form mesh that tightly presses first two layers of fabric to fuel.
After glue hardening quality plug will form.
Next we'll lay subsequent layer of glue-impregnated material and last layer with paper plug.
After sewing such wire surface forms.
More convenient even to sew with help of thread and needle in these holes, comes out faster.
Took wire for clarity, so it's visible how formed.
Next once more impregnate surface with glue.
This quality gluing has decisive significance so your cork isn't knocked out during operation, or burns through.
Also one more layer of bandage is added, after which already glued with porous paper.
Can take napkin.
Last hole closed and flat surface formed equal in height to engine body.
Before paper laying layer fully poured with glue and its full impregnation happens.
Then on this glue paper lays.
For strength can add fine sawdust here, or add gypsum.
Mix with glue, will increase strength and reduce drying time of glue itself.
In practice can experiment and find most optimal constructions for own solutions.
After plug fully dried, move to forming part that's responsible for light-noise effects in sky.
For this need to make tubes from paper of various diameters.
Can much bigger diameter than rocket engine itself.
All depends what you want to fill it with.
In this case I took body offcut.
Now we fix it.
Visible that fuse comes out for igniting working substance.
Fix it on body with help of adhesive tape.
What can be used as filling?
As filling can use absolutely anything.
Any cheap pyrotechnic products that can burn with help of sparkling stars.
Can use such balls with sparkling stars, filling from them.
Can load some quantity of firecrackers here.
If you have larger diameter tube, then quantity of firecrackers will fit much more.
This, I repeat, for example took model, what can be done.
Now, what does filling serve as ejection charge for such construction?
I, say, use black powder of homemade production.
But can also use filling from pyrotechnic products.
Can use as ejection charge granules from same rocket fuel.
Granules are rolled into small balls 3-4 mm diameter and fill about 1 cm.
In this case I fill working zone with black powder.
For reliable ejection charge operation about 1 cm enough.
And for spectacle and effect add metal powders.
In this case I'll add some quantity of magnesium powder.
Now
composition should be slightly mixed.
Magnesium will give in sky beautiful flash of silver-white color, that'll be visible, observing
mixture.
Now can move to installation of components that'll be ejected by gas pressure and work in air.
In this case will use firecrackers.
Then charge with sparkling stars.
Whole filling should freely come out from ejection charge pressure.
It descends without special effort.
Also use sparkling stars from pyrotechnic product.
Plastic balls that rupture with crack.
Take their filling.
Add some powder for reliable igniting of this part of filling.
Fuse tip I lower into this zone.
As nose cone we'll be served by part from disassembled ball.
It very well sits here.
Like this.
Becomes like little cap and holds very tightly.
Our demonstration product ready.
Now I'll fix it with help of adhesive tape on wooden stabilizer.
Wooden stabilizer length about 80 cm.
And we'll test its flight characteristics.
Product in ready form.
Attached to wooden stabilizer with help of adhesive tape.
Visible that need to combine rocket engine channel center with wooden guide.
And as fuse for igniting rocket fuel will use two factory little fuses twisted with thread from cheap pyrotechnic products.
Fuse, so it's reliably fixed, bent and introduced into engine.
Now weigh our ready product.
Weight is 96 grams.