Hi everyone!
Look, hot disputes are flaring up on the channel about this device.
There are lots of interesting comments — and plenty of nonsense ones, like "you don't know how to use the device, the measurement is wrong."
Or "the probes on your oscilloscope burned out."
By the way, they're 1500-volt probes.
These probes have 100x suppression.
There's no way they can burn out here.
Anyway, let me show you so you can see.
I'll show you — although in that video I showed that when I put the yellow channel on the transistor gate, it clearly shows the oscillogram, meaning it didn't burn out.
OK, enough talking nonsense.
A guy writes: "Finally convinced that 99.9% of similar videos are purely making money on views."
Well, if that's what you think, fine.
And here's an interesting comment.
"Of course the pulse polarity didn't change — you didn't swap the probe."
Yeah, no question.
I'll swap the probe now — you won't see this pulse at all there.
You'll just see the switch working, that's it.
The pulse happens for us exclusively at this point.
Why do I take it from here?
Exclusively here — nowhere else in the schematic.
Damn, I'm already tired of repeating that this isn't back EMF.
Well, OK.
What people won't come up with.
And boost converter, this one.
I'm familiar with its schematic.
And flyback, familiar.
And I've built such schematics.
Everything looks great to me.
This pulse — we'll flip it now and you won't see it there.
It's only here at this point.
So — measurement 1.
Confirming that my probes are still intact.
Oscilloscope common is on minus.
Now we'll watch the oscillogram on the transistor gates.
That is, after the drivers.
Here — two probes, and you can see the picture is identical.
There, damn, it works.
Potential is 15 volts.
And here we see power.
Exactly 15 volts, drawing 0.15 A.
Probes normal — passed the check.
So, now the probe has moved — also relative to common minus — to the output of one of the bifilars.
I do all measurements directly before the diode, not after it.
After it is useless — there's DC on the cap.
So strictly before the diode.
Now applying — voltage isn't applied to the switches yet, here's the oscillogram, applying voltage.
Remember, we have this kind of oscillogram.
Here it is.
Remember it well.
It's not back EMF.
Now look — switching common to plus.
Switched.
The oscillogram is still there.
Here it is.
Now look — even a joke.
Measurements aren't done this way, but watch — I'll disconnect common.
Only the probe hangs.
Positive.
The oscillogram is still there.
This current doesn't belong to this system, to the power source.
Now switching the probe.
Look on the contrary.
You won't see this signal there — none of it at that point.
Probe flipped.
Now it's on minus of power.
Common on the same bifilar.
Here's the picture.
No flipped signal of large amplitude that we saw before.
Notice the sweep — volts per cell.
Now 20 V per cell.
None of that signal.
Now switching the probe to plus.
I don't see anything in this sense, but let me switch it.
Here it is on plus.
Here's the work.
None of that signal.
It's only in one place.
Swap places — everything's as it should be.
Place the probe.
Didn't even connect it yet.
Look — we need to change the volts-per-cell sweep.
Amplitude is very high here.
Going to have to change it because we won't see.
Here's the oscillogram.
No matter what we measure relative to what, I already showed.
Place it relative to plus here.
Signal remains.
Don't change any settings.
And relative to minus — also don't change any settings.
Signal remains.
Swap this probe around.
No point — because we need this effect specifically at this point, where the break happens at the switch.
Let's do the next measurement.
The yellow channel will hang on one of the bifilars as before.
The oscilloscope measurement will be done relative to the minus of the common wire.
The blue channel will hang at the input.
Plus-minus.
Look — actually the system input is supplied with DC.
Here are the oscillograms.
For now nothing.
0 V supplied.
Applying voltage — now watching.
Watch — the potential on the blue channel is rising.
DC.
Sweep is 10 V per cell.
Now it makes a bit more than one cell.
And the voltage is exactly 17 V here.
Everything matches.
Apply higher — this potential grows.
And on the yellow channel we have a sweep — here it is, 50 V per cell.
That is, we see a classical normal measurement relative to the common point.
Actually DC — here it is, watch the blue channel.
DC.
One more thing — maybe DC doesn't go to the lamp.
Let's measure on the lamp too — does DC go there.
Here I connected the lamp — in that case we looked at 100 W, here I found 200 W.
Got 200 W on it.
Here you see the output and we measure directly — here the probe is on the lamp.
Look — applying voltage, lamp lights up, watch.
Apply — you see potential growing on the lamp, DC, no sags, nothing.
Watch — the lamp's running at the output, hanging there.
Measurement done strictly on DC.
If that weren't the case, I wouldn't post the measurement and calculate efficiency.
It all works.
So don't make stuff up — if you don't know how to measure, I like how I measure, measure yourself.
And here's a small crash test so it's clear that your back EMF will never throw enough onto this cap and that fast.
Look — I apply only 20 V at the input and look how it throws here, 20 V.
Back EMF here can never charge a cap that fast.
Don't look for it there — whoever works on it won't get anything.
Look how fast the cap charges.
And here's a discussion — I liked a comment.
A guy writes — well, you can scoop a barrel out with a bucket, and you can also pour it out all at once.
And the other replies — the barrel is already full.
Absolutely right — the barrel's already full, we need to take the excess.
And about the full barrel.
The system has to accelerate — don't choke it.
Here I showed you how it works directly — 90% efficiency.
The barrel is full and at the right moment we just take the excess.
Look — from the same 20 V.
And imagine — now I'll add 44 V here, what'll happen.
The system needs about 200-300 V at the input — then there's a real festival.
Watch.
Anyway — those who got it got it, the rest can keep building boosters, flybacks and other classical schematics.
Now one more interesting experiment.
Look — I took a neon, now we'll look where this potential is present.
I apply 56 V here at the input and look — will the neon glow.
Touch minus — doesn't light.
Touch plus — doesn't light.
Touch the output — doesn't light, because here's DC, no pulses — already DC on this cap.
Now look what happens on the heat sinks.
By the way, the transistors are isolated from the heat sinks, but the heat sinks are also part of the suction zone in this effect.
Touch — look, the neon glows.
And on the bifilar leads — here.
It's everywhere on the bifilars.
This effect is on each one.
This is what BD didn't show — at his place this thing glows.
And on the common — where we connect — no glow, it goes to the cap.
But if we now disconnect this wire that comes to the cap,
turn it off, pull it out — these pulses come after the diodes.
Naturally, the cap doesn't smooth it here, so the effect is present.
The phenomenon is different.
No need to invent back EMF and the rest.
Real radio amateurs have already done a lot of experiments and written it off.
I talked with them about this.
And no one saw your flybacks in this scheme.
The effect is different.
Moreover — look carefully where you saw back EMF, where it works — where did you ever see back EMF with such width?
It's thin as a needle and decaying after.
This isn't back EMF.
Run the experiment and try.
The schematic is already there for the experiment, everything's available.
I don't know what else you need.
Show a miracle — but I'm not an idiot to show miracles and then have my brain carted off about it.
Anyway, OK, all this is small stuff, what people write here.
I read it and am amazed, as they say.
Now after this clip I'll embed an interesting video.
You've probably seen it many times, and those who haven't — and even those who watched — I'd recommend rewatching several times.
Very interesting material about how this works and what happens.
Where the energy actually goes.
Where electrons and positrons appear, their interaction, what an electron-positron dipole is.
It's time to wake up, time to look facts in the eye — otherwise we'll be a long time getting to success.
Does this effect create a standing wave?
Yes, a standing wave.
It looks like creating a pressure difference.
You select frequencies from the whole spectrum so there are fewer frequencies.
You should say that the frequencies contain energy.
There's less energy in the frequencies between the plates than in the frequencies outside that bombard them.
So the forces aren't balanced.
The force acting from outside is slightly bigger than the force acting from inside, and the plates being bombarded get pushed apart.
So the plates end up being attracted to each other.
Essentially, they get compressed together.
Interesting.
Could you give a definition of a dipole, please?
And tell us how the dipole is destroyed in existing schemes.
Good.
Given the situation we're in now and wanting to extract energy from vacuum — energy we can use to power lamps, motors, supply houses — we need to
find a reaction that can give us a substantial amount of electromagnetic energy from vacuum.
Until 1957 we didn't know for sure about the existence of such a reaction that would be widely accessible.
But from 1957 this became known.
Then the phenomenon of so-called broken symmetry was discovered.
Lee and Yang put forward the hypothesis of its existence in 1956, in the beginning of 1957, in the first half of 1957.
This is very short time for a work to gain world fame.
Publications appeared predicting the discovery of broken symmetry.
We're talking about broken symmetry of the flow of virtual particles in vacuum.
This means that one part of it isn't similar to the other.
Some changes happened in it.
This is what's called broken symmetry.
Moreover, this change should be substantial enough to be observable.
As Lee said when he encountered broken symmetry, something virtual became accessible for observation.
Thus, now we have something measurable, at least theoretically.
Something big enough to be noticed and measured.
Broken symmetry became the magical tool whose existence was proven in 1956-57.
But this hypothesis was so important that it could revolutionize science if proven experimentally.
A very strong experimental physicist immediately joined them, to prove whether it was true or not.
This was so important that everything had to be done very fast, and they succeeded.
In fact, in February 1957 Wu and her colleagues...
Wu recently died... proved it experimentally, in very short time after the hypothesis was put forward.
The influence and consequences of this discovery on physics as a whole were so significant that the Nobel Prize was also awarded unprecedentedly fast.
Lee and Yang received it the same year, in December 1957.
I want to give a full picture of how fast the revolution in science happened and how fast recognition came.
One of the phenomena of broken symmetry — one of those things that transform part of virtual energy into positive or observable energy that can be fixed and measured — was
broken symmetry of opposite charges.
Let's talk about charge.
Charge is a very unusual thing.
We have no absolutely accurate definition of the concept of "charge."
This still isn't a clear concept, but nevertheless we have a series of facts about it, some of which formed back in the 19th century.
Elementary particle physics in the 20th century allowed us to learn much about how charge behaves, how it works and interacts with other things.
If I have a charge in the classical understanding, then this'll be one electron at rest in space.
It's actually not at rest in empty space, as we usually picture, going from the classical concept.
It's located as if in a boiling pot — in a flow of particles that chaotically move and collide with each other.
Very small, tiny photons are absorbed and dropped again, and all that.
Each time the electron absorbs a photon, a tiny increment of its mass is observed, and so on.
This is a boiling pot, and the charge itself is very dynamic.
Essentially, if I place this charge in such a pot, in the empty space we'd better call vacuum, say this electron, a negative charge.
Around it the bubbles with opposite charges will dominate.
That is, here we'll have many positive charges appearing and disappearing at huge speed.
Incredible speed.
If we have opposite charges, then we have what's called force lines in classical physics.
But this isn't yet force.
We have lines of attraction between these opposite charges.
What we have now is broken symmetry of opposite charges, because in the middle there's one charge, and around it a whole screen of bubbles with opposite charges.
If I need to examine this charge with an instrument or measure this charge, I actually can't measure the charge.
I measure it through the screen of charges, which, by the way, is infinite.
And the internal or isolated charge — if I managed to get rid of the screen — is also infinite.
But the difference between them is finite.
Infinity of potentials... infinity.
Yes, they're actually infinite.
Energetically... energetically.
Boundless energy without borders.
Of an isolated set of charges.
This surrounding — or better said, the totality — has two sets of infinite energy.
Various flows of boundless energy.
That is, one single electron contains a huge amount of energy.
Remember these fields and interactions permeate the entire Universe.
They've been present from ancient times and exist everywhere in the Universe.
So, we have a huge amount of charge, and with instruments we can't measure a separate charge inside.
We can only measure the difference we see through the screen of opposite charges.
This difference is presented in classical physics textbooks as the electron charge.
That's what was printed in textbooks.
But classical physics stops here.
The models stop here.
On this difference.
If we talk about energy from vacuum, we need to use more modern knowledge.
We know these processes are much more complex.
And we know that the only reason we have fields in this surrounding is because of broken symmetry, the hypothesis of which was put forward and then proven by scientists who got
the 1957 Nobel Prize.
Now we have various dipoles.
This means there's one charge, and at some distance from it the opposite charge is located, forming a dipole.
This is dipolarity.
Broken symmetry of opposite charges is broken symmetry of dipolarity.
What do you understand by broken symmetry?
Broken symmetry means the object isn't the same as it was before.
It's fed by virtual particles.
Something broke, and the object switched to an observable state, crossed the quantum threshold and became real.
Not all the fish are under water anymore.
Some jumped out from there.
That's the breakthrough?
Yes, that's the breakthrough from vacuum into the real world.
The importance of the broken-symmetry phenomenon is that it lets us do this.
This means that this surrounding we just talked about — one small electron does this.
It constantly absorbs this scattering energy of bubbles — if we can call it that — energy of the virtual state, transforms it into tiny bubbles of additional mass, tiny
increments of mass.
But it grows because the mass is attracted.
It goes from invisible to visible?
Tangible.
Yes, it continues to accumulate increments.
Here's the dm-1 increment that comes from absorption of energy.
At the next absorption it'll be dm-2, where m is the mass of this electron.
At the next absorption it'll already be dm-3.
All this sums up since the mass is attracted.
You add a little and it increases.
It's like deflection on a scale.
What's dm?
dm is the increment.
Increment.
In the process of mass increase, the sum of the increments — by the way, that's integration in math terms.
The electron integrates what would otherwise be disordered energy, since there's no reason for absorbing these particles.
But here they are.
They're ordered in time.
They're absorbed by mass, increasing it.
When the next mass increase happens, mass — as we know — is energy.
The energy in this mass becomes enough to form a photon we can see.
It broke through to the surface and formed a wave that's always pushed out.
Then this totality emits the photon.
Usually a real photon that can be captured on film, recorded on film and taken into account in calculations.
Right after it the next goes, and the next process continues.
One more.
And one more.
These photons.
What do they do when they follow each other in an infinite line, replacing each other?
They form what we call a static field.
Or if we look at the process from the standpoint of potentials — a static process.
Actually it's not static — it's in a stable non-equilibrium state.
That is, we have something that freely emits real energy.
If we don't consider the arrival of energy from vacuum, energy of bubbles, energy of the virtual state, then it seems the law of energy conservation is violated.
But no.
From modern theory we know the system gets energy from virtual particles constantly.
That is, energy comes in one form, and at the output we get energy in a form we can use — standard electromagnetic fields and potentials connected with this
initial totality or initial charge.
This is what Lee and Yang predicted and then proved.
Yes, all correct.
They don't go further and don't say, so the field was created, and so on.
The problem is that the achievement of one section of physics isn't accepted by other sections, and especially not by electrical engineering.
The thing is, for a hundred years the problem of the initial charge — how it forms all these fields and produces energy — wasn't solved.
It was rightfully called the most complex problem of electrodynamics.
If we take the classical approach, it actually was complex because energy didn't come into the system.
But the system provided a constant exit of an energy flow that never interrupts, absolutely free.
In this approach this is a riddle, but that's how it is.
Correct.
Because the law of energy conservation can't be violated.
But in this model no source of this energy was provided, since the presence of the virtual state and the achievements of elementary particle physics as a whole weren't recognized.
Bubbles.
They aren't accounted for in this model.
If they weren't there and the system continued to produce energy, then we'd violate the law of energy conservation in the whole Universe.
But this isn't so.
It constantly gets energy.
The law of energy conservation is very glad it's observed.
The only problem is that we need to understand the energy comes from an unusual source.
But that's the source we're looking for.
Active vacuum.
It provides broken symmetry?
Yes.
Does the electron have mass?
Yes, it does.
Is the photon mass bigger?
No, the photon doesn't have mass from the standard standpoint.
In curved space-time, to be technically accurate, the photon may have what we'd call mass.
But in the standard approach, the photon doesn't have mass.
For a very simple reason.
If I represent space-time as an uncurved plane and curve it, we have a photon.
Say it's emitted as a three-dimensional object with length, width and height.
And I start moving the photon.
The faster it moves, the more energy it has — kinetic energy.
But it also experiences length compression in the direction of movement.
And moving at the speed of light, it reaches zero length.
So I have no mass.
And there's something like a flat plane flying at the speed of light.
This is how an electromagnetic wave is usually represented.
A flat wave, with oscillations in this plane.
But for our purposes — since we need to power something — we have something emitting a huge amount of energy from vacuum.
We made a breakthrough from the Casimir effect.
And no one isolated how these fields form, and didn't connect this with broken symmetry, for the discovery of which Lee and Yang received the Nobel Prize.
Until 2000, when I finally pulled this together into a unified system.
I took scattered information.
I used knowledge from elementary particle physics and found the pieces of information I needed.
I didn't invent anything — just found them and brought them together, like folding puzzle pieces into one picture, and in 2000 I published this work.
That's why the fields are preserved — this generous gift of nature.
Nature gave us an incredible amount of generators of free energy that lawfully and constantly extract energy from vacuum and emit it as real, ready-to-use
electromagnetic energy.
It's already here.
It's called the initial charge, located in this totality.
How much energy can it release?
An unlimited amount of energy.
There are two objects with infinite energy that it works with.
It can work forever.
Charges have existed in the initial mass of the Universe for approximately 13.7 billion years.
They've been emitting energy constantly for 13.7 billion years.
And they haven't depleted.
The process still goes at the same speed.
Around us?
Around us.
Now the problem isn't that we contradict official knowledge.
We don't need to find a mechanism to extract energy from vacuum.
Nature served it to us on a platter.
It gave us this and already does this for us.
Now we need to learn to use it.
We want to collect this exiting flow of energy.
We want to apply power to a larger number of charges to get a larger flow of exiting energy.
We don't want to interfere with the work of charges and the dipole.
Because if we destroy the dipole, if we destroy our picture, erase it — we don't get the energy flow.
Energy is obtained thanks to broken symmetry of opposite charges — the dipole.
If we destroy dipolarity — which we love to do in our generators, each time the dipolarity is destroyed, the flow of energy stops.
If we don't destroy dipolarity, don't break any dipole — if we don't want to close our eyes to all the achievements of elementary particle physics — each existing dipole will produce
energy for another 13.7 billion years.
Can the electrical needs of a household be supplied by vacuum energy?
Yes.
But nature isn't going to give this energy for free.
As soon as you understand the principle of the natural generator nature prepared for use, you need to learn how to use these generators.
But our knowledge about this is pretty rough.
In your understanding, do we need to take this model and compress it or scale it to a large volume?
Yes, correct.
If we add enough electrons or charges to form a strong enough dipole, it'll produce a sufficient amount of energy.
Even if we can extract half, or a tenth, or a thousandth of it.
To fully provide energy.
The energy is already there.
It can be extracted from vacuum, and the extraction mechanism has already been created by nature itself.
We don't need to invent anything anew.
And Nobel laureates Lee and Yang prove this.
And experiments by you and other scientists also confirmed this knowledge.
This is recognized.
But we haven't introduced it into electrical engineering.
We still use 1865 knowledge.
Knowledge from 1880.
We use no knowledge about vacuum.
Let's go further and talk about the practical use of dipoles in power supply systems.
And the destruction of dipoles.
Let's.
For example, consider how power is actually supplied to a usual power supply system.
Because the electrical engineering model correctly assumes that all fields, all potentials consist of these same initial charges, produced by initial charges.
But this model also wrongly assumes that this charge creates energy out of nothing.
So it's very strange that electrical engineers today use a model that assumes that every electromagnetic field, every electromagnetic potential, and every joule of electromagnetic
energy in our Universe freely arises out of nothing.
Magic?
Magic.
I keep my sense of humor.
I sometimes can't hold back my laughter when these people start talking about perpetual motion and the like.
Because the most flagrant way the law of energy conservation is violated is in the books produced by electrical engineering departments, in the views of professors and engineers themselves.
And they don't even know about this.
They don't even ask the question.
There's no single book, as far as I know, that says: here are the basic views and basics of the model of modern electrodynamics, the model of classical electrodynamics we use, like,
for example in electrical engineering, the Maxwell-Heaviside models.
And here are the models that, according to subsequent discoveries in physics, are erroneous.
There's no single such agreement or book that I managed to find.
You can find evidence — outstanding scientists who emphasize this.
Wheeler, Feynman and so on.
There are no force fields in vacuum.
And the models still contain these fields when they aren't there.
This has been known for a hundred years.
The myth about the existence of force fields in vacuum was dispelled in 1887.
Since 1887 the models haven't changed.
And obviously all the views in electrical engineering now, all the models, aren't going to be corrected for another hundred years.
This is fundamentally wrong.
In all models it's assumed that the initial charge appears in some magical way.
The initial charge produces energy out of nothing, according to this model.
No energy comes to the initial charge.
But they can't refuse the idea that energy constantly comes to it.
Why can't they refuse this?
Because it was proven experimentally.
You can create a charge suddenly.
Let me show you.
This point in the lab.
Say I'm so smart — I take this point, or one of the students does this for the demonstration.
Nothing bad in my doing this.
We take some point in the lab, and this'll be zero in our coordinate system.
And whichever point we conduct measurements at, they'll be ideally accurate since this is a thought experiment.
At each point we installed a set of ideal instruments for measuring.
Since I can do measurements conveniently, take the speed of light over one second and convert it to distance.
That's about 300 million meters.
However it goes, let's assume we have ideal measuring instruments.
Now what do I do?
We have a thought experiment.
We can idealize everything.
In our lab a charge suddenly appears.
Actually I can't get it instantly, but now I have an electrical pulse, and we needn't worry about that.
What happens when the charge is formed?
Here, at zero point in our lab, a charge appeared.
After one second the first set of instruments captures readings.
Regardless of the value of the propagating field, the photon flux density at this point — the instruments will show the field strength value, the potential strength.
This instrument suddenly starts to read and won't stop.
It continues to take measurements further, starting from the current moment.
Even after a billion years it'll show the same value.
That happens after one second has passed.
The instrument suddenly started to read, and this'll continue forever.
The field is constantly renewed — it's stable here.
After two seconds the second set of instruments starts to take readings.
The third after three seconds.
Seconds will go by, and instruments installed further away will start to record readings.
Since this is a thought experiment, we placed instruments in the Solar system and beyond its limits.
After a year, the instruments located far beyond the limits of the Solar system suddenly start to record readings.
The readings will stay unchanged as long as the charge is in our lab and we don't destroy it.
Thus, we can easily prove that the energy flow is constant, according to instrument readings.
In real conditions we place instruments much closer to each other, and their number is limited, but this is normal.
Enough to prove the principle.
But it'll work if we manage to do this in real conditions.
Experimentally, we can easily prove that constant energy flow comes from each charge.
Now the question arises — where does this energy come from?
We can integrate.
You know, engineers do this excellently.
They can take instrument readings, integrate the energy density, and calculate the amount of energy at any moment.
It's located in all space, filled with energy.
Of course, energy density falls with distance from the charge — drops as the square for the field and linearly for the potential.
But in any case it won't equal zero across the whole Universe.
Thus, we have huge energy generators — charges, initial charges that extract energy from vacuum.
And all electromagnetic energy, all field energy.
All fields, all potentials arise thanks to these initial charges.
And all this comes from vacuum.
Everything we do involves energy from vacuum.
We call it electromagnetic field energy, electromagnetic potential energy.
And permanent magnets?
Permanent magnets are dipoles.
A magnetic charge we call a pole.
Magnetic pole.
A permanent magnet is a dipole.
The principle of broken symmetry of the dipole also applies to it.
A permanent magnet participates in this process constantly.
But if the field is absolutely stationary, you can take measurements again and again, and the readings will stay the same at the same point.
You may think it's static.
But it can't be static, since this is a flow, and you can't make a photon stand still in space.
In free space the photon moves at the speed of light.
Otherwise we'll have to give up the theory of relativity, including special relativity.
We need to forget about this.
It's not true.
It moves.
But the thing is — as Tom Van Flandern emphasized — there are two ways of understanding statics.
And he cited a beautiful example with a waterfall.
If the waterfall was truly static — it looks static when it's perfect.
Suppose it's perfect and looks beautiful because at any moment it's the same.
No single element is disturbed, but inside it there's fast movement.
It flows, one part following another.
They constantly replace each other.
So such a waterfall isn't completely static.
A fully static one would be a frozen waterfall.
An unfrozen waterfall is what thermodynamics calls a stationary flow.
A system in a non-equilibrium state.
This is when energy constantly comes in and constantly goes out at a constant rate.
The state of such a system is defined by the term "constant non-equilibrium state."
In the case of Van Flandern's unfrozen waterfall — which is almost a full analogy of a static field — we see its non-equilibrium stationary state.
Can we prove this?
Of course.
Thanks to our model we examined, where energy is extracted from vacuum.
In it, a constant flow of energy in a special virtual state passes into the charge that absorbs this flow and transforms it into visible photon energy that it constantly emits at a constant
rate.
The charge absorbs energy at a constant rate, transforms and emits it at a constant rate.
And this is a non-equilibrium stationary state in pure form, in which energy is extracted from vacuum and transformed into real energy.
We don't need to transform it ourselves.
I don't need to transform energy from vacuum into real visible energy.
Nature already does this.
Every charge in the Universe already does this.
Every dipole already does this.
That is, the EMF just uses this energy.
Everything we do with electrical energy uses what the charges produce by extracting energy from vacuum.
All energy in any electromagnetic circuit is the result of dipole formation in that circuit.
Do you understand what I mean?
Charges form dipoles in space, according to the charge model accepted in modern physics.
Everything dipoles do is extracting energy from vacuum.
And this has nothing to do with rotating a generator shaft.
Why do we rotate the generator shaft?
First, let's look at why we need to rotate the shaft at all.
Here we have a wonderful generator.
Since we're smart, the shaft will be rotated by, say, a hydroelectric station turbine, or something of that kind.
So we don't have to pay for this.
Only a madman would agree to pay for this.
But otherwise we'd have to burn coal, heat boilers and produce steam so steam turbines could rotate the shaft.
But for this we'd have to pay a lot.
But our generator has a shaft, and we need to constantly rotate it.
In electrical engineering we absorbed, you might say, with mother's milk, the concept that the mechanical energy gotten by rotating the shaft is transferred from the outputs to external circuits
and powers all the loads in it.
But this isn't so.
This is completely not so.
First, inside the generator I can do nothing with mechanical energy.
It won't give me even a watt in the transmission line.
A transmission line can't transfer mechanical energy.
That is, I need to transform it into a different form inside the generator that would act on charges.
In any case, all energy comes from charges.
If I need an energy flow, I separate the charges and get a dipole.
If I do this with a rotating field — the concept introduced by Tesla — if I force the rotor inside this generator to rotate, I produce a rotating magnetic field.
Now all the energy that came to the generator as mechanical energy transforms into energy of the rotating magnetic field.
What does it do?
It doesn't go to the transmission line.
It acts on the charges inside the generator.
It forces positive charges to move in one direction, and negative ones in the opposite.
Thus, it gives us dipolarity at the generator outputs.
That is, it's a rough attempt to artificially intensify broken symmetry.
Correct.
Creating broken symmetry of the dipole by means of forming a dipole.
We use all the magnetic field energy only to separate charges.
In big schemes this is rather hard to do so the dipole forms, because in front and behind there's a huge amount of electrons that need to be separated to form the dipole.
But suppose you pay for this?
You pay for energy bringing the generator shaft into motion, to separate charges and form the dipole.
Then, if you don't allow anything to happen with the dipole, energy will flow from the generator forever.
Why can I claim this?
This isn't a perpetual motion machine.
As soon as the dipole appears, energy is constantly extracted from vacuum.
Nature was very kind.
This is already proven by elementary particle physics.
But this knowledge isn't accepted by electrical engineering.
There's not even a concept of "active vacuum."
Where could we extract energy from?
It's simply not considered.
In electrical engineering it's considered that it comes from the energy of the generator shaft.
But that's not so.
In any case, as soon as a dipole forms, it starts to interact with the turbulent vacuum.
We get a rather big charge in a big generator.
And the flow is also big.
A lot of energy comes from here.
So, here's an energy flow with thousands of volts.
For example, thousands of volts going along this line.
Transmission lines to power electrical systems.
A strange thing happens.
Two people who discovered the energy flow — came up with the concept of energy flow in space that didn't exist in Maxwell's time...
Maxwell died in 1879, and this concept appeared in the 1880s, and was introduced simultaneously, independently from each other, by Poynting and Heaviside.
An interesting thing happens.
A small part of the energy flow is located around the conductors — the conductors, on the contrary, have conductivity, like a waveguide, that allows transfer of the energy flow to where needed.
That's its function.
The energy around the wire and the various charges of their fields located inside the wire interact with each other, and part of the external energy penetrates into the wires.
Very little energy penetrates there.
Quite little.
Very little — possibly up to a ten-trillionth part.
This part that penetrates into the wire was considered by Poynting — he didn't study any other energy except what penetrates into the wire.
He didn't study processes by which energy comes out of the wire.
And a strange thing happens.
Heaviside discovered that a lot of energy is lost when all the energy that can penetrate into the wire penetrates in the whole system.
This is much more than what penetrates inside.
But energy is still present outside the wire.
But it won't interact with anything since it's in vortex form.
Dissipation of vortex flow in flat space-time equals zero.
It doesn't interact with anything.
Usually most of the space-time we live in is relatively flat.
Thus, we get an amazing thing.
This generator produces and sends along wires a flow of energy trillions of times — maybe even ten trillion times — bigger, most of which is completely unused, than we spend on
rotating the generator shaft.
This isn't surprising as soon as we understand that the source of energy is vacuum, not the mechanical energy we use to rotate the shaft.
But if you don't understand this — if in your view all this energy is what we apply to the shaft — then for you this is unimaginable.
Because in such case it seems we get energy out of nothing.
There's no source of this additional energy.
Vacuum hasn't yet appeared.
Understand?
The concept of active vacuum hasn't reached you yet.
A 19th-century concept.
Where then did they know there was energy?
Heaviside knew this.
Poynting didn't have to think about this since he considered only the dissipating component.
He never researched any other flows or components there.
He considered all the energy that penetrated the wire.
But he was off by ninety degrees in the flow direction, which Heaviside corrected.
But Heaviside was an amazing person.
He had outstanding abilities.
These are his equations that we today call Maxwell's equations.
He simplified them and came up with the notation for them.
But he also didn't study at university.
And many mathematicians and other scientists were against him.
He came up with the Heaviside function and many other outstanding things.
At first he was hated, and then his discoveries were accepted and started being used.
Heaviside was a loner, almost a hermit.
He died a poor starving hermit in a terribly small poor apartment.
He starved terribly.
But at the end he got recognition from the Royal Academy and other institutions for his outstanding contribution to science.
Heaviside discovered this additional component, but he didn't dare to talk about it openly.
This soon reached Lorenz, who in the 1890s was the greatest scientist in the field of electricity.
Lorenz understood the works of both.
But even the great Lorenz had limitations.
If he had tried to openly say that yes, each of our generators produces a huge number of times more energy than we spend on it, they'd have tied him up, put him on a train and put him out of
town.
That is, he couldn't do it so as not to lose his reputation and position.
No one would have done so.
If you have a problem you can solve, but the science that would allow this hasn't yet appeared, then you'll be crucified for recognizing it.
And the best way out is to exclude the problem, which is what Lorenz did.
Lorenz taught us to take the energy flow vector as a whole, integrated into a sphere that could be drawn around any point you choose.
This allowed a wonderful thing to be done.
Let's draw a sphere.
This is a round ball.
Some amount of energy comes here.
A small part of it dissipates, and the main part passes further.
If we subtract the energy that came out of the sphere from the energy that came into it, we get the dissipated energy — the Poynting component.
And every electrical engineer was taught this trick.
But its real goal isn't that this is actually worth doing — but to get rid of the problem they refused to solve for over a hundred years, the solution of which would help
get huge amounts of free energy from vacuum.
The question now is whether we can actually use this other component.
By the way, the dissipating Poynting flow now corresponds to all standard concepts.
We power loads.
We collect a large amount of energy and dissipating energy flow along the path of these electrons' movement in the flow.
But the entire current going by the wire in this direction returns back in this direction.
So the voltage along the whole loop from positive output to negative output of the generator is the same, but opposite in sign to the voltage of the current going in the other direction.
First, this is direct EMF pushing current forward.
And second, reverse EMF pushing current in the reverse direction.
To force it to go against the voltage, we need to do work.
And when you do this, the charges doing the work will destroy the dipole.
Reverse current equals reverse current at equal voltage.
This confirms the symmetric Lorenz gauge, according to which direct EMF equals reverse EMF, and half of the energy you get from the external circuit you should use for nothing other than
destroying the external source and its ability to extract energy from vacuum and give it to you.
So we destroy the dipole.
Energy comes to the load, and we destroy the dipole.
Half of the energy destroys the dipole, and part of the remaining energy goes out of the circuit as leaks and losses.
That is, less energy comes to the load.
Thus, we spend less on powering the load than on destroying the dipole.
To restore the dipole, we need to do at least the same amount of work to separate the charges.
Apply brute force.
Brute force.
That is, here we need to apply the same amount of energy — if your generator has 100% efficiency — to separate charges, restore the dipole and restore the inflow of energy from vacuum.
This amount of energy is more than what's supplied to the load.
Efficiency is defined as the ratio of useful energy reaching the load to the total energy applied at the input of the circuits.
In this case, I'll always have to spend more than reaches the load, so efficiency will be less than one.
The ratio of these values will be less than one.
That is, we specifically developed a system — a closed loop that equates direct and reverse EMF currents.
And we leave the generator connected to the circuit so that we can actually destroy the dipole in the generator and the source of energy faster than we feed the load.
So to constantly restore dipolarity and get energy from vacuum, we need to rotate the generator shaft, but we'll always apply more energy to the generator than reaches
the load.
This is the absurdity of the modern electric power systems we've developed and built over the last 100 years.
What powers the load?
You still have a load and reverse current.
Correct.
But not necessarily.
There's no such load by its nature that would say you don't need to use a closed loop.
Tesla switched to single-wire schemes.
Correct.
Supplying a pulse to a capacitor on the other end of the circuit, and then back.
In your vision of the future, it's assumed that we'll develop energy sources that extract energy from vacuum.
How does it fit into the closed schemes of energy use?
The first requirement for getting an electromagnetic system with super-unity efficiency, the first requirement is refusing the closed system that guarantees you need to apply
more energy than reaches the load.
You need to refuse this — it can be done several ways.
The load stays the same.
The load is connected in series.
Of course, no problem.
Good.
If you, of course, aren't going to power the load with negative energy, you need to develop a load that can be powered by negative energy, and then the load will not only power itself, but also
give you energy from vacuum.
Use the current, or what?
Positive energy.
Right, positive energy.
Then a load is a load, and impedance is impedance.
Yes.
Why does it happen that we still need to power the load?
It's all current.
And we still need to return the current back.
No.
Good.
The only way to return current is to use it again.
By the way, let's talk about current.
Current isn't at all like water flow in a pipe.
It's all not so.
Electrons in wires are free — they constantly jump into other atoms, jump back and forth.
This is called the Drude electron gas.
Drude discovered it around 1900.
In a conductor at every moment we have an electron gas consisting of jumping electrons.
And when we send this energy flow along the conductor, this flow passes through all these charges.
It moves almost at the speed of light.
If everything was ideal, it would move at the speed of light — but we have inductance, capacitance, and so on, so its speed is less than light, with which real potential and real
energy flow along the conductor.
The electron itself doesn't move that way — only on average.
In a circuit the electron moves along the conductor at about 10 centimeters per hour.
Per hour!
About 10 centimeters along the conductor because it has to jump, and we have electron drift.
On average it shifts, jumps, then shifts further.
This is drift statistics formed by electrons.
The electron can't simply move along the conductor because the electrons ahead prevent this, throwing it back.
Everything should be in interaction.
Jumps, collisions, and drift along the conductor at about 10 centimeters per hour.
This is the actual electron speed in longitudinal movement in the conductor.
Meanwhile the energy moves practically at the speed of light.
Thus, one of the ways to go from this...
Say you have a good copper conductor.
The reaction of electrons to current after voltage transfer in it is so fast we can consider it instantaneous.
Different people cite different data, but it's about 10 to the minus 16 seconds.
This is very short time.
Forget about measuring the distance between when you apply voltage and current starts to flow.
That is, effectively.
In normal circuits we assemble with copper wires and the like, current starts flowing immediately after we apply voltage.
And the dipole is always destroyed.
Here's voltage, here's current.
But suppose we slowed the process.
We briefly froze the electron, literally for a millisecond.
A thousandth of a second.
This is a pretty long time for something moving at the speed of light.
300 million meters per second.
And you delayed the start of movement by 300 thousand meters — understand — that could pass before electron movement starts.
Simply delaying them for one millisecond.
It would create potential in the whole scheme with a very small, near-zero current.
If you assemble a device that automatically provides this delay in the conductor, this can be done.
If you make a conductor from an aluminum alloy with 2% iron content, you can get a current delay of about one millisecond.
You can calculate everything and measure the iron percentage, and all that, to get a delay of one millisecond.
We need an alloy.
We need a good alloy so nothing prevents the particles.
If we have a good alloy with 2% iron, take a small content.
We can make a conductor with a delay of approximately one millisecond between when voltage is applied — even if you applied it very sharply — and when any significant current
starts flowing.
The delay is about one millisecond.
During this millisecond, if your circuit is no longer than 300 thousand meters or 300 kilometers — because no one uses circuits of such length — you can create potential in the circuit without help of current,
electric energy, or work.
Energy is free.
Potential energy is free.
It doesn't cost a penny.
It comes from vacuum thanks to dipole formation, and remains with you for free.
You only have to pay when you need to do work on dissipating energy and changing its form.
We'd want to create potential in this circuit, and then disconnect the generator from it before current flows.
We can do this.
It's simpler than simple.
You just need to find a metallurgical lab that would make this conductor.
Then you'd have to buy a lot of it, and it would be terribly expensive.
We figured this out and weren't ready to pay 30-40 thousand dollars to make this conductor — if, of course, you don't need to make a lot of this alloy.
But if you needed it for a research program, or you have your own metallurgical lab, then of course you can make them and run experiments with them.
So what do we do?
We very fast connect the generator.
Immediately apply voltage and create potential in the whole scheme.
And current, meanwhile, hasn't come into it.
It tries to pass into the circuit, but the iron doesn't let it.
Delays its movement.
At this moment we suddenly disconnect the circuit from the generator, from the source of dipolarity.
Instead of it we place a semiconductor, a diode, so current passes only in this direction.
Now our circuit with all its capacitance and potentials.
We can run experiments to optimize it by connecting different devices.
There's not that much energy in it — at least half of it will dissipate in the load.
It'll be released and power the load for free.
You spend only a small amount on connecting the generator, and don't pay for energy.
Meanwhile, the dipole in the generator isn't destroyed.
You can connect it again and again and again and again.
Practically you'll lose part of this energy, so you'll still have to rotate the generator shaft a bit.
But the efficiency coefficient will automatically be more than one.
You'll spend more energy powering the load than rotating the generator shaft.
This is really feasible.
For example, if the Department of Energy seriously approaches innovative research, this can be done by some of the national labs, but actually none of them will do this.
This is the last thing they'd want to deal with.
They'll deal with thermonuclear synthesis, fuel cells, burning coal and utilizing waste, and similar things.
The last thing they'll do is research that'll change electrical engineering.
We still use a model that's over 100 years old, long outdated — but nevertheless it's defended instead of changed.
As scientists should act when experiments prove the invalidity of the current model — by scientific procedure the model should be changed, not the experiments criticized, as
happened with cold fusion.
Don't deny them, and don't keep doing business the old way, because eventually we may bankrupt the nation, because all they need is energy cost.
But all you need to do for creating potential in static mode — disconnect the generator so the circuit comes alive, make it dynamic, and then use the energy it would get for
free.
But our engineers are taught that the static field is useless.
But it's the most valuable thing we have.
It's a pure energy flow.
Stationary flow.
Yes, stationary flow.
Use this flow for free, from a source containing a dipole.
And don't destroy the source.
That's a dozen recommendations combined into one when using free energy.
Don't destroy the initial dipolarity, because then you destroy the source extracting energy from vacuum.
You just didn't know about this before.
A discussion between researcher US Army retired Lieutenant Colonel Ken Moore, physicist-mathematician David Clemens, and executive producer Tony Cradoc.
Many different devices or elements may appear that'll be designed to do the same task.
I don't want to say this is the only way.
Yes, this is the basic approach worth thinking about.
It's fundamentally different and not at all like the traditional approach to electrical engineering.
Here you have a positive and negative energy source.
What does the controller do?
It provides a periodic signal and a timer.
It closes this switch and applies power in this circuit.
When the switch is closed, the capacitor charges with energy from the generator.
But this happens so fast that current doesn't get to flow in the circuit.
Here we'll put an ammeter.
It should show zero.
Before current flows in the circuit, this switch opens, and the controller opens this switch.
Then we can use all this energy to power the load.
This process repeats constantly.
It does this constantly.
This is a type of DC-to-DC converter.
Got it.
The difference is that
a traditional scheme is exactly the same, but it doesn't have a switch system.
It's single-phase.
If you want, here you can have a switch closing and opening the circuit.
Now you see what you get.
When you apply power to the load, you'll have losses connected with back EMF.
So you won't get super-unity.
You do this for this circuit too.
Dr. David Clemens.
When you open the switch, not letting current come into the circuit before you charge the initial device so nothing could eat or destroy the source.
Yes, all correct.
Correct time calculation is very important here.
You need to organize it so the cap can absorb energy fast enough to turn off the dipole before current appears here.
If you don't turn off this part of the circuit, you'll end up with this scheme.
Clear.
Almost the same, except that the cap becomes the load.
But you don't want to allow this, so you need to organize timing.
We know one... no, two ways to do this.
First — use a capacitor.
John uses this method.
The other way — use a coil made of material that lengthens relaxation time.
Relaxation time is the time we talked about — during which after switch closure no current flows in the circuit, and then you open this switch and turn on the second part of the scheme.
Energy is accumulated here, and you close this switch.
Now you use the accumulated energy to power the load.
Those are the two phases I talked about.
And if this was a coil, then the winding would be made from aluminum alloy with 2% iron.
Yes, we'll install a timing sensor for this coil.
You published this work in 1992?
You know?
Good.
That's why I'm here.
The winding would be made from an alloy of 98% aluminum and 2% iron.
This would give you about a millisecond of relaxation time, which is actually quite much.
What would the wires in your circuit be made of?
I don't mean the coil winding, but the wires connecting devices in the circuit.
The wires can be copper.
Got it.
And the coil will be made from an aluminum-iron alloy.
That's all you need.
But manufacturers say the alloy needs to be made with inert gas.
This is a pretty complex procedure.
Yeah, it's not so simple.
In a usual lab it won't be made just like that.
That's how this is done.
And the scheme is very simple if you understand the concepts.
That's what Tom tried to work with.
You need to change your way of thinking to switch from such schemes to such, with two phases.
We're taught to do these.
That's been the case for more than 100 years.
And physics... you see, when they created this model, for the time this was the most modern information.
Special relativity hadn't appeared yet.
The Drude electron gas wasn't known yet.
Yes, and the electron itself hadn't been discovered.
People didn't know about the existence of the electron.
Then the atom was represented as a ball with no structure.
That's how it was shown in models.
But it was clear the atom had energy.
Correct.
All particles have energy.
But the deeper understanding of physics we have now wasn't there.
In those times if we found ourselves there, we couldn't have thought up anything better, and possibly would have done only worse, because they then created a clear specialized system.
So in your own work they were based on practical knowledge.
Correct.
They were based on various energy phenomena and created theoretical models explaining these phenomena.
What I did was study two things.
I started in science at a time when a lot of research was being done in physics, but most of it wasn't being implemented, wasn't extracted from the huge volume of works that
was done.
No one ever talked on this topic.
People say "ah, yes, I read about this."
But that knowledge wasn't used to redo the model.
I was lucky that the physics works were accessible.
If you decide to do research, you can dig through and collect this information — it's there.
But it isn't collected together, applied to electrical engineering, and used to advance that field.
One more advantage I had — I was lucky to work with independent inventors who managed to assemble working devices.
Floyd Sweet, Howard Johnson, Frank Golden, people of this kind.
I worked with inventors who actually had working models.
They ran lab experiments with these devices, and they worked.
Sometimes it was hard as hell to understand what happens, and developing and building models took years.
But these experiments allowed us to look at the phenomena in practice.
If you have a set of these phenomena plus certain knowledge needed to build a model, easy — you take this theoretical knowledge and compare it to the experimental results, which
act as a filter for that knowledge.
This is the scientific method.
At least, before it was exactly this.
Have you found anything new and useful on this topic since the discovery of broken symmetry?
Broken symmetry is now widely used in physics.
Are there any modern works on this topic?
Yes, of course.
One after another, new works appear about symmetry and broken symmetry.
There are millions of works.
Are there new discoveries equal in importance?
New discoveries tend to be understandable only to the initiated.
For example, you've now started asking such questions.
How, in what aspect should we consider reality?
I mean from the standpoint that interests you.
Then yes.
For example, time is now seriously being researched.
What does it represent?
Time can be used as energy.
Time is similar to atomic energy.
It has the same energy density as mass when you convert it.
If you want to develop this aspect, you can take a small period of time and convert it to energy — this small tiny piece of time gives you a huge amount of
energy.
It can be electromagnetic.
One more path we'll eventually go down.
One more conclusion that pushes us — the study of both positive and negative energy, and further straight to Dirac space and Holes before they turn into positrons.
This pushes you to the main question because every energy conservation law is a symmetry.
Understand?
Every time you encounter a violation of symmetry, it's a violation of an energy conservation law — meaning, if you look at the works of Michael Leyton, we now have no structures that
would allow us to reach this level.
But Leyton provided them to us in the late 90s.
If we use object-oriented geometry and the best theoretical methods of grouping, we discover that violation of symmetry at one level doesn't lose all this knowledge, as we always
assumed.
That what happens in nature, knowledge is preserved at some level.
But on a new level in the hierarchy, symmetry is created.
The initial charge fully fits into this concept.
You violate symmetry at a lower level in the virtual state.
You automatically create symmetry at the new level.
A new conservation law at the observable state level of electromagnetic field energy, electromagnetic potential energy, and so on.
And this works.
So we developed a new geometry we can use to replace the old 1872 geometry.
If we use Leyton's more modern object-oriented geometry — Michael Leyton — we can understand many things, for example the problem of initial charge and so on.
This is one more fundamental breakthrough we couldn't make before.
Leyton's work is actively applied in robotics and other fields.
His postulates work even when old Euclidean geometry can't solve the problem.
This is successful development, well proven experimentally.
But no one yet applied it to studying initial charge in electrodynamics.
But possibilities for its application are huge.
All I did was point at it.
And youth, postgraduates writing PhD theses, young professors should develop this problem.
This is a whole field not yet studied.
The Department of Energy should pay close attention to it.
But they don't do this.
They don't even know what this is because it isn't what they're working on.
And not what they planned.
A big organization is like a big heavy ship.
You can't turn it instantly.
It goes full steam on its course, and to turn, it needs quite a lot of time.
The same is true for all big heavy organizations that change course very slowly.
Sometimes excessively slowly.
It can be changed, but it's always youth that does this.
This is well known, and many scientists say that most scientific discoveries are made by young people.
Einstein was a young Swiss clerk working in the patent office when he came up with relativity, and so on.
What's funniest is that we can change science, even if slowly, only by reaching out to youth and giving them knowledge.
Then they'll come and look up references.
They can make the needed changes, fine-tune everything, accurately model — and they'll give us new technology and new science.
You said time can be used to extract energy.
Yes.
I said it and I say it.
It's not complex when you have special relativity.
When you use speed, you convert some amount of time into energy — kinetic energy.
Remember, you need to learn to think within a model that uses only one basic unit — energy.
Time is energy, a function of energy, like mass.
Mass as energy doesn't surprise us.
The atomic bomb appeared, relativity, E equals MC squared.
Even a humanities student knows this today.
But at the time it was shocking.
It was unbelievable.
People said only 10-12 people in the whole world understood relativity.
That's how they put it at the time.
But in subject courses this is normal.
If young people understand this, knowledge spreads.
And now millions of people perceive this knowledge as self-evident.
We're at the stage where we need to make changes of this kind.
We can get energy from time.
Take a bit of time, use it and get much energy.
We can improve many electrical devices and power systems.
Create a better model, eliminate errors, and then we'll have at our disposal all the energy from vacuum.
A huge amount of energy.
We'll have this additional huge component we now ignore — from each generator, accumulator, and all the rest — accessible-for-use Heaviside component.
This is a rich reserve of energy.
If we can quickly force country leadership to learn the terms innovative research and innovative science, and perceive them as a basic concept, use them to designate
funded research programs in this direction, and give young scientists freedom.
We have many qualified young specialists with excellent training.
Magnificent mathematicians, magnificent theorists, magnificent experimenters.
We now have more young scientists than ever in the country's history.
And we use these cadres incorrectly.
Completely incorrectly.
We drive everyone under pressure and force them to think stereotypically.
They're forced to compete for money when studying in postgraduate programs, participating in programs and writing doctoral works.
We talked about packages of programs funded from above.
You can't choose your research field.
It's already chosen for you.
Electrical engineering or physics department faculties at leading universities don't sit and discuss what they'd want to research.
They consider what they can get — some funded projects — and what they're ordered to do.
And then, maybe, something remains for what they'd want to do.
What's now happening actually suppresses diversity.