Hi everyone!
Happy Radio Day, everyone.
One way or another, anyone who's ever soldered something can consider themselves part of this holiday.
It sometimes happens that in everyday life or for experiments you need some little thing — ideally simple, that can be made quickly, that raises voltage.
In particular, I needed a circuit like this for electronic ignition.
The electronic ignition board itself switches via a coil like this.
But for successful switching I needed to apply 70 volts to the primary winding of this coil.
And the on-board power is 12 volts, so I have to build a converter like this.
But I decided right away that my converter will be not only at 70 volts — I marked a tap for that — but I'll also do the full 220 volts, so on the road I could charge a mobile
phone or light up a 220-volt lamp.
You can also charge laptops and other stuff.
So, the task is set — now we just have to settle on the schematic.
I stopped at this schematic solution, on the pretty common IR2153 chip.
In the radio-amateur world it's been nicknamed "Irka" for a long time.
The chip has proven itself well, but you have to be careful here.
There are IR2153 chips, and there's the same abbreviation with a D suffix.
For this converter we need specifically the IR2153.
The chip with the D suffix has a diode in the package between pins 1 and 8.
These solutions, on the contrary, aren't designed for step-up converters but for step-down ones.
On a half-bridge or bridge basis — if you use two control chips for a bridge.
So at purchase, pay attention so there's no D suffix here.
If you have lab gear — power supplies, oscilloscope and other equipment — you'll find it quite easy to tune this circuit, and an experienced radio amateur handles it without
problems.
But if you decided to just build a converter for everyday needs and you have no equipment, that's actually not a problem.
I'll show you how to do it.
We'll follow a few rules.
First basic rule.
Assemble the control side with the transistors, without connecting the step-up transformer itself.
And start it up — check mounting, and startup is mandatory.
Connect a 12 V lamp from 10 to 21 W in series in the power path.
If on startup the lamp glows or lights up, immediately turn off and understand that an error was made somewhere in the circuit.
If the lamp doesn't light, then you can connect the transformer next and check with it.
I recommend starting through a lamp because usually at home there's some power source.
Usually it's the same battery that'll power the converter.
If you don't put a lamp at the input, this thing might blow very fast.
It'll be frustrating and discourage any further desire from a beginner to deal with electronics.
To start checking the circuit without instruments, we need to solder a lamp in series with the power.
And take two more lamps that'll serve as the load for these transistors.
They'll be connected instead of these windings.
Check our circuit for errors.
Connect the minus terminal of the power to minus, plus through the lamp to plus.
You can notice the circuit is discharging now — visible that a small spark slips through here.
See in practice — this is the electrolytics charging.
And the lamp doesn't light up.
We can rotate the variable resistor, and as you can see, the lamp doesn't light in any mode.
This confirms we already assembled the circuit correctly, and most likely it'll work.
Now we should check whether the switches work.
Now we'll solder lamps and check.
Lamps soldered — meaning lamps are now connected instead of these windings.
The middle point the lamps connect to is this lead.
It corresponds to this plus power wire.
That is, this point.
Before applying power, set the resistor slider roughly in the middle position.
That'll be about 30-40 kHz.
And apply power to the input.
As you can see, the lamp doesn't light — nothing happens.
Checking the first transistor.
This is its lead.
This is from its drain.
These black wires are from the transistor drains.
Checking.
You see the lamp glows.
The transistor works in operating mode.
Now check the second transistor.
The lamp also glows.
All normal.
With a dual-beam oscilloscope we can check the following.
First we look at the signal at these points.
On the FET gates.
We need to confirm the circuit works correctly.
And that there's so-called dead time between control signals.
Dead time.
That is, time when the controls don't overlap.
Apply power to the input.
Watching the controls.
You can play with frequency.
Watch.
The limit is somewhere up to 100 kHz.
And the minimum is 12.8 kHz.
We're interested in operation from 20 kHz.
Let's stop at about 30 kHz.
And look.
The signal is rectangular.
Now we check for the presence of dead time.
Offset the signals from each other.
And observe that there are actually pauses between the work of one arm and the other.
You can pay attention to the flat front.
The transistor-opening front.
This is the work of the built-in internal drivers through the resistor on the transistor gate.
Next is gate capacitance discharge.
It's steeper.
Falls through the 1 kΩ resistor.
Normal signal.
It'll work.
Now we'll look at the switch operation under load.
We'll look at the lamps at these points.
On the transistor drains.
I connected the probes at these points.
You can see they're on the lamps.
The measurement is done relative to the common wire.
The oscilloscope common is on the minus of the power source.
Apply power.
You see — the load works.
And what does this oscillogram tell us?
If we look at the oscillogram on the lamps, we see that operation happens with overlap.
This is a normal oscillogram because don't forget that the FET inverts on voltage.
So the switch operation will be in this zone when voltage drops to zero.
Now I'll come back.
The switch opens, voltage drops.
The switch operates and closes.
We can see — here's the first switch working, a pause, and here the second switch.
On this load we've verified the circuit works correctly.
You can sweep through the frequency range and check that dead time is preserved.
This suits us.
Next step.
Circuit checked — it's working, runs correctly.
And move on to the step-up transformer.
Say I took ferrite, a ring, and wound the secondary winding on it.
The step-up turn count is picked individually.
There are programs you can use to calculate it, but at home we won't bother with that.
We wound the winding, connected it, checked the voltage at the output with a multimeter.
If we're happy, leave it.
If not, then add more turns until you reach the target.
And wind the primary winding.
The primary winding is wound all in one direction.
The same turn count per arm.
With a tap from the middle.
Don't forget that the whole winding goes in one direction — because from inexperience you might wind in different directions, and then the converter will blow up.
I assembled the circuit, connected a 15 W load at 220 V.
And here I should explain one important point.
Even after you've verified the circuit works, don't disconnect this lamp during the first startups with the step-up transformer.
Because switch operation on lamps — on active resistance — is completely different from when the switch works on a reactive load.
That is, on a coil.
Let me show you visually.
Apply power.
As we thought.
We don't need a big core for the power.
Our loads are small.
Phone charging, some low-power lamp.
At 20 W.
Apply power.
Here you see — the lamp lit.
At the input.
But the load barely glows.
What's going on?
You can make a major mistake here.
You need to look at the signs of what's happening.
First, you need to touch the heat sink and the switches.
You'll see the heat sink is heating up strongly.
Plus the core itself is heating up strongly.
If there weren't a limiting lamp here, smoke would come from this core.
And the switches might have blown.
Because in this situation, this core has entered saturation.
Saturation is an unpleasant operating mode for the ferrite core.
Turning off because it's already heated up strongly.
A mode in which the core loses the property of remagnetizing.
Since our circuit doesn't allow regulation of the control pulse duration.
Which is actually the duration of switch opening when working on the load.
Then we can't pick optimal parameters for this core by adjusting duration.
Even increasing turn count or changing operating frequency won't lead anywhere.
There's one way out — change the core of the step-up transformer itself.
Until the circuit starts correctly.
For this circuit I picked ferrite, also of the 2000 brand like this, but you can see its dimensions.
It's slightly larger by outer diameter, and larger inside.
But the main thing to be guided by isn't the diameters but the core's cross-section.
If this magnetic core has a cross-section of 9 by 9 mm, then this one has a cross-section of 10 by 13 mm.
And only such ferrite is the minimum possible core for this circuit to work correctly.
Also note one more important point.
You can check whether your core is suitable for this circuit only with the secondary winding present.
If you wind the primary winding on the core without the secondary, it'll work.
And may create the impression that this core is suitable.
But as soon as you wind the secondary on it, it'll also enter saturation.
So you have to check exclusively with at least several tens of turns of the secondary winding on the core.
So, I installed the step-up transformer with a magnetic core of larger cross-section.
And now we'll test it.
Pay attention to how this load will glow now.
And pay attention to how the spiral of the limiting lamp will heat up.
If in that experiment we connected and the load barely glowed while the lamp lit immediately, then look in this case.
You see — the lamp doesn't heat up immediately, and the load shines much brighter.
This confirms the circuit has already started.
And you can hear the step-up transformer working.
Since we need the system to work inaudibly, we move its frequency into the inaudible range.
Here.
And the system runs quietly.
Now consumption is 13 V, 0.9 A.
And now we can already check how the system behaves with a direct connection.
You see the lamp shines at full brightness and the system works.
Now I'll show a small nuance that many aren't familiar with.
Pay attention to this capacitor.
1 µF at 50 V, ceramic.
Which is at pin 8, directly next to the chip itself.
On the board it's here.
Very close.
Its presence is mandatory because ceramic capacitors release charge faster than electrolytics.
This improves the gate-opening system — that is, it saturates the gate capacitance faster.
And the built-in drivers in the chip can open the switches more sharply.
Since the switch opens more sharply, its switching time is much shorter.
So the heat released in the switch tends to a minimum.
Now we can check the circuit on a more serious load.
In this case I'll use a 60 W load since my lab supply delivers 5 A maximum.
Now I'll show how to tune the output for the load with turn count.
Put it at the input directly and look — the lamp's lit.
Now consumption is 4 A at 13 V.
In this mode on a small load, you should run the converter for about 20 minutes.
To check the thermal mode of the switches.
The switches shouldn't heat up strongly.
With a heat sink like this, there practically shouldn't be any heating.
Maybe a bit above room temperature at such a load.
You need to test and observe the converter.
After this time, if you've confirmed everything works, you can move to bigger loads.
Now let's also measure the voltage on the load.
For this we need a multimeter.
So we see we now have 195 V on the load.
There's a sag — meaning we have 5 turns per arm now.
If there's a sag, we need to reduce the turn count.
We saw in the previous measurement that there was a sag on the supply voltage.
So to raise the voltage on the lamp, we have two options.
Either add turns to the secondary winding or reduce the primary turn count.
With the primary winding you need to work carefully — remove one turn at a time.
I had 5 turns, now I made 4.
And observe — apply power.
And we see 230 V on the lamp.
I only removed one turn.
Now consumption has gone up — our converter has reached the 60 W load power.
Here's the build I ended up with.
The step-up transformer is mounted with a screw to the heat sink through a cardboard gasket.
I settled on 5.5 turns for the primary.
Here it is — the white wire.
Installed a regular diode bridge — 4 diodes and reservoir cap.
Also a discharge resistor of 820 kΩ at 1 W.
It's for safety, so these caps discharge after some time.
The whole mount is done by hanging mount.
You can see the track wiring — the simplest build without PCB etching.
Now we'll tune the circuit first.
Pick the optimal mode with a trim pot.
I'll show how this is done.
And then move to full testing under load.
To tune the system by frequency that optimally corresponds to this core, we need a load.
A 40-volt lamp.
Or a multimeter hooked to the output — it directly shows the potential on the lamp.
Well, or a power source.
For anyone who doesn't have one, you can take a well-charged battery and an ammeter.
We're interested in the ammeter reading.
The point of tuning is that we'll observe the voltage on the lamp and find the minimum consumption at which this voltage is maintained.
Before the experiment, switch the trim pot slider to the minimum frequency mode.
That's about 12 kHz.
You'll hear the transformer working.
So, apply power.
Here's the consumption.
2.86 A at 13.9 V.
And the voltage on the lamp is 220 V.
Now I'll move the lamp slightly to the side so it doesn't shine in the lens.
The step-up transformer is slightly squeaking — and I start slowly rotating the trim pot.
Observing current and voltage.
The current, you see, starts falling, and the voltage stays.
There's a point — 221 V, 2.8 A consumption.
Further on, with frequency increase, consumption grows.
Back off and find the minimum-consumption point.
That's 2.8 A and voltage on the lamp 221 V.
Next action.
Unsolder the resistor, measure it, and pick a stationary working resistor to replace it that'll go on the board.
This goes in place of the 10 kΩ.
I unsoldered the resistor — here it is — now we measure it.
So we see the resistance is 3.2 kΩ.
And I found this resistor for myself — the closest to that value.
Its resistance is 3.28 kΩ.
Which suits well.
You can also use these trim pots.
You can buy them at 10 kΩ and install them on the board right away.
It's multi-turn and you can set the operating point.
But since this device will be used on the road, I decided to use this type of resistor.
So I installed the resistor on the board.
Now we can check consumption.
Apply power.
You see — 221 V.
And consumption of 2.8 A.
That fully suits us.
So now, on to the tests.
I think I'd planned to test this board operating in the 120-150 W range.
Because my laptop charger consumes a maximum of 120 W.
And so I'll always operate it in the up-to-50-W range.
So let's arrange a check for it.
At 200 W.
I think such a small circuit will pull this.
200 W will be consumption at 12 V power.
Most likely about 15 A.
This power supply won't pull it.
So I'll bring out a car battery charger.
Moving to a test on a 200 W lamp.
While I was preparing and checking, a small accident happened.
These EFR207 diodes in the diode bridge couldn't take it.
At 150 W it worked great, but the 200 W lamp didn't withstand.
Although at 230 V on a 200 W lamp the current through it is 0.87 A.
And this current divided into 4 diodes — they should handle it normally.
But one of them didn't survive.
Moreover, it failed in an interesting way.
The multimeter shows it's intact.
And when you do a conductivity test at about 100 V, it starts breaking down.
Either I got a defective one, or it actually couldn't withstand.
But anyway, I replaced them with HER508 diodes.
This will be reflected in the schematic too.
Launch.
200 W lamp.
I recommend power supplies like this.
That is, a charger.
You can also use it as a power supply.
It sets the battery charge current.
But it works for our purposes too.
Launch.
You see 222 V on the lamp.
Consumption slightly less than 15 A.
There's some sag on the 200 W lamp.
You can reduce by one turn.
Then we'd get 230 V nominal.
Or add a few more turns on the secondary.
But I won't need to operate it at this power.
So this is a test already with overload.
On a trip or in field conditions, drawing 15 A from a battery will drain it fast.
And besides — these days there are LED lamps.
[Incandescents] make no sense.
Because they release a lot of heat.
Eat a lot.
Light, yes.
But the rest doesn't interest us.
So it works better.
Let me show what this system looks like on an LED lamp.
It consumes only 11 W.
And shines several times brighter than this 15 W lamp.
Tens of times — there's no comparison at all.
You see the circuit works on the lamp.
The lamp's glowing.
The charger power supply is maxed out at 15 A.
What about the heat sink?
The heat sink — I'd say about 60 degrees.
Fingers start to burn.
So yes, 200 W is heavy load for this converter.
But nevertheless it works.
And moreover, it works without forced cooling.
So up to 150 W it's in an acceptable temperature range.
Can work without a fan.
And at 50 W or 80 W operation.
It absolutely doesn't need additional airflow.
Such a DIY thing.
A lazy converter, basically.
Whoever liked it — repeat it.
Turn off.
Now I'll show how the lamp works from this converter.
LED.
Its consumption is marked here.
11 W.
And compare its glow with a 15 W incandescent lamp.
Apply power to the input.
Look how this lamp shines.
Just a flood of light.
In field conditions this is plenty.
And here's the consumption.
We have 13.1 V.
Multiply by 0.72 A.
We get 9.5 W.
Moreover, the chip itself has protection from supply voltage drop so the switches work in the optimal range.
So if we lower the voltage — say the battery is discharging.
10.6 V — the lamp is glowing.
Threshold 8.4 V.
The lamp is still glowing.
But the battery never discharges to that level for us.
That'd already be kaput.
8.3 V.
Startup happens around 9 V.
And now compare with a test of a 15 W incandescent.
Connect.
And there's no comparison, naturally.
So there's no point in field conditions to use these converters for incandescent lamps.
Now two-lamp consumption.
12.8 V.
1.74 A.
About 22.3 W.
So I recommend using LED lamps.
Next part of the video.
A short continuation.
Most likely it'll be uninteresting to those experienced in these matters.
I'll give some advice to beginners.
What tools are needed to make this lazy DIY.
Now another moment — measure.
How much does it draw without a load.
Disconnect this lamp.
Disconnect this.
And look.
Now multiply.
12.8 times 0.07.
What do we have?
0.9 W at idle.
Pretty good actually.
For this kind of thing, without any stabilization.
A minimum gentleman's tool kit for a beginner radio amateur.
Who wants to replicate this converter.
Accordingly, we need a screwdriver or drill.
Because we need to drill holes for fastening bolts.
Fastening the board itself and the transistors.
And I attached the step-up transformer with a bolt.
That's the first thing.
What drills will we need?
We'll need a 3.2 mm drill.
So that these bolts with 3 mm outer size pass through.
And we'll also need a 2.6 mm drill.
You can buy 2.5 mm in stores.
So we drilled a hole in the heat sink.
And we could, with the tap — the M3 thread — cut a thread there.
Tap the thread carefully.
If it's aluminum, the metal is viscous, and you can easily break the tap.
So I'd suggest greasing it with some lubricant when tapping.
Simplest is to use WD-40.
Two drills and the tap, don't forget.
Add tweezers — very helpful for soldering small parts.
Cutting tools — side cutters and small round-nose pliers.
The wire I used for the 5.5-turn primary winding.
Single-core, its core is 1.1 mm.
And it's 1.8 mm with insulation outside.
The wire I wound the step-up secondary with — this red one.
Now let's measure it too.
0.7 mm core and 1.4 mm with insulation.
When wound on this core, here's how it's laid.
First layer turn-to-turn, with no gaps around the full circumference.
Then the second layer also from the inside, turn-to-turn.
And the third layer is laid with this wire turn-to-turn.
So it's wound in three layers.
And that was enough on this core for us to get 220 V on the lamp under load.
You adjust the voltage individually with the turn count.
If the wire is slightly different — no problem.
Besides buying the radio parts per the list of this schematic, don't forget to mandatorily get KPT thermal paste.
Mine is KPT-19 non-drying thermal paste.
And if you can find mica insulating pads for transistors — though they're rare now.
Most often you can find this material that has polyethylene on top.
It protects from dust.
This is a thermal-conductive material, while being insulating.
Because you can't mount transistors directly on the heat sink.
Because this lead, where the bolt is fastened, is connected to the current.
And if you fasten directly to metal, there will be a short circuit.
So a gasket is mandatory.
The gasket is placed at least 3 mm beyond this contact, the cooling surface.
Smeared with thermal paste, and the transistor is installed on this substrate.
And there's another small thing you might forget.
These plastic insulator washers.
They go on the screw that fastens the transistor to the heat sink.
And when in place, the gasket sits in the transistor's eye.
And prevents contact between the fastening bolt and the metal lead of the transistor.
Also a critical thing, because if you just screw it in, there'll be a short circuit.
And basically that's all.
Soldering iron and solder.
If you have no experience, you might need about a day with breaks to make this thing.
For me it took one day.
Literally 5-6 hours to wind, assemble, and tune.
Now about the mounting.
There are a few rules useful for beginners.
This is power electronics mounting.
The leads going from the chip through the resistor to the transistors should be the shortest possible length.
In general everything that controls the transistors should be as short as possible.
That is, the chip is located closest to the power switches.
This way you reduce pickups, parasitic ringing, and other negative phenomena that may show up during converter operation.
I already explained why this cap is needed.
Mandatorily put it in.
This is a ceramic capacitor.
Ceramic capacitors at 50 V — like these, yellow color.
And work with mounting density as tight as possible.
So we don't have big distances between parts.
They're practically all next to each other.
The diode bridge — doesn't matter how you make it.
Reservoir cap.
And don't forget to put this resistor in.
Because residual charge on the capacitors — if it doesn't discharge — you can get hit, and it'll be very unpleasant.
After this thing the voltage can be high, and here's residual.
Don't pay attention to these leads, those are my taps further on.
Here 70 V and here 135 V.
Relative to the start of the wire.
And if operating up to 50 W, you can fully put it in some box, even without leaving cooling holes.
If more than 50 W, you can position the heat sink so it sticks out of the box for cooling.
The heat sink dimensions are 6 cm in length.
Width practically 3.5 cm.
And this dimension is 1.7 cm.
When you pick a heat sink, this part should be as thick as possible relative to these cooling ribs.
And basically that's all — nothing tricky here.
You can tune it all without instruments.
I already showed how to do that, and this thing starts up right away.
A small downside is that this circuit is open-loop.
If you leave it without load, high potential can build up here.
Significantly above 350 V.
I took a 450 V capacitor — that's enough.
But I'll tinker with this circuit a bit more.
I'll lay out this circuit, then show how it works.
This chip has one wonderful property.
If you apply logical zero to pin 3 — simply apply minus of the power source — it stops generation.
I think on this principle you can make voltage feedback.
For example, to hold 330 V DC at the output.
The cap reaches 330 V and the chip stops generation.
I'll make something simple — then I'll share the schematic.
Marking here — before I print this schematic, sending it to my Yandex.Disk.
I'll mark the HER508 diodes too.
And basically that's all.