Greetings everyone.
Equipped this lazy converter construction with voltage feedback.
Now it stably holds 238 V at output.
Feedback also done quite simply.
These are two additional microchips.
One of them optocoupler PC817, other — controllable zener TL431.
4 resistances, 1 capacitor.
That's all feedback.
Thus, this converter got possibility to supply at input not only 12 V but also up to 20 V inclusive.
In any range of voltages of this order.
And stabilized output voltage.
Now we'll test it and further examine feedback scheme.
Now will test trigger point of voltage feedback.
To output connected tester, with this lamp not connected.
Apply power 12 V.
Visible that converter trigger point by sound audible starts to buzz.
Such sound comes out.
237 V.
Connect lamp.
Visible that on lamp there's some drop, 218 V.
Output voltage went away from feedback trigger point and converter works in usual mode.
No sound at all.
With voltage feedback present can supply at input voltage also higher.
Inclusive 20 V higher not worth.
Now supplied 14 V.
Visible that voltage is within norm and feedback trigger sound appeared.
Sound goes from step-up transformer, since microchip now controls keys in pulse bursts mode.
If reduce, then sound disappears.
Feedback fully works.
To question what can connect to such converter.
To it can connect all modern devices that have voltage inverter without transformer at input.
That is, these are mobile phone chargers, laptop chargers, such devices.
Can't connect device that contains step-down transformer at input.
Such power supplies, their weight significantly higher than of inverter power supply.
Also can't connect here asynchronous motors.
Most often in everyday life we can meet them in fans, for example.
And brush collector motors that are here, will work freely.
That is various kind small drills at 220 volts, power up to 200 watts, this system will freely power.
To supplement our scheme with voltage feedback, use property of microchip IR2153.
If at third pin of this microchip apply logical zero, microchip stops generation on both channels.
For this I stopped at variant with galvanic isolation OPTOCOUPLER, widespread PC817.
Soldered it in this scheme, according to its leads.
Leads 1 and 2 are infrared diode, built into OPTOCOUPLER.
Third and fourth lead are opto-transistor.
OPTOCOUPLER is such small detail, here it is, with four leads.
On upper part of case there's dot, it means lead numbering.
This is first lead.
Leads, if observe from dot, in this case it's now located upper left corner, counted counter-clockwise.
That is first, second, third and fourth.
On scheme OPTOCOUPLER presented lying legs up.
Like this now corresponds to its leads.
So, solder OPTOCOUPLER into scheme.
Here visible, I installed it on board.
And check, does OPTOCOUPLER work.
For this apply power to converter, preliminarily soldering small load to it.
In this case lamp 15 watts.
Apply power.
See, lamp lit.
Now we need to solder to second lead of OPTOCOUPLER a wire.
Here it is.
And to first lead of OPTOCOUPLER current-limiting resistor 91 Ohm.
And one-and-half-volt battery.
Minus from battery we supply to second leg.
Plus to resistor.
And observe, I connect battery.
And at connecting battery plus to resistor, microchip stops generation, load goes out.
This experiment shows that OPTOCOUPLER is in working state.
If there's lab signal generator on hand, can look how converter triggers under OPTOCOUPLER control with rectangular signal applied to input, common signal generator
connects to second lead, signal one to first lead, also through current-limiting resistance.
Input potential supply not more than 5 V.
Enough for OPTOCOUPLER triggering 1.5-2 V freely.
Equivalent to what we did from battery.
I supply rectangular signal with frequency 10 Hz.
See that scheme excellently responds.
Reduce frequency.
Frequency 5 Hz.
That is, understand, who deals with electronics, can on such principle already form microchip work in form of bursts.
Frequency 1 Hz.
If apply, say, mains frequency, here I smoothly raise, now 25 Hz.
50.
Can hear when will be such possibility to supply, that this step-up transformer hums at mains frequency 50 Hz.
Further we need to introduce into scheme one more element.
This is microchip TL431.
Graphically it presented as zener.
With branch turns out controllable zener system.
Pinout of leads presented under graphic image.
Detail itself also very small.
Here it is.
Three leads at detail.
Left to right counted leads, if microchip name reads directly frontally.
What is this done for?
Earlier I gave scheme of one more converter, and we can observe that here by feedback converter, master microchip, controlled directly through OPTOCOUPLER PC817 by means of dividing
voltage on bundle of resistances connected in series.
Here in this scheme can't control so, because if LED glow will be different intensity, accordingly and opto-transistor will, since it's bipolar, it will
open with various degree of conductivity.
And therefore, if measure it, play with OPTOCOUPLER, can see that resistance of this transistor changes.
And for this microchip need order not less than 200 Ohm of resistance, to reliably short third leg to common wire.
Precisely for this introduced additional sensitive element TL431 that controls this optocoupler.
TL431 quite for us elderly microchip.
Made it end 1970s, but nevertheless widely used till now.
Its advantage is operating voltage up to 36 Volts and main possibility to set trigger points of this microchip.
Inside there's reference power source about 2.5 Volts and comparator.
At one comparator input supplied stabilized power 2.5 Volts, and at other input supplied voltage from external part, from first lead.
At that comparator compares reference and input voltage.
If input voltage exceeds reference, microchip triggers and, graphically speaking, zener for us breaks down, that is microchip starts conducting.
Picked I divider on resistors.
Resistors one-watt 4.6 kOhm and 390 kOhm.
At such resistance, if its leads take already from converter output, voltage protection triggering happens at 238 Volts.
That is, changing ratings of this resistance 4.6 kOhm, can set trigger point of converter.
Mandatory need not forget to put this capacitor not less than 10 nF, ceramic, between third and first lead.
Otherwise possible false feedback triggers at some transient processes in transformer.
For example, if there'll be needle-like voltage spikes, microchip will trigger earlier than needed.
Capacitor mandatory.
And this resistance that placed parallel to LED of optocoupler 1 kOhm.
This resistance also doesn't let LED glow when microchip TL431 approaches trigger point.
Limiting resistance 150 Ohm.
Searched at start feedbacks of such kind in internet, but interesting, nothing found.
Very many such solutions for low voltage, but with high voltage had to fiddle.
Divider long picked in practice and changed various scheme variants, until it started working stably.
Many details for this converter can be borrowed in some broken power supplies, for example, from computer power supplies.
Can buy them cheaply or you may be given them at service centers just so.
In particular can see that on board located optocoupler PC817 and this microchip.
Small TL431.
Also heat sinks on which can plant transistors.
Thermal insulation gaskets under these transistors, all can find here.
Well and such also quite suits.
Can it, this transformer disassemble.
Soldered out it from board, but usually either heat it with construction dryer help until this glue melts so halves separate, or boil in water, also until it falls apart.
After this all unwound, well and wound own winding according to desired voltages.
So this converter can come out very cheap if make it from recycled material.
If this converter will be used, for example, for lighting when electric power supply turned off, then advise in this case put here at input some diode of any brand,
no difference what find, at 20 A here.
Voltage so order not less than 100 V.
So in case of insufficient lighting not mix up these power inputs.
Otherwise if mix up, scheme of course will immediately come into uselessness, microchip will fail and possibly one of keys will fly out.
If it's connected stationary constantly, can not put diode.
But also whoever wants can equip scheme input with fuse.
That is at your discretion can upgrade this scheme.
Also on such principle, this feedback I applied by voltage.
I need operating voltage point so it'd be... If voltage feedback assembled, here can already at input supply not only 12 V but voltage up to 20 V inclusive, with this it'll
stably hold output voltage.
That is can even take in pocket two Krona-type batteries, connect them in series and supply at input 18 V.
And you'll have at output voltage 220 V.
Always charge mobile phone.
In whole scheme such flexible.
Whoever interested can also assemble here current feedback.
That is if interested specifically that at output shorting microchip went to protection.
For this will need to change divider resistance, wind small toroidal transformer, so-called current transformer.
Can hang it at this common point by power plus to middle point of primary winding.
And already playing with its turn count, bring operating voltage point say somewhere above 2.6 V.
Say if this converter works on load 200 V.
And feed this output from this current sensor to small diode bridge.
After this put capacity.
Approximately scheme for you will turn out analog of this one presented.
Diode bridge, capacity and already for you may turn out quite working system that'll protect converter from short voltage, that is from short circuit at its output.
Everyone successful experiments, all good!