Greetings everyone.
Starting another project that's designed to ease searches for experimenters in free energy area.
Block of scheme shown on this picture is power supply, universal for our experiments.
Planned output voltage up to 1000 V.
Also will run in this scheme new for me solution, this is work on opto-drivers.
So why is such scheme needed?
The thing is, can of course manage with bought power supplies.
In particular, two I have.
One of them low-voltage up to 30 V, other high-voltage up to 300 V.
Seemingly voltage range normal and suitable, but there are some problems.
First, these power supplies connect to mains.
And connection to mains guarantees us connection with neutral.
That is zero wire in lighting network inevitably tied to grounding.
If we construct devices designed to get energy relative to earth, then with use of these power supplies we won't get anything, since we're already automatically tied to
grounding through neutral.
Seemingly could exclude connection with grounding, for example by turning on these power supplies through two transformers to isolate.
But even in this case we also have connection.
Anyway somehow it slips through and interferes with work.
Could apply solution start power supplies through inverter.
Yes, solution good and this solves main problem of earth connection.
But there's one moment.
All our experiments in most cases happen at pulse consumption from these power sources.
And effects accompanying these experiments often so unpredictable that these power supplies behave absolutely inadequately.
Generally, controllers start behaving chaotically, with this output voltage jumps, output current and besides, for example, of such power supply it starts giving operation in bursts mode.
That is so strongly influence goes on it from these output wires.
Tried putting filters here, this also doesn't save from this problem.
Constant incorrect readings.
And plus, when these blocks start working in pulse power supply mode, signal in form of bursts forms at output after key on control device.
That is additional frequency modulation, and what naturally doesn't allow us to adequately tune system.
So from these power blocks had to refuse due to their unsuitability.
Such solutions very good for electronics tuning, they greatly help me.
But unfortunately, for powering devices and for such experiments they're unsuitable.
So was decided to develop this power supply that'll meet set tasks.
In particular, same advice can give about oscilloscope use.
Watching people's experiments, they connect oscilloscope to device and try to tune something.
Forgetting that oscilloscope plugged into lighting network, common wire of oscilloscope inevitably tied to neutral.
And turns out, even with power supply use we connect device and introduce same problem.
In Nikola Tesla's times there was lighting network on direct current and there was no connection to neutral.
Moreover, Nikola Tesla himself constructed devices that would allow him to work.
Such as DC dynamo machines.
Such dynamo machine gave autonomous power source and could be brought to rotation with help of external motor.
The thing is, all dynamo machines essentially are AC machines.
But if make dynamo machine with many contacts and do collector takeoff, can take from it potential at peak of AC wave.
Thereby getting DC at output, which he was doing.
But return to our scheme.
Examine it in more detail.
First, power will be from battery, which solves our problem of connection with grounding.
Next, I introduced relay element and diode so during our experiments with energetic effect inclusions in cheerful coil haze, not accidentally swap power wires.
Such polarity reversal would inevitably lead to failure of keys and DC-DC converter that gives independent power.
Solution simple.
We have relay with normally-open contacts and there's winding that creates magnetic field, thereby attracting contact, and they close.
If in correct direction install diode, can exclude wrong scheme inclusion.
That is, when plus power applied to diode anode, current passes through it and naturally forming magnetic field, contacts attract.
With reverse battery inclusion contact closure won't be.
Next introduced filter system, in capacities will be choke, well and already power applied to power keys.
Decided to stop on full bridge scheme.
Such scheme will allow qualitatively commutating primary winding and additionally introduce opto-isolations.
Four opto-drivers controlling keys.
Also introduced DC-DC converter with galvanic isolation.
All this done so during our experiments no influence on PWM controller or drivers controlling keys, which could lead to incorrect system operation.
In whole scheme quite simple, but there'll be nuances in its manufacture which I'll demonstrate along the way.
For us will be introduced current feedback, thereby we can do current protection regulation.
Very important parameter so if some shorting happened at output, system didn't fail.
And this point can be regulated, thereby setting trigger threshold.
Also will be introduced pulse duration regulation, which ultimately will be responsible for output voltage.
That is on each transformer lead we'll have voltage regulation from zero to maximum that allows turn count of this transformer.
At that transformer will be made on ferrite ring and secondary winding will have taps.
Here I schematically marked taps that'll go to switch and between taps can switch, thereby regulating maximum output voltage.
Voltage feedback can't be introduced here due to scheme being very bulky.
Will have to use same switch that'll change resistor circuits that'll set feedback trigger point.
But in PWM controller I'll introduce this system.
Say, if we need to hold on some lead constant voltage, we just take from here potential of this voltage, create resistor divider and feed back.
Say, we have tested scheme of some transistor and we precisely know its parameters.
This can be done.
And so, main switching of voltage potential will be done with switch help.
And output voltage will be calculated by Ohm's law on load, where current multiplied by load resistance.
But since for us power will be pulse, taken from output of this converter, this formula will be incorrect a little, but this quite suits us.
Before moving to making this scheme, need to first buy all parts.
So far at my place found such switch that perfectly suits us from Soviet equipment.
It has ceramic contact pad and quite powerful terminal output.
Here I drew where additional work on terminals is needed, because now if we switch, visible that switch due to contact pad width temporarily closes contact.
This need to get rid of and switch will be fully suitable.
Switch has 12 leads in circle, one of them common, from it supply voltage will be taken, and this petal does commutation.
In this case I drew on 12 leads, but at my place found 11-lead switch.
Not critical, quite suits us.
Can pick any here, who'll like, for output rating.
Of details that set common system dimensions, already have ready DC-DC converter.
Video on its tuning and making can look in previous video clip on my channel.
Specifically made for purpose of installation in this universal power supply.
It'll be located here.
For all other parts I go to store.
After this when I buy, move to manufacture.
And at same time count how such universal power supply works out by price of radio parts.
Thanks to all who watched.
Awaiting next release.