Greetings everyone.
Continue work on making lab power supply.
Now before you presented part of its schematic diagram.
What already managed to do, so to say, in iron.
And this part today we'll test.
Slightly turn to schematics.
Master generator made on microchip UC3825N.
On its base also assembled PWM controller with feedbacks by current and by voltage.
Now can see that current feedback not yet introduced.
That is we'll test system without it.
Current feedback introduced to ninth leg through resistor 1 kOhm.
So microchip started in such connection, ninth leg through this resistor need to set on common circuit, on minus power.
Also can see that outputs from controller go from 14th leg and from 11th.
Schematically I marked 14th leg as one, 11th leg as two in circle.
And now we can track control.
One for us comes to this optical driver.
And also see that one exits to driver diagonally.
Also for us work keys.
That is crosswise so work keys.
One pair and second pair.
Thereby we create bipolar current pulsations through primary winding of pulse transformer.
Also can observe separate power on each of four drivers.
Schematically marked plus-minus.
And supplied 16 volts at these points.
This power galvanically isolated.
And further same power introduced separately to PWM controller itself.
Introduced it from DC-DC converter for 5 leads.
Schematics can find on my channel.
And also video on its making.
Optical connection for us also will be by voltage.
Here visible optocoupler PC817.
Introduced its output to first leg.
And receives it power from 16th lead through current-limiting resistance 1 kOhm.
This optocoupler planned to use as sensor of limited voltage of power supply, namely 1000 volts.
That is at reaching 1000 volts at output converter should enter limiting mode to maintain this potential.
Up to 1000 volts voltage regulation will be done with this trimmer resistance variable resistor.
And also can observe that I picked ratings of resistors connected with variable resistance in series.
So smooth was regulation on whole length of variable resistance rotation.
Which very convenient for regulation.
Also picked them so that if slider will be at extreme left position, microchip generation stops and power supply goes to standby mode.
Can observe on scheme that PWM controller powering done from potential 16 volts that supplied to 15th lead of microchip.
13th lead powered with voltage 12 volts, that turns out on regulator L7812.
Done it with purpose to apply potential 12 volts to input LED of opto-drivers.
Limit voltage.
12 volts quite enough for these drivers and they excellently work.
Applied this potential through current-limiting resistance 470 Ohm and also parallel to LED in driver connected resistance 1 kOhm, that excludes false trigger of opto-driver in this
system.
Now slightly will show how this looks in iron and further move to testing and tuning of block.
This block in assembly.
What can see here?
Here I made bus by which supplied power and connection with rest of control bodies of device.
This separable unit.
Further DC-DC converter for 5 galvanically isolated outputs.
4 opto-drivers HCPL3120.
Microchip of PWM controller itself UC3825N.
This for us regulator L7812.
Of main strapping elements of drivers.
These resistance chains.
And further visible resistances 1-watt.
These chains going to FET transistor gate.
Also here can see bundles of 15-volt zeners connected counter.
These parts parallel to transistor leads.
On scheme can see that one of ratings of current-limiting resistance I set.
This 4.7 Ohm by gate.
Second rating not yet marked.
By default I have on board connected same resistance 4.7 Ohm.
In practice I'll pick and if need rating of this resistance will be reduced.
For more quality opening of FET transistor gate by leading edge.
But this again if needed.
This resistance is this part responsible for control of voltage potential.
More nothing here such on which can in detail stop.
Connected power pulse transformer.
Decided I to make primary winding with wire in insulation, multi-strand from pure copper.
In thermal stable insulation.
7 turns, which corresponds at fully charged accumulator to about 14 volts.
2 volts per turn primary winding.
So, all ready for testing.
Now need to look how controlled optical drivers.
For this we'll look initial work of PWM controller at these points.
Point 1 and point 2.
Actually our control pulses supplied in antiphase and at their maximum duration PWM controller leaves pause between them, so-called dead time.
Connected I oscilloscope probes at these points.
Now apply power to DC-DC converter.
Now will be audible sound of working core.
And at changing pulse duration DC-DC converter will adapt to consumption and tonality of this sound will change.
Applied I power.
DC-DC converter started.
See that oscillogram slightly changed.
And now I bring slider of variable resistor out of extreme position when PWM controller doesn't do work.
Smoothly add.
See that appeared minimum pulse.
And audible how DC-DC converter changed tonality.
Such feature of it.
Us interested how smoothly changes duration of control pulses.
Bring to limit.
End of resistor slider.
And now observe, is there pause between control pulses.
Yes, actually pause present in time.
Now look what it is.
Set sweep to 100 ns per cell.
And turns out 100, 200, 300, 400 ns makes pause at this PWM controller.
When we convinced that all works, now can look how behaves optical driver at load on FET transistor gate.
For this I'll switch blue channel of oscilloscope to output of optical driver.
Place it directly on FET transistor gate.
And here we can already observe its real work under load.
For start look how duration changes.
Control channel yellow.
That is optical driver works properly.
Now can observe key opening front.
Will need to look at front of blue channel of oscilloscope.
Also to 100 ns per cell.
These small interferences we can observe, this work of DC-DC converter.
But this absolutely not critical and in no way affects work of common scheme.
See that reducing pulse duration, front remains same.
And can measure it in time.
At this chain in gate circuit 4.7 Ohm and resistance 4.7 Ohm, front of signal growth on FET transistor gate makes by time 300 ns.
And front by which controlled, very steep, that supplied precisely from PWM controller.
Us interested precisely this parameter.
And can also look at rear front of key closure.
This front makes approximately 200 ns.
Now about moment I talked, about picking this resistance that not specified.
If we short it, now I'll do this with tweezers help, can see that front will grow.
Steepness of front that opens.
Visible that at shorting, with us steepness of opening front increases.
That is from 300 ns to 200 ns.
And means we have wide variant for picking these resistances in gate circuit to set clear work of power key.
On this can consider check of work.
Schemes finished, all functions.
Such same checks should conduct on each optical driver.
Picture should be maintained.
So do first launch of system.
This I recommend doing always using incandescent lamp.
Carefully check once more whole schematics of supply wires, polarity that brought to connection of electrolytic capacitors.
Because their reversal can lead to failure.
And not applying power to scheme, check for start power module.
For this connect one of wires to accumulator.
In this case I connected minus power source.
And plus lead, going here to capacitor battery and further to power keys, I'll connect with incandescent lamp.
It immediately will show if we have some malfunction.
Observe, I connect.
And saw that lamp slightly flashed.
And further its connection doesn't lead to filament glow.
First flash symbolized that charged these capacities.
And further moment that lamp doesn't burn, testifies to that power block assembled correctly and keys don't pass current without control.
Now after we convinced of this, can move to testing of block.
Convince that system for us off.
That is with resistance slider help set it in non-working mode.
Extreme position, smallest pulse duration, more precisely their full absence.
And now connect system.
Can use for this purpose ammeter.
Very well with its help observe current that system consumes.
Connect accumulator battery.
And now can apply power to DC-DC converter.
Power supplied.
Say immediately, that turn count in pulse transformer quite high.
Transformation ratio big at steep pulses.
And voltage here will be quite high.
Can look that now system doesn't work and discharge at us none at outputs.
Now I shorted start green wire and end of transformer winding.
Now I slightly add pulse duration.
And see that appeared small discharge.
System started, by ammeter can also control.
Now consumption very small.
Add more.
Observe.
Discharge already increased its length.
And already stretches.
That is system works.
In such visual way can determine how voltage rises.
Add more.
Tell you guys, here far over 1000 volts at such discharge.
At touching wires stick.
Would still ammeter get in lens.
Now try to do this.
So.
So was visible.
Scale at zero.
Bad slightly contact.
Here now is.
We see that at shorting consumption reaches 9 amps current.
Add more pulse duration.
10 amps short.
Add already full duration.
Probably now will be specific discharge.
With this matter already need to be more careful.
Better such experiments conduct through lamp bulb so system didn't fail.
You see all yourselves.
Hellish power at this system.
Switch to off mode.
Now will interest us tuning of this system by frequency.
For this we need oscilloscope.
Look oscillogram on one of transformer leads relative to start lead.
And already tune to optimal frequency.
Tune core under operating frequency.
For this I connected yellow channel of oscilloscope to one of leads.
Namely to third lead of transformer, since voltage here high.
If count from start of winding.
Probes I have at 1500 volts, hundredfold suppression.
So not afraid for device.
If you have probes of tenfold suppression, this better do by first lead.
Now power supplied to keys from accumulator.
And now apply power to DC-DC converter.
At that resistance slider responsible for pulse duration switched to system off.
Apply power to converter.
And see for now at transformer output nothing.
Now smoothly add duration of control pulses.
And see such picture.
With increasing duration can observe that quantity of these waves also increases.
This means our core is not in optimal operating mode.
Pulse duration to full.
And we can count quantity of these waves.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
That is approximately we need to raise frequency 5 times.
For this transformer.
This will now do.
This resistance answers on scheme for frequency.
At ratings presented on scheme.
This 10 kOhm at fifth leg and 2200 pF seventh leg.
Frequency will regulate from 35 kHz to 185 kHz.
At this PWM controller.
And raise frequency.
Observe how phenomenon of ringing in transformer will disappear.
This such preliminary tuning.
Further, after connection of diode bridge.
Will be conducted correction of transformer work.
Directly under load by DC.
Now we'll remove this negative phenomenon.
Of oscillations.
Frequency raise.
We need so was one pulse each.
Power supply slightly grumbles.
Since doesn't withstand consumption of DC-DC converter.
But nothing.
So we bring.
And here practically already what we need.
Now can control pulse duration.
From zero to maximum.
Oscillogram became significantly more beautiful.
Now need to connect at these points load.
And look what signal form will be under load.
Connected I lamp 60 W at 220 Volts.
And on it we'll observe oscillogram and voltage.
Parallel its output.
Apply power.
And smoothly add duration of control pulses.
See that lamp spiral starts to glow.
Go further.
Oscillogram changes.
And here maximum duration of control pulses.
Such have oscillogram.
Need to look at its symmetry.
See symmetric work.
Smooth regulation if we rotate slider.
Output voltage.
At this stage can consider preliminary tuning of system finished.
Frequency for us made 93 kHz approximately.
Can slightly more add.
But this we'll already do after play finally with frequency.
When here we'll already look at voltage by DC, us will interest maximum voltage rating on load at minimum consumption from power source.
That is will need look at ammeter.
At this stage convinced that system fully workable.
Interesting, heats it or no after such...
Absolutely cold heat sink.
Blowing absolutely won't be needed.
On this with you say goodbye for next series.
Everyone all good and successful experiments.