Greetings everyone on my channel.
So, today we have very interesting topic on lab power supply.
Namely, will pick and tune current protection.
Very important parameter that determines whole idea of this device.
This moment when device will hold certain current passing through power keys.
Thereby we'll regulate output parameters, pick under load.
Before you now schematic diagram that for today looks so.
Slightly it'll still be drawn out, some modifications, but elements presented all here, will no longer be subject to changes.
So, stop in more detail at current protection.
Introduced it to ninth leg of microchip UC3825N.
Interesting property of this microchip is that at applying voltage rating 0.9 V starts current protection trigger, that is reduces duration of output pulses.
And this parameter from 0.9 V to 1.3 V lasts width reduction.
At reaching amplitude voltage to 1.3 V at output fully stops generation of control pulses.
That is such small window of possibilities.
For us to fit into it, need to do strapping of this system and sensitive current sensor.
Current sensor, this schematically presented this on drawing, ring, and around it wire in form of spiral.
Physically this such ring, its dimensions presented also on drawing.
Make I it on ferrite of Epcos company, permeability 2200.
If you'll use any other ferrites, then accordingly data that I'll cite in this video, you'll have slightly different.
In practice this will need pick everyone.
Experimentally I found out, that for my ferrite, this core, for proper sensitivity, so could regulate from 0.5 A to point I desire, and for me this will be 20 A
consumption of 12 V accumulator.
Me needed wind on this core 120 turns of wire section 0.35 mm.
Wound I for experiments on same cores and other wire diameters, in particular wire 0.45, but this quantity of turns turned out little.
Here need to wind in several layers, so went experimentally toward reducing wire section and stopped in optimal mode.
That is this core wound fully around circumference in one layer.
Before start of work on winding wire on this core, won't be superfluous to calculate total wire length that will fit on this magnetic core.
For this use known formula of calculating circumference length, expressed through diameter, where P — circumference length, π — constant 3.14 and D — diameter.
Measure with caliper this diameter and substitute it in formula.
Multiply, get circumference length 42.39 mm.
Further need to stop at wire diameter that we'll wind.
In this case at me this 0.35 mm.
Further act so.
Circumference length divide by wire diameter, get turn count.
121 turn will fit on this core.
Now should know length of one turn.
For this tightly wrap core with wire, straighten and measure.
In this case turn length at me made 21 mm.
Now multiply turn count by length of one turn and get wire length in millimeters.
Further divide by 1000 mm in one meter and express length already in meters.
In my case made 2.54 mm.
Approximately with leads I took 2.6 mm.
Wound I with such bobbin help from copper wire with flattened edges.
Such product I got in course of doing work.
Took about hour of continuous work.
Now visible that I brought out its leads.
Start lead soldered to start of wire directly, and already end lead laid in heat shrink.
Now this product should be well insulated.
Insulate will with masking tape help, for protecting damage of wire with which wound current-pickup transformer from mechanical damage.
Finished I insulation protection of current sensor and while drying glue, fixing tip of tape.
Slightly explain by scheme.
On scheme can notice graphic notations at various points.
This nothing other than terminal block.
At boundary of these parts happens connection of wire.
On scheme they sold, cost not expensive, 40 rubles piece with mating part.
So it connects and very convenient, can cut any quantity of contact block.
So board looks in finished form.
This back part of board.
Wiring done with hanging mount.
Nothing super-complex.
Also on scheme are by leads 1, 2 in previous video, explained.
And letter notations.
To these letter notations also will be connected wires.
Done it so wasn't pile-up of connectors.
That is they'll be on other sheet.
Second part of scheme, this sheet 1, passes to sheet 2.
And there already will connect contacts with corresponding letters.
These contacts at us under ratings E, F.
This for switching PWM controller to standby mode.
That is at applying here voltage rating, used I current output, at ninth leg of microchip stops to generate control pulses.
Can notice that here letter F and output of letter F assembled on divider from resistors.
Here approximately picked divider so was 2-2.5 volts.
From this point here factually located switch and button that we close.
And at applying here voltage potential, generation stops.
As soon as voltage potential from here turn off, microchip again switches to operating mode.
Which will be quite convenient in practice.
Also with letters C and D marked inputs for optocoupler PC817.
Here also will be connected voltage feedback.
Can whoever convenient make precisely feedback with voltage regulation if slightly change this scheme.
But I'll use this for stopping generation at reaching 1000 volts at output of power supply.
Voltage control at me assembled on this chain of resistances.
Variable resistance 2 kOhm and limiting resistances 1 kOhm and 2.4 kOhm.
Leads marked A and B, will be supplied precisely power to bridge from keys.
Now slightly I already assembled system, attached to regular place power module, power pulse transformer, cleaned and soldered leads.
Now we'll move to fastening of current sensor.
Can see.
Visible that wire bent in such way going from this primary winding, that it forms bend at 90 degrees and goes to transistors.
That is, this point can hook.
This further goes to primary winding.
And here in this point will be placed current sensor.
Now I'll mount, solder and move to installation of board on regular place.
Current sensor installed on its regular place.
Here it on wire.
Board also installed.
All connected.
Now for next experiment that consists in determining at what frequency our converter will work in constant mode, we need load, in this case lamp 60
W, 220 V, diode bridge with capacity, to look at DC voltage on this lamp, voltmeter, in this case tester that'll track voltage on lamp, power
source, accumulator battery and ammeter that'll show consumption of whole device from accumulator battery.
For start we disconnect current sensor, interrupt one of wires, not important what, in this case I unsoldered it on board,
this wire, and we should connect in scheme these two wires together, that is connect ninth leg of microchip to ground, these two wires I connect, in this case they exit connected
to board.
Next step, this switch this trimmer resistance on scheme, this resistor 10 kOhm, switch it to extreme position so frequency of pulses controlling FET transistor gates was
maximum, in this case this 190 kHz.
Course of work will be so, track consumption and track voltage on lamp, and when find moment at which voltage on lamp maximum, and consumption at that minimum, we
stop adjustment.
Chain assembled, now should switch this resistance responsible for pulse duration in position when duration of control pulses on keys will be maximum.
I preliminarily did this, this variable resistance, now apply power to DC-DC converter, and see that load with some glow lit, and on it slowly grows
voltage.
Such growth will last some time because now transformer not in mode, frequency high.
And now observe ammeter readings at input and voltage on load.
Need to set maximum voltage on load.
Now I'll slowly drop frequency, and here frequency went down, and see that voltage at us was moment, jumped to 200 volts, but consumption about 5 amps.
Look for point at which consumption will fall, here now slowly ammeter needle moves left.
Here reached stable moment.
Stopped consumption at 4.5 amps, and voltage about 185 volts.
Now look is there lower.
There's moment when jump at us.
Slightly raise, falls consumption and falls output.
Reduce slightly further, and here moment is, narrow, when minimum consumption less 4.5 amps, and voltage about 180 volts.
Here one point, now look is there other at reducing frequency.
Here was good mode, 190 volts.
Now go lower.
Here second point will be.
Pay attention, 190 volts and consumption less than 4.5 amps, somewhere 4.2 amps.
This most likely will be our operating point.
But preliminarily I conducted such tests, and for this core with three layers, this frequency 55 kHz.
Frequency can already look with oscilloscope help.
I'll connect device and we'll see this.
Now look.
I'll go down further, will observe operating mode.
Go down,
and see that voltage starts to sag,
consumption remains same.
Already by frequency down no sense going down.
Return to original position when here will be maximum voltage.
Here 185.
Skipped slightly.
Here it, this operating point.
And now do measurement of it with oscilloscope.
Connected I oscilloscope and can observe oscillogram.
In this case stopped I at frequency 50 kHz.
This range of working core, somewhere 45-60 kHz will be.
In average I'll stop at 55 kHz of system work.
This will be normal zone for core work.
Raise frequency slightly.
At this frequency, now look, consumption makes 4.2 A and 180 V on load.
At 12 V accumulator, slightly here me jolted by current.
Happens hot end uninsulated invigorates.
Here voltage regulation present.
On this fitting by frequency ends.
Now move to tuning of current feedback.
For next stage of tuning we mandatorily need oscilloscope.
By it we'll track, works current protection or no, and its correctness of work.
Probes in this case, two channels will be used, I connected at these points that send control signal to drivers, point 1 and 2.
Start system without applying power to power module.
See oscillogram of system work.
And now reduce operating duration to position slightly less than half.
Further we need weighty load with small ohm resistance, for example lamp 300 W.
And now what we'll do?
Tracking by ammeter desired consumption current at which we'd want stop, bring ammeter readings slightly above this point.
In this case I calculate that I'll have maximum consumption 20 A, may, slightly higher.
For 12 V accumulator this already weighty consumption, and go higher of it no sense, otherwise accumulator will very quickly discharge.
For my needs this quite enough.
Load we'll turn on between these leads.
First lead of transformer and last, to give maximum load that only can be.
Here now duration and connect lamp briefly.
Ah, power.
Power now can apply to power module.
Apply power.
And now turn on.
Yes, power supplied.
See by ammeter consumption 11 A.
Here discharge.
Slightly add duration of control pulses.
14.
Add more.
19.
More.
Already flies past 30, much.
Can converter of course in this mode work and more, but for this it'll need blowing.
I wanted system to work precisely without blowing.
21 A in maximum.
Approximately what's needed.
Now, when tuned so, can these contacts open.
Now they closed.
And here we'll pick resistance.
This connects at this point.
And this resistance, it signed, determines final current trigger of current protection.
That is precisely we need tune slightly above 20 A this protection.
Now start picking resistance approximately from 10 Ohm.
Solder 10 Ohm and look at what amperage consumption triggers current protection.
So, I soldered resistance 10 Ohm.
Recommend precisely solder so contact was very good.
And now short transformer output.
See, observe changes in duration.
Such duration of control pulses, when connect load, it reduces.
That is system starts confident capture and current protection triggers.
Now I can add maximum duration of control signal and test current protection.
Here see 10 A.
Pay attention to ammeter.
Now check on short.
At short slightly above 10 A.
Already protection works, can confidently say that turn count of transformer picked correctly.
Now task consists in bringing consumption at trigger of current protection 20 A.
For this this resistance that I soldered.
We'll smoothly reduce its rating in Ohms until bring to this point.
Duration of control pulses at that now can hold at maximum.
Next test for us 8.5 Ohm.
Apply power.
See duration of pulses at maximum and load.
Observe ammeter.
11.5 A.
Don't look at that lamp 300 W slightly glows because this last lead, it high-voltage.
You see yourselves what voltage here stretches.
Lamp will burn normally on reduced number of leads.
Short, 11.5 A.
Can reduce resistance rating further.
Next resistance 4.6 Ohm.
Apply power and test on load.
18 A trigger point.
As see on this high-voltage lead, lamp glow increases.
Now I test through lamp, do short circuit.
Same 18 A on case.
We somewhere close, and now need reduce by 0.1 Ohm.
This I'll do.
So not drag video, I won't show whole system of picking by 0.1 Ohm.
Picked I so, now visible what garland of resistances.
Total its resistance makes 4.1 Ohm.
Now I achieved what I need.
Apply power and on load.
20 A.
And on short check.
Short also 20 A.
By oscilloscope also well visible that current protection triggers, reduces duration of control pulses.
All excellent.
Want say that such mode of work when happens short circuit, this most complex mode for key work, in such current limiting mode.
And in this mode heat sink will maximum heat up.
If for example do in such mode, manually reduce, then here heating will be, here I set, and in such mode heating will be minimum.
And in mode when at you duration maximum, precisely when system triggers current protection, at this moment precisely will be heating of heat sink.
But heating should be not strong.
Approximately at... now will short system, look.
Accumulator already drains of course.
Look.
There's heat release, order so 50 degrees.
In such tough mode this converter not planned to operate, especially without blowing.
So all normal.
Next stage we need to tune so trigger of current protection.
We now experiment conduct, picked this resistance here.
To here add still variable resistance, we had smooth trigger regulation from 0.10 A to 20 A.
Can set any regulation.
Decided I to stop at such scheme solution of current protection regulation.
It done on two resistances connected in series.
And in parallel to one of them connected variable resistance.
Thus, in case of exit of middle point of slider, we have current protection with help of these two resistances remains workable.
And we don't risk getting into such situation when at wear, if we simply this point connected here, at some moment our system would remain without current protection.
If this resistance remove, then system will work in mode of smallest current passing through power keys.
Will supply smallest duration at their opening.
Now show how this works.
Approximately picked ratings.
Further slightly will change.
Announce.
0.7 Ohm, 120 Ohm and 1 kOhm this resistance.
Apply power.
Regulation starts from 1 Amp and to 19 Amps.
Add with slider.
Slowly move.
See, current protection how works now.
Tune for example 2 Amps consumption.
Further 5 Amps consumption.
See duration of control pulses.
And already not important how we control output voltage, can only its reduce.
But at increase to maximum, we and will have our desired tuned with this slider.
Seems resistance slightly got low-quality.
There sharp jerks.
Will need replace.
But this all fixable.
Now bring to maximum.
18 Amps.
Yes, resistance need change, but regulation present.
So at such scheme can stop.
On this can consider tuning of current protection finished.
System successfully handles by feedback.
Until next videos.
Everyone successful experiments and all good.