Greetings everyone.
In this video clip our talk will be about homemade machine for winding multi-turn coils, of Tesla transformer type.
All who ever wound them know what laborious process this is and how much time it takes.
For example, wind such Tesla on 50-mm frame by time, where work takes about hour of intensive labor.
Make it in manual mode quite simple, because such diameter easily fits in hand.
But when speech goes about winding such coils, here frame diameter 153 millimeters, and besides if it's covered with varnish, then in manual mode do this already very problematic.
Made I such construction in couple of evenings, considering that glue dried.
Machine itself made from solid pine, width 20 centimeters and length from front rack of machine to end of lower guide makes 80 centimeters.
Front rack of machine fastened rigidly, and rear rack has possibility to move along lower guide, thereby can install here frames of different lengths.
Here from central hole to base of lower guide 16 centimeters, which can allow us to install coil about 30 centimeters in diameter for winding wire.
Work on this construction should start with that could find some motor with reducer.
In this case in my stocks I found such, can't say from what, sometime bought it incidentally.
Main moment here is gear ratio, here it makes 100 to 1, that is 100 motor revolutions correspond to 1 revolution of central shaft.
Motor here DC and this very good, since can further here make rotation regulation.
Minimum tool set for this construction is jigsaw.
Advise to apply on jigsaw for cutting such small-tooth blades, they very well suit for cutting plywood, but also end cut turns out quite quality.
Further this is screwdriver, set of bits and some set of drills.
Carpenter's glue and bit of patience.
Front rack for us glued at angle 90 degrees.
Desirable to follow this angle, so we didn't have further beatings and curvatures of central guide rotation axis.
Rear rack installed on lower guide also at angle 90 degrees at its movement.
Well and here visible that I here traced lines, that here also we have angle 90 degrees.
By rear rack it's also glued, but glued it to this point.
Here have adjustment screws.
Width of rear rack of machine, I slightly planed it.
Thereby it's 3 millimeters narrower than main guide.
And here visible certain gaps from one side and other.
These gaps allow me with tightening of these screws to set support force on lower guide so that this rear rack could move with effort and didn't pop out.
Fastened it then to lower guide at these holes with screws.
This part seated on carpenter's glue, as and these guide corners.
Central rotation axis of coil is 6 millimeter stud with cut thread.
Cut thread along its whole length allows easily to choose needed distance for installing guide disks.
Guide disks also cut from solid plywood thickness 9 millimeters.
After disk cut, drew I it with compass.
All put on axis, axis clamped in screwdriver and rotates.
Edges passed with sandpaper help, thereby acquired clear geometric circle.
And with sandpaper we fit these disks under moment that they with effort enter tube of frame of future Tesla coil.
So construction works in assembly.
Now revolution number doing regulation with lab power supply help by changing supply DC potential.
Now move to some small tricks.
At end I'll show how on this machine wound Tesla transformer.
Before start of winding wire cut frame of necessary length, according to calculation of winding length on this frame.
And make hole through which will pass wire.
This will be start of winding.
I made it at this point with awl help.
After hole made, its top cleaned with knife help, so was even surface.
Recommend to do start hole couple centimeters from edge of frame, so then was distance for which could conveniently fix coil on board.
And now when hole made, can move to installation of guide disk.
Front guide disk I already fastened.
And rear guide disk is in movable position.
Rear guide disk will install so this hole that was made was in front.
After guide disks tightened, coil frame put on its place.
Front guide disk put practically at edge of coil frame, and rear precisely sunk on depth so hole for wire in frame was behind it.
Can demonstrate.
Awl enters, and here is tip.
Here will pull through wire.
Remained two unfastened nuts.
This will do support in rear part of machine rack.
Now here moment stud that's rotation axis and has through hole.
Same through hole present at transitional shaft made from copper tube of corresponding diameter.
At putting this shaft on stud, hole becomes coaxial and in hole lowered cotter pin, thereby preventing rotation of coupling on stud.
Stud from this side round, and from opposite end I made forming under reducer shaft.
All made from plywood 9 mm.
Here glued magnet that serves as revolution sensor on machine.
It activates reed switch.
Now I installed guide axis between front support rack of machine and rear.
Rear support rack movable, it can move along machine guide board, thereby we can change installation point under various frame lengths.
I approximately made myself winding machine for coils length 80 cm.
This quite enough for my needs.
Also on stud I installed spacer tube that abuts this point.
So wood didn't break from thread, I made washer, seating it on two screws.
Precisely into it abuts copper spacer tube and already it then abuts these spacer nuts.
Important to accurately strengthen whole construction so it didn't have play.
Because when will wind wire, if there'll be play, this will reflect additional inconveniences.
And so when pressed, system works stably.
Construction of rear support of machine fastened to guide with two screws.
In front and rear part and analogously from opposite side.
Thereby construction acquires rigidity and can be in all positions installed.
Here I removed play with nuts help.
Now axial shift absent.
Can pay attention how reed switch works.
When magnet approaches, reed switch contact attracts.
And closes system.
Output of reed switch through this adapter will be connected to calculator.
It'll count revolutions.
I did connection of calculator to reed switch.
These two conductors going into calculator, now connected on board parallel to contacts of equals key.
How this works?
Turn on calculator and dial so it counted revolution count for us.
1 plus 1 and press equals.
Calculator now switched to Grand Total mode.
And at each press of equals key, it'll add last addend to previous number.
Last addend was 1.
Thereby, we now at each press will sum plus 1.
Now turn on system, apply power.
And see that at shaft rotation our calculator counts revolution count.
If supply voltage increase, revolutions accelerate and count goes faster.
There's one more feature of using calculator.
For example, winding we and our wire sharply went on overlap and we passed some turn count.
And system continues count for us.
Turn off power and remember number of revolutions that was on calculator.
Now we have 46.
Zero indicator.
Now enter it again.
46.
Minus.
And dial one.
Now unwind turn count manually back to spool that went on overlap.
And calculator at that subtracts turn count.
I now rotate in manual mode.
45.
Unwind.
44.
Thus we unwind defect that happened during winding.
And further don't forget at subsequent start of winding to switch system again to summing mode.
Repeat same operation.
Our 40 turns.
Add one.
And at subsequent system start calculator will count in larger direction.
This important moment that we count turn count that coil frame did for us.
To precisely know quantity of meters of wire that was laid on this frame.
This in moment to us will be useful then at frequency fitting.
Combining frequency of LC resonance with frequency of wave on conductor length.
Important addition to construction of this machine serves frame on which will rotate spool with winding wire.
This simplest variant, made on quick hand, but nevertheless from this its effectiveness doesn't decrease.
Sense in setting spool so its lower cheeks rubbed against lower surface of board.
Thereby because of friction force we provide certain wire tension.
Here it slips.
Visible places where spool frame rubs during rotation.
If this moment not provided, then will be very hard at winding wire to hold so turns didn't go off, because will need constantly use second hand as tensioning mechanism.
And at such reception process much simplifies.
In best case, of course, here on construction provide some additional friction, adjustable, but this in future.
For now for winding couple coils such variant quite working.
Here made holes under plastic guide at certain needed me height.
And whole this system quite well showed itself in work.
Before start of winding coil frame dry-wiped if there any contamination on surface.
Then leads wire into frame hole and bends in opposite side to winding direction.
Fixed conductor from inside of frame with sticky tape help.
I fixed it in two places.
Visible that it's fixed.
Now can move to winding.
First meters will be hardest, until form about tens of turns.
Further motor rotation speed can increase and systematically wind.
Spool with wire installed on floor.
Machine itself install at edge of table and do first wire revolutions manually on frame.
At that don't forget to turn on calculator for revolution count.
Thus this happens.
Necessary to do about 4-5 turns.
Pay attention that I dropped wire.
Nothing unwinds since wire has certain tension.
Now shift wire carefully along coil axis.
Form perpendicular direction to frame.
This most complex part of start of winding work.
Carefully do this work.
And further all will go much faster.
Correct start of wire done.
Calculator counted already 11 turns.
And now at subsequent winding conductor lays evenly.
Now can already move to winding mode in automatic mode.
Order of automatic winding so.
With nail of index finger of left hand I hold turns.
And right hand slightly lead conductor.
Thereby do laying turn to turn.
Now I apply power.
First small potential.
Motor here at 24 volts.
Apply about 9 volts.
And then can accelerate rotation.
Rotation slowly started.
I hold.
And increase supply voltage.
In such mode happens winding.
As do about 50 turns, speed can increase.
Rotation.
Because already appears rigidity of start.
I applied 20 volts of power.
Now calculator already shows 60 turns.
We managed to lay.
As they say, primitively but effectively.
Now I laid 100 turns on coil frame.
Such came out winding for us.
First turn we then carefully equalize.
Calculator shows exactly 100 turns.
What now I recommend to do?
Very important moment.
Because in winding process can happen different things.
Will go on overlap wire or something else.
Every 100 turns make mark on frame behind conductor.
And mark turn count.
Thereby if something happened for you, you always can unwind conductor back to coil spool.
Reach point of turn count that indicated for you here.
And further go from precise count point.
Now I'll apply this marker mark.
Like this.
And sign.
Here at this point we had 100 turns.
What calculator shows us.
Work finished.
Took somewhere 15 minutes for whole this coil winding operation.
Turn count recorded here.
By readings 832 turns.
And edge of wire fixed with sticky tape help.
Plus additionally 2 turns made.
Now can move to painting coil with first layer of shellac.
It'll fix whole wire.
Won't give it further to wind off, go away.
Especially this critical for coil edges.
Varnishing too one pleasure.
DC motor and voltage regulation.
I can regulate revolution count.
Of course also to this machine will need to make foot pedal.
Which will work as PWM regulator in system.
And then will be absolute convenience.
Before start of varnishing coil passed with napkin help.
Remove dust.
And now can directly apply varnish.
Apply will with small brush.
Dip in varnish.
Here.
And with such simple movement varnish applied.
That is not need even apply efforts.
Varnish evenly distributes by turns.
Small such mechanization pleasant and convenient.
Small coils of smaller diameters can of course wind manually.
But such, with diameter 150 mm, this already extremely inconvenient.
And thin wire will be very long.
Also at such method of applying varnish, after whole coil covered, leave it at slow rotation for 20 minutes.
And thereby very evenly varnish distributes without drops.
Convenient.
In whole so covered whole coil.
Here.
One coil I already made.
Covered with varnish.
Here it second same.
Covered with one layer.
Fully identical to that one I now wound.
On this all.
Assemble.
Construction not complex.
For work on its making me in light tempo took 2 days.
Everyone luck.