Hi all subscribers and viewers of my channel.
Today we'll examine several interesting moments people face in the tuning process.
The question.
The first of this format: I tuned a Tesla transformer to quarter wave by your calculations.
Now I want to retune it to half wave.
But when I calculate frequencies, my math doesn't add up.
And if by math I switch to the frequency I calculated, the coil doesn't settle in any way.
And what to do with this?
And are the calculations correct at all?
On this schematic picture I drew here conventionally the standing wave distribution in the Tesla transformer.
The same concerns the system on the grenade with grounding.
How currents and voltage are distributed in the case when the system stands at quarter wave, and in the case when the system stands at half wave.
It turns out that to fix the moment when our system is in quarter, we should get maximum voltage at the upper hot end of the Tesla transformer, at its isolated capacity.
At that, the maximum current will be at the lower end of the Tesla transformer.
This part — this is the grounding wire and its wave distributions.
The thing is, usually only this part is considered, and they forget what's happening at this moment in the grounding.
And in the grounding the picture happens in antiphase to what happens in the resonator.
So if the system as a whole became at quarter wave, effectively the whole system forms an integral picture, and we get this half-wave distribution.
But only a quarter of the standing wave is in our Tesla transformer.
Another situation, more interesting, we get when the system becomes at half wave.
In this case the point of voltage maximum moves from the hot end of the Tesla transformer to the middle of the coil.
At that, the current distributes differently, since between them there's a 90-degree shift, and the frequency here is higher, so this point moved with the rising of frequency.
The wavelength shortens, and it distributes differently along the length of our coil.
So the ratio turns out like this.
At half-wave distribution on our Tesla transformer, the current will be in antiphase at its ends.
At that, also don't forget as always about the grounding part that's here with us.
Here an integral figure also forms, and only now we get a full wave here.
If you consider the system as a whole, only half a wave falls on our resonator.
What calculations does a person do?
For example, I'll show calculations for my real coil so it's understandable with its example.
The action logic is simple.
A person calculates the Tesla transformer, then takes the quarter-wave resonance frequency, multiplies it by 2, and gets the frequency for the half wave on this resonator.
The thing is, here already there's idealized math, and for those who believe in it — in all these formulas and so on — it doesn't work.
If for quarter-wave resonance up to frequency 1.5 MHz you can still calculate wave speed through the known speed of light, then applying these calculations to a half-wave resonator already can't be done.
There'll be very large errors.
And now in practice we'll examine what errors come out in reality.
To move to the practical part, to start we need a simple device with which we'll track antinode and voltage in our coil.
I made it from a piece of copper wire 65 cm long — the wire folds practically in half, the system length comes out to 30 cm from the neon bulb to the point where we'll hold with fingers.
A system from copper wire, to the end of which a neon bulb is soldered, and the connection looks like this.
One contact I solder to the copper, and the other contact bend into this form.
Now we have a convenient probe for determining the voltage antinode on the Tesla transformer.
We'll supply frequency to the Tesla transformer with the help of a lab signal generator, and through it, changing its frequency, we'll determine via this indicator: does math actually show us the truth, that multiplying the quarter-wave resonance frequency we determine half wave, and what problems are connected with this.
Before you is our test specimen, my Tesla transformer, with conductor length 149 m, calculated frequency 500 kHz.
I made this transformer on a frame from air ducts, white plastic, using wire of 0.96 mm cross-section.
For it I also picked the isolated capacity, combined the wave distribution on wire length with LC resonance with the help of additional isolated capacity.
The Tesla transformer in this case is now connected to grounding, and at the base of the Tesla transformer coil there's one turn of conductor, to which we'll supply the signal from the lab generator.
In the first case we examine the moment of tuning the Tesla transformer to quarter wave.
Reminder, at quarter wave the voltage antinode will be at this point for us.
And accordingly the neon lamp should glow at this point, and as the neon lamp moves to the base of the transformer it'll go out.
I apply 500 kHz frequency.
You see, the neon lamp glows, and as we lower it, it goes out.
That is, the voltage antinode is clearly visible at the end of the winding of the high-voltage transformer.
The neon lamp will also glow near the isolated capacity.
With this moment, no special difficulty arises, and most often people do it successfully.
If you do the calculations that I gave earlier on my channel, all these moments are present, and you can calculate by them.
We also fix the frequency in this experiment.
Here it's visible on the lab signal generator at 500 kHz.
The neon lamp glows.
Now switch our system to half-wave mode.
According to idealized math, we multiply our frequency by 2.
So I set the frequency here at 1 MHz.
Now at this frequency the neon lamp at the hot end of the Tesla transformer went out.
And we can check whether the voltage antinode actually moved to the center of our coil.
Lead the indicator.
And as you see, the lamp doesn't glow anywhere.
Maybe we have some small errors.
Now we'll try to look at them.
Say, I reset the frequency to MHz and 100 kHz.
No distribution at all.
That is, it's a clear moment that the math doesn't work for us.
How did we calculate the half wave?
We place at the base of the middle of the Tesla transformer our indicator.
Approximately in the center of the winding.
And start adding frequency.
Lead smoothly by 10 kHz.
And see the moment when the lamp brightly lights up.
The moment of maximum lamp glow corresponds for us to the frequency for the Tesla transformer equal to half wave.
Now examine by indicator that at the hot end the neon lamp doesn't glow.
Glow is present in the center.
And also it doesn't glow at the base of the Tesla transformer.
And now what we got in fact.
What frequency?
Switch attention to the lab signal generator.
And see, the half-wave resonance frequency corresponds to 1480 kHz.
That is, we can make a conclusion — wow, what a difference.
We clearly understand that the math here doesn't work.
Now I'll also do a measurement of the spectral range of this Tesla transformer with the help of a spectrum analyzer.
Maybe I did something incorrectly somewhere, and the spectrum analyzer will show us the whole spectral range 100%.
Let's move to the experiment with the spectrum analyzer.
The optimal variant for tracking the resonance transformer frequency is the method of receiving it onto an antenna without connecting probes to this system.
Pay attention that the lab signal generator is now disconnected from the one turn.
And it's generally off to not create interference.
Now we check in this experiment the accuracy of tuning our Tesla transformer to quarter wave.
You can pay attention that a spectral peak appears periodically on the device.
This is the spike that jumps.
It's very well visible.
I installed a marker on it.
The marker frequency that shows by maximum is 500.1 kHz.
What does the appearance of this spike testify to?
That this Tesla transformer, when affected by some external radio waves from distant radio station transmitters or — as you could see, one spike slipped through.
Say, there's thunderstorm activity going somewhere.
Receiving it, it reacts.
And so I apply our frequency 500 kHz.
See, the spectral peak immediately grew multiple times.
And the presence of my hand, when I approach, the amplitude decreases.
This testifies to accurate tuning.
Also at this frequency the next spectral peaks of the range of our transformer start being tracked.
Now I'll change the frequency and we'll observe the spectrogram further.
I start increasing the frequency.
The step will be 10 kHz.
We see detuning.
Amplitude falls.
And the peak moves.
Here now is our math-calculated frequency 1 MHz.
See how small it is on this transformer.
I raise further.
Observe the growth.
And look where the maximum will be on such a frequency.
Our maximum
corresponds to 1.5 MHz.
Our measurements with neon lamp help were practically accurate.
In the course of these measurements the frequency was calculated at 1480 kHz.
Now I'll move the marker and look at the frequency.
Here's the frequency.
See that the marker moved up.
And here it corresponds to 1500 kHz.
At that, if we return to our Tesla transformer, at this frequency, as we remember, the neon lamp glows in the center.
Now I'll slightly raise the voltage so it lit, because for half-wave distribution I literally added 4 V, and this was already enough so the neon bulb lit.
Because the quarter-wave signal by voltage antinode is higher than at half-wave distribution.
What interesting can we notice on the spectrum analyzer?
We see that next frequencies are tracked for us.
Here they are, the spectral peaks that appear.
And this peak that jumps for us — this is our frequency 500 kHz.
That is, we see the range of frequencies of our Tesla transformer — that when we put it at half wave, both 500 kHz and subsequent frequencies were also excited.
Now I'll sweep through frequency, and we'll write out its frequency characteristic.
Move further.
So, the step will lead also by 10 kHz.
Go to the next maximum.
Remember by cells where the next peak was.
And at the next peak we'll have amplitude growth.
Here the amplitude started growing.
Here is its maximum.
The frequency by lab signal generator is 2990 kHz for us.
Look at the frequency.
The peak moved.
And see the frequency 2990 kHz.
Go further by frequency.
And here see the growth of the peak.
The next frequency
3840 kHz.
Look does it correspond.
All corresponds.
3840.
Now we fully know the frequency range of this Tesla transformer.
In those frequencies we can work out.
The whole scale now from 100 kHz start to the 5 MHz band in which we capture the spectral range.
All experiments that I conducted with the spectrum analyzer can be conducted with an oscilloscope and lab signal generator present.
Only now the course of the experiment will be different.
The same antenna that's now on the spectrum analyzer, we move to the oscilloscope.
Or hang nearby with the Tesla transformer its probe in the air.
And further change the frequency on the one turn with the help of the lab signal generator.
And write down for yourself all maxima and amplitudes the oscilloscope will fix at changing frequency on the lab signal generator.
The frequency picture will be the same.
Simply with the spectrum analyzer present this is conducted much more effectively and faster.
That's the whole difference.
Now by fact we can observe frequency distributions.
Quarter, half wave, three quarters, and four quarters is a wave.
Those frequencies we can still really work at with electronics help.
You see they don't obey math.
Say, if we'd found through math the wavelength, we'd have 500 kHz multiplied by 4.
It should correspond to 2 MHz.
And you see what frequency we have by fact.
So I don't recommend applying math.
In this case this question — how the person did the calculation — we cross out.
Now the essence of the physical phenomenon.
Why such an interesting moment happens with frequency distribution.
The thing is, these moments very brightly manifest themselves in resonance systems.
In classical systems where wave distribution goes, they don't behave like this, as namely in wave resonators.
Shortening coefficients are also applied there.
But in our case this manifests itself very brightly.
Let's examine the first case when the system stands at quarter.
The common system with grounding at half wave.
Here the spiral-wave resonator effectively affects 2 times less than in the system at half wave.
That is, in this case in the coil spiral half a wave fits, and here only quarter.
So the influence in this case increases.
And the interesting effect is observed that the wave speed in the spiral wave resonator grows compared to wave speed that moves simply in a straight conductor.
Paradoxical as it is, here's the interest.
Also it should be mentioned that the wave distributes not only in the wire to the grounding, but also in the soil to which this grounding is connected.
That is, from the cold end to the wire end, effectively the wave walks not only in this part, but also in the soils.
All depends on the soils.
And we have the moment that we now know that as frequency rises, physical wavelength meters decrease.
And so to in our case at half wave we fit our spiral wave resonator wire length precisely half wave, we also should raise frequency.
Exactly then it'll fit.
Reduce physical meters and put it into coil length.
Now a reasonable question arises or will arise from viewers.
Why these dances with a tambourine and switching the coil to half wave?
The thing is, for the build of a working system the presence of a half-wave vibrator is mandatory.
Without it any serious energy you won't get.
So no one is going anywhere from tuning the receiving coil to half wave.
And once more pay attention to the build of this coil.
I made it with thick copper wire, to remove active resistance specifically from it.
Further I'll make my own generator.
On this, all successful experiments and best wishes.
In the next video, which I'll try to film faster, another interesting question was asked.
How does one Tesla transformer affect another with the help of its fields?
What distributions happen?
How to create modulation without applying a lab signal generator and complex electronics?
It'll be interesting!