Greetings everyone on my channel.
This is again Q&A rubric.
First of all express gratitude to two people who gave little financial support to channel, didn't stay aside.
So, move to questions.
First question will be from person under nickname NelsonX.
How did health change after being near Tesla system working in needed?
I understand, word "mode" not finished.
Personally I didn't feel any global changes on my health, because I run these systems briefly, exclusively to peek operation mode and do measurements.
That is I don't leave system on, to admire streamers in such mode.
Only brief launches.
Saw in comments and heard from people also, that say, if they long time work with Tesla transformer on, some complain about headache.
Quite possibly, if expose self to this changing electromagnetic background, most likely it may somehow affect well-being in sensitive people.
But personally I believe Tesla transformer less dangerous in plan of radiation than same mobile phone or Wi-Fi.
From them much more person gets damage when uses these devices.
Especially recommended to turn off Wi-Fi system at least for night.
So, can be problems for those who have any electronic heart stimulation systems.
That is with this carefully, or other electronic devices helping person's life activity may fail.
With this carefully.
Question kind of, if can express so, slightly in joke form.
But I'll tell interesting story that happened personally with me.
With Tesla transformers wasn't such, but with gradient coils that we popularly call grenade, was interesting case.
Here where my lab is, I have warm floor made.
And turns out, when I started working with this system, to me every evening came cat, our domestic animal.
And he here, under desk where I work, here had bedding, and he here slept on warm floor.
And at one moment I work with this coil, wound another and test it.
Turns out, cat peacefully sleeps, suddenly he jumps up and starts running around room.
I don't understand what happens to him, take him in arms, he scratches me, bites, breaks free.
I opened door for him, he ran out to street and that's it, since then he didn't come to me.
And turns out, I didn't understand what happened with animal, what he was scared of, and further continue my experiments.
And somewhere through 10 minutes I felt some discomfort, in what plan it expressed, became not enough air.
I opened window, but it didn't help.
And then, after some time, literally 2-3 minutes, felt heart rhythm disturbance.
That is turns out, if in system low-frequency oscillations form, somewhere in hertz range, that is from 7 to 15 hertz, if such wave forms, it may affect internal rhythm of organ
work.
Because our brain sends signals at these frequencies for controlling our internal organs.
And this system affected precisely heart rhythm.
That is these moments track and observe self.
As such damage to health I didn't feel at that moment, but as fact, such observation is present.
Next question from person Yuri38.
So, also would shed light on Tesla tuning.
As already turned out, Tesla in this installation should work in wave LC resonance simultaneously to form statics.
In one of your videos you showed that at sharp break of wick it turns into streamer.
This mode we need, question.
Turns out our Tesla need to additionally interrupt at needed moment, besides that it works in bursts.
Seems this not enough.
When system tuned, yes, was me such video where I in manual mode additionally interrupted by power and observed static potential.
This was kind of hint at in what mode Tesla should work in this system.
Mean lying board, where we have Tesla transformer, antenna, gradient coil, known system.
Yes, Tesla there works actually in this mode.
Additionally interrupt it shouldn't, that is, put any additional generator.
There with us happens this interruption at correct tuning of trigger time.
But indeed Tesla should be in superposition mode, otherwise no static potential on antenna we naturally won't get.
Turn out usual oscillations, but this in no way has impact on receiving resonator.
Read further comments under video, and here paid attention.
Vladimir Matveev writes "Soon in country PEDS, and you here discuss radio parts."
I understand, call for urgent actions for us turns out.
This pizdets in country won't be, Vladimir.
Head-on us no scoundrel yet took.
Hold firmly.
Only thing, against us work from outside and constantly throw some ideas, invasion from abroad.
And this with our people often takes root.
That is need to observe self and clearly understand each person when he wants to commit some actions.
And really this idea that now in his head, was born precisely from him?
Where his origins?
And most often people don't even give themselves account of this.
And if stop and think, I say, go for some actions, but is this my idea?
And who reminded me of it, threw it in?
Where did I hear it?
And if act quite prudently, and not yield to this herd movement, then with us all will be normal.
Next question for us from Miss Nicole.
Hello.
If there's output frequency 24 kHz in fall from neon transformer, passing through power diode, will frequency change?
With neon ones didn't work, but understand so, if from neon comes sine wave, and we put one diode, that is cut one half-period, naturally this diode will divide your frequency 24 kHz in half,
that is will be for you 12 kHz at output.
But if at neon you have unipolar pulses, and in correct direction connected diode, then frequency will remain unchanged.
Question from zaryadshauberger.
Hello, Sergey.
About bonus.
Ah, this precisely about that video that was filmed together with Andrey Tirtho.
How much approximately added degrees to phase shift between Tesla coils, I understand transmitting, and second receiving?
Does phase shift 90 degrees decrease when these coils close in?
This second part of question I didn't yet review.
There turns out shift between them by 90, but precisely when move toward each other, didn't watch this moment, wasn't even interested.
And what phase shift becomes between them, this phase shift increases, but approximately there 2-5 degrees only.
Shift insignificant, that is detuning by frequency for us turns out several kilohertz between transmitting Tesla transformer and receiving.
And here this phase shift already quite enough.
If detune strongly system, there feels very well this point, turns out two identical Tesla transformers made, generally fully identical, tuned to one and same frequency.
Here you place them between selves at some distance and start pushing.
And can notice interesting phenomenon, that receiving Tesla transformer very strongly acts on transmitting with such force that if turn off system and then try to turn it on, it may not
start.
This phenomenon happens on systems with self-generators, that is Kacher-type systems, and on such systems, schemes of which I gave, that have direct control from master generator,
even in such mode transmitting doesn't start.
So, turns out two identical coils we made, then on isolated capacity, as in that video, there was visible, I have such spiral made, just twisted from aluminum and hung on top.
This spiral slightly shifted frequency down on receiving Tesla transformer, and this allowed transmitting transformer to easily start.
And further already main shift to operating zone I did with hand help, that is added additional capacity to receiving system.
At moment very easily caught, so don't think there'll be problems in finding this.
Only modes will need to search, this by interruption frequency, there'll be only several frequencies.
Again, them can well see by spectrum analyzer, well or in manual mode scroll interruption frequencies and watch what forms in your system.
Vivid example, that is criterion when system starts working, this is bright white discharge on receiving Tesla transformer and multiple amplitude excess on receiver.
Next question asks Anton Goloveznin.
Sergey, thank you, such question.
Can ready kit-sets be made for all installation blocks and tuning blocks?
Order at factory in China, boards with tracks, set of details.
Desirable with video for those like me, hard guys, how to assemble these logic blocks.
Anton, now this clearly no time to deal with.
My channel not yet at that level, so I could afford to spend extra time, say, on tracing these boards.
Make, order, negotiate, set up this whole global process.
System actually I try to give in very simple format.
I don't draw schematic in form, say, of logic elements.
I try to draw it in form of microchip.
And here what to connect to each leg.
That is each person can take my scheme, take details with ratings that presented on this scheme and already just looking at drawing, solder detail to detail.
And if during soldering wasn't any errors, that is person, say, didn't solder there, or forgot how to solder some wire, scheme starts from first time.
Because schemes personally mine, by me checked and by me developed.
Difficult in this especially nothing.
Can handle large number of people.
No need to consider yourself hard person in this case, because it'll be simpler than you think.
Main accuracy and perseverance.
And other moment still.
Matter in these systems not in electronics.
I in my videos already said that electronics is only 10% of total success.
There need to deal in larger extent with mechanical tunings.
What is mechanical tuning?
This is winding of coils, fitting turns, fitting inductance, conductor lengths, location relative to each other in this system.
In this big problem.
If tunings were reduced only to electronics, long ago everyone would already make and it'd simplify.
Need to have certain experience of tuning resonance systems.
Unfortunately, person who only acquaints with these things, has very small amount of practical experience.
And if he takes even classical electrical engineering as model for his activity and does everything correctly by it, this doesn't give guarantee that person can assemble this classic system.
This very good.
I always recommend people study classical electrical engineering first.
In plan that if person familiar with effects of classical electrical engineering, for him subsequent experiments won't be novelty.
Person when doesn't know even classical electrical engineering, any experiment he sets, for him it's something like small new discovery he made.
And if you don't have knowledge in classic, then to you all effects you get further will seem something new.
And this really what's needed to start this system.
So should be some practical experience.
Start need from small, study very well resonance systems, oscillating circuits, interacting oscillating circuits, complex resonance systems.
That is when one circuit interacts with another, and with third, and various modes of their work.
And all this precisely reduces to mechanical tunings.
Because there such modes happen interesting, that say, if you tuned one oscillating circuit.
And as people think, I tuned one circuit to needed frequency for me, and I tune second circuit to needed frequency, to same say.
And then person thinks, I now these circuits between selves connect, and resonance frequency for me already tuned, and like system will work.
So, what interesting, if such experiment done, frequency already very strongly shifts.
That is tunings of these two oscillating circuits to one and same frequency won't turn out this way.
Them need to tune jointly at once.
And turns out such moment, that jointly tuned system, say, of two oscillating circuits, and if then consider them separately, turns out they tuned to completely different
frequencies.
And resulting component of these frequencies, it'll be precisely needed.
This like first stage that should learn to do with resonance systems.
And then task complicates already.
Say, tune coupled circuits between selves, so one circuit worked at one frequency, and other, for example, at its harmonic, and system that swings this, generally worked, that is first
oscillating circuit of system that swings it, it should work at third frequency.
And this third frequency doesn't belong to first circuit or second.
These already systems that allow working on phase shifts, allow doing such tricks when to takeoff oscillating circuit connected load, and initiating oscillating circuit
that pushes our generator, doesn't see this load on itself.
That is, from such, would seem simple moments need to start, otherwise further will be very hard.
So, well and that's it, last was question.
I'll ask you to ask your questions under last video that comes out on my channel, with mark question-answer, as NelsonX did, by this mark for me will be easier to navigate in large
amount of comments.
Also under video clip leave channel help details, don't stay indifferent, will go for development for good cause.
On this say goodbye, everyone all good and successful experiments.