Greetings everyone on my channel.
This Q&A rubric.
Large quantity of questions came under last videos.
Now part of them will cover.
Well and along way I here make for one of my channel subscribers Tesla coil on order.
Real such tsar-coil came out.
Pipe 200 mm in diameter.
Winding length 80 cm.
Now stands under varnish.
Dries.
2475 turns laid on this coil.
Question first from user with nickname Sega Mega.
Good day.
I have question on your video.
Where does flow addition come from in gradient coil of 2015 experiment?
I'm not strong in electronics, but on ready scheme can solder scheme.
I have pulse generator plus-minus 10 volts at top 50 mA.
Me interested how can and with what devices and coils find frequency of ether oscillations in my region.
Yes, these experiments I conducted in 2015.
This effect was noticed not only on such gradient coils, but also on usual coils can see it.
Only in gradient notices it this moment better because we have there counter magnetic fields.
Windings wound counter.
Turns out, what's essence of experiment.
If we have such coil and apply on it frequency with very smooth transition.
Good if in your generator provided function of sweeping.
You set frequency range and long time for which generator automatically passes this range of set frequencies.
And by oscilloscope observe oscillation oscillogram in your coil.
And what can notice.
This transition should be smooth, if even in manual mode led by 10 Hz.
Not more than that.
For one switch apply sine wave.
Observed such effect that at some frequencies appears amplitude modulation of signal.
Usually most often visible such amplitude modulation, that it sags signal from your generator on coil.
Less it becomes by amplitude.
And at other frequencies can notice such moment that amplitude becomes multiple times bigger.
May be several times bigger than maximum amplitude that your generator capable of giving.
And this not connected with resonance of coil itself.
Desirable before this experiment conduct find resonance frequencies of your coil so not deceive.
Write out these frequencies.
There will be several pieces.
One of them maximum will be by LC resonance.
So when discovered such frequencies, they recorded and further can already conduct next experiment.
Remember frequency at which this moment happened.
And already at this frequency pick in parallel to outputs of gradient coil capacitors.
Tune it in resonance already accordingly to this frequency.
And then these effects intensify.
And can already conduct such experiments.
Notice that only at these frequencies currents of your coil will exceed short circuit current.
Short circuit naturally absent from generator.
There usually stands matching resistance 50 Ohm.
But on coil will be current higher than that your signal generator capable of.
And accordingly voltage amplitudes also will be multiple times higher.
This can each do such experiments and see.
Next moment.
Can find oscillation frequency of metals, for example copper sheet, or stones, or concrete.
Here didn't conduct such experiments, but accordingly oscillation frequency determine at material can various ways.
Only for such massive materials this already sound frequencies will be.
Need work in sound range.
On first question I'll throw link on video channel of Denis Permakov.
Here his video channel.
Now switch to it.
So what here is.
Here is at very start of video channel clip.
Here second clip starts, third, fourth, fifth, sixth, seventh clip, eighth, ninth.
Here in these clips described interesting system that helps calculate frequencies of your region.
Here in particular very interesting audio recording, third clip.
Now launch it.
Listen, me interested this picture to explain by it.
Sense of this device that we have electromagnet coil and we have coil wound around magnet.
And to magnet we apply signal, in video Denis I think here applied with pulses and drove this coil into resonance, and signal took from magnet.
Turns out, that he also found these same environment oscillations in region where he conducted these experiments.
Mandatory conditions of experiment, what here should be.
Need have teslameter to tune same magnetic field from electromagnet and so it equaled magnetic field by force to magnet.
This most mandatory condition, they should be equal.
Pickup can wind over magnet, but more accurate turns out, if here, in this zone between electromagnet and magnet place HALL sensor or piezoelectric sensor.
And already sweeping through frequency grid, at some we find same reverberations, only they here clearly expressed, amplitude modulations.
And about this, these videos that I above listed, there precisely goes talk about these processes.
Can view video clips, all quite accessible.
Question number 2 from Vitaly S.
Sergey, what's fate of your first installation with grenade?
You detailed told process of making, but now switched to experiments with Tesla-Tesla system.
Did you manage to set up stable work?
Did self-sustaining work out?
There's opinion that semiconductors-capacitors long don't withstand passing cold current.
In Nikola Tesla's times wasn't such elemental base, but somehow managed.
All normal with my first installation, alive-healthy.
So, say so, all that wanted to see, saw and special effects present.
Kilowatts didn't see, and so usually love pay for light.
All normal with this.
Did self-sustaining work out?
This in same topic with special effects.
Did manage to set up stable work?
With stability precisely big problem.
Thing is, can't there bypass one moment connected with elemental base.
Constantly fail capacitors in parallel of grenade.
They there do two functions.
Loop and second function.
This carcase that pushes this coil, switching resonator from quarter to half wave.
Sharp transfer happens and forms powerful energy surge.
Frequency grid restructuring that already comes to us on load further.
So, from this breakdown inside dielectric they constantly fail.
May work several seconds, may work longer.
System, they heat, but also fail accordingly.
Already bucket of them threw out, large quantity of finances goes on them, just tired.
For now not figuring out how to bypass this problem.
Effects same turn out on Tesla-type system.
Only here no loop capacity, so on this place big hopes.
That in this mode interfere this system won't.
There's opinion that semiconductors, capacitors long don't withstand.
Precisely they don't withstand.
About cold current, don't know, is it that kills them.
I so look that this physical breakdown of dielectric.
And at moment such, seemingly, can put, logically, take capacitors at bigger voltage.
Well and all will be good, breakdown absent.
So, precisely no.
Take capacitors that have voltage bigger and no breakdown, no effect, system doesn't work.
If do external some spark gap, this doesn't help, there such specific breakdown happens precisely in capacities.
In Nikola Tesla's times wasn't such elemental base, but somehow managed.
Yes, elemental base such absent, but he dealt with mechanical systems, synchronization was mechanical.
That is if we remember his patents, drawings of devices, there were at him drums on which could move along axis brushes.
And he made various type of contact.
Were usual straight, were wedge-shaped contacts.
So, what turns out.
Regulating speed of rotation of such drum, we factually regulate frequency.
And moving contact brush along drum axis, if we have wedge-shaped contacts, we change time.
That is turns out system that we analogous make now with electronics help, form pulse bursts.
Also at him were drums synchronized by angular speed of rotation with generator.
That is this very convenient actually system when at you, say, in lab is dynamo machine.
And you can synchronize directly drum with its rotor that rotates.
Thereby, turns out, can make even system of current rectification, quite big by amplitude of voltage and total power.
That is if for example we'll take with such drum synchronized by angular speed, for example sine waves at its peak, at output we'll get already practically direct current.
Remains only smooth it with accumulator capacity help.
And here already ready powerful system for charging capacitors.
Here what he dealt with.
That is, he found elegant exit from situation, having only mechanical means.
This all easily achievable.
Plus he also dealt with various systems precisely by interrupting discharge.
If look, he and interrupted it with magnetic field help.
Usually draw that there simply magnets are.
But maybe now, in our current time, when have powerful neodymium magnets, this and can do.
But then he did this with controlled electromagnets help.
Then were at him systems of blowing spark gap with hot air stream help.
Mechanical interrupters on motors that rotated toward each other with spark gaps.
That is, all solved mechanical way and quite well worked.
And moreover, on mechanics can achieve commutation of very big currents with high voltages.
What for us even now on our elemental base absolutely unavailable.
So, who wants precisely work in that direction, find effects that Tesla himself got, mechanics, don't worth refusing from it.
Question third from Herkon.
Sergey, hi!
Formed two questions.
First.
Classic of theory of electromagnetic circuits says, more precisely teacher told us so, that at circuit closure at first moment of time capacitor represents short circuit.
But if with meter start measuring capacitor resistance, its resistance will go to negative area.
Does this effect have relation to cosa nostra, that is to FE generator.
About ammeter.
It goes to negative resistance because capacitor takes charge from ammeter battery.
And about that capacitor equivalent to short circuit, this here your teacher lied.
Capacitor actually, its charging process much more complex process than to many seems.
Could you send to read books of classical electrical engineering.
There are all graphs.
I even typed in internet to see what to us draws.
In search graph of capacitor charge by current.
Went to pictures, here different pictures.
Here one of cited books of electrical engineering.
Here we have graphs.
Drawing 118.
Us will interest this picture.
Graph of change of current and voltage on capacitor terminals at its charge.
Time scale at us.
This scale of conditional amplitudes.
And I understand this scale of growing voltage.
And this current scale.
So they tell us that at moment of capacitor connection happens current maximum, then it fades.
And at moment of maximum current minimum voltage.
Now we this matter check in practice.
I have no classical education in profile university, so I don't tend to trust what they write.
Earlier, long ago I this experiment conducted, and there mass of interesting things.
So, scheme of experiment.
With us will have dual-channel oscilloscope, two probes.
Probe highlighted with blue will track current.
By voltage drop will on resistor.
Resistor at us will be 0.1 Ohm.
First beam, yellow, will look voltage on this capacity.
Capacity 2.2 mcF.
Simultaneously with two probes look.
Also at us is key, and before key is fast-acting diode.
To exclude influence of any post-resonance processes with long conductors that go from lab power supply.
Voltage that I'll apply, makes 200 V.
Here scheme in iron.
Capacity film 2.2 mcF.
Resistance 0.1 Ohm.
Visible that common two channels at one point.
Here also comes minus power source.
First channel follows voltage.
Second channel current, by voltage drop on resistor.
In role of key will be simple movement, closure of conductors.
And here at us is fast-acting diode.
Now oscilloscope in mode of recording one-time signals.
Do closure, capacitor charge.
So, device recorded our signal.
Now can examine it more detail.
What we see here?
Yellow, remind, this at us voltage.
Blue, this current.
We clearly see that our graph at least very strongly differs from what cited in textbooks of classical electrical engineering.
Clearly is some wave process.
Current goes not by smooth growing.
If we look picture from smart book, this first drawing, this our voltage graph.
If voltage graph approximately matches, then current graph absolutely not similar to what we now see on oscilloscope screen.
This already becomes interesting.
Need now figure out where with us turns out such process.
Clearly process resonance, that is with us oscillations.
And we now conduct second experiment and more detail examine this most interesting phenomenon.
And for now I'll transfer to sheet of paper resulting oscillogram.
Now conduct experiment number 2.
Blue probe that tracks current, remains in place on resistance.
And yellow channel probe at us moves at this point, directly after diode.
Essence of this experiment in observing how behaves voltage at moment when we close this key.
Here our graph that as was in previous case.
Only now we observe that at us is amplitude of supply voltage.
200 volts.
Here precisely see one cell and two cells.
If precisely combine, with us will be here voltage, applied 200 volts.
And here first most interesting feature.
Why I apply 200 volts, and maximum amplitude makes 348 volts.
Where this addition by voltage on capacitor?
Let's examine more detail.
Here clearly visible resonance processes by current.
And here desired by us point.
There's intersection of current and voltage.
Now will do one more charge of capacity at bigger sweep to look more detail this process.
Discharged capacity and now try to catch.
Here, there's moment.
Can now see more detail.
Turns out, we have clear oscillation processes.
And visible moment, if so more detail examine, that growth of current intersects with fall of voltage.
Precisely this and is that important moment that classical electrical engineering hushes.
When happens such phase shift of current and voltage, factually it makes 90 degrees, then in our circuit are sine oscillations.
And this leads to these resonance processes, that throws up voltage on capacity ultimately.
Now let's discuss what we got.
So, this point, this moment, marked with dashes, when we do key closure and connect capacity.
At initial moment of time have maximum voltage, potential 200 volts and zero current.
Here our voltage curve, and here our current curve, remember oscillogram.
And here what happens.
Closure, voltage starts sharply striving to zero and at this same moment starts growing current.
But happens such moment that current growth, this part, it meets with voltage, at this point.
Here is, as in resonance circuit, shift of current and voltage by 90 degrees or about this.
And these moments, they generate at us such powerful current oscillations that distort curve of current charge.
It goes not as draws us by logic, it goes precisely by such graph.
This graph, it may depend on many factors.
Capacitor capacity, resistance in circuit, wire lengths, inductances.
Resonates, essentially, at us here all capacities and conductors that present in our experiment.
Because even smallest conductor has inductance.
And precisely this process allows us additionally get on capacitor small portion of energy.
Turns out not on all capacitors, I specially took such capacitor that can fast charge, high-quality film capacitor.
On electrolytes this phenomenon will be expressed very weakly.
So here many nuances.
And precisely on these nuances people work, and make some interesting devices.
These transient processes that classic point-blank doesn't see, for them this usual graph.
They allow us charge our capacity to bigger potential than we had at input.
Make conclusions self, is there addition or no, and what this is.
Well as see, respected Herkot, that your teacher turned out simply lazy parrot that never conducted experiments in practice, but only repeated learned in smart books.
Item 2 of Herkot question.
In general, he checked Wi-Fi hub power supply, and turns out it gives stable voltage 9 volts, but at more detailed examination turned out that there pulsation 1 Hz, as I understand.
And essence of question reduces to whether can from these pulsations get rid and further use as duty.
Or power supply for microchips.
This common problem in switching power supplies, such pulsations with various frequencies.
Defeat them can if apply chains at output that serve for filtering, this chokes and electrolytic capacitors.
Often manufacturer for economy purpose puts cheap capacitors that fast fail.
Or happen cases when on board still provided places for capacitors.
For example, developer provided installation of three capacitors, and there instead of three stands one.
And I understand still smaller rating than needed.
Chokes may not be at all.
Install can additional such chains and such pulsations may be defeated.
Pulsation 1 Hz, of course, very low-frequency.
In this case, don't know, will manage to get rid of it.
Need search reason from what this happens, if interesting.
And so, if power supply worked and then started pulsating with some frequency, then most likely cover electrolytic capacities.
And in most cases, at their replacement in output path of power supply, already from this problem get rid.
Item 3.
Since speech went about lab block, what are and what kinds of each pluses and minuses.
And what good for cosa nostra, that is for FE generator building.
When I picked self lab power supply, I immediately determined that I need high-voltage power supply.
And when I searched their brands, I noticed that high-voltage power supplies as such very few who makes.
My power supply, say, brand Mostech, it at 300 volts.
But such power supplies quite expensive.
If something professionally don't deal, no sense take them.
Still for reason that these our devices that we deal with on FE generator topic, they should launch exclusively from accumulator battery.
And after accumulator battery made own converter at needed voltage.
Thus this system works.
Why better do through launch from accumulator?
Because system automatically gets untied at us from network.
In all cases when we run system from lab power supply, inevitable its connection of our device through interlayer capacity in winding of pulse transformer with network.
Because our device quite high-frequency.
And here may be very many problems, smallest of which that device will unstable launch or not launch at all.
And most, I consider probably big problem will be that moment that may happen hit directed toward lab power supply, and it'll fail.
For what, say, I acquired lab power supply at 300 volts?
Thing is, with it convenient quite to use.
And further, for schemes that I test, on my channel is video about lab power supply with voltage up to 1000 volts.
Because in some cases, for detecting specific effects in system, need raise voltage potential higher.
At devices there's so-called threshold, when should be supplied certain potential so processes in system started.
Talk about pluses and minuses here doesn't come relative to our FE generator building because manufacturer doesn't even assume that we'll for this these power supplies use.
Here advise can't, no one specially for our purposes made them.
Question from Valery Khomyakov.
Hello, thanks for sharing experience.
Can now or in near future acquire from you something working to connect at least 2 kW oil heater?
Valery, I myself would want acquire something stable at 2 kW.
Probably here should say about what negative role internet played in forming opinion about these devices.
Many video clips are, many people talk on this topic.
And majority of these clips are deception, fake.
For what people make me unclear such fakes, may be to attract self attention or earn money, but fact is fact.
Most big result that was achieved in these systems, personally I trust, among my acquaintances who deal with this, was 650 W.
About no kilowatts yet speech goes.
Now all is at stage of lab specimens that show most interesting results.
And there's hope that further can them stabilize and already get some energy for own use in stable mode.
So sorry, offer nothing can, and sell I most likely don't plan, this such slippery matter.
For me this hobby and most interesting occupation.
For many people this also is interest.
And moreover noticed such interesting moment, when person starts experimenting in this area and at him in head such thought sits, sooner make this magic box and start it
sell.
Won't turn out at such person ever.
Need slightly change morally, internally, survive this moment.
I and myself sometime was obsessed with such idea, think, soldering know how, what there to do, now I'll do.
And this now stretched 8 years before I got my first result.
So in sale I don't think soon something similar will appear.
Such today situation.
Question 5 from Anatoly Avarazhikhin.
Good time of day, Sergey.
In your scheme from clip flyback converter with stabilized output voltage and current protection.
At drain of FET transistor stands diode FR207, resistance 5.1 Ohm and capacitor 1 nF 1000 V.
If I correctly understand work of this trio, then these elements needed for restraining energy surge from coil at moment of transistor turn off.
Role of capacitor — absorb this surge, resistor — prepare capacitor to absorb next surge of diode, not let high potential back to drain.
Did error not creep in arrangement of these elements?
Now examine this scheme more detail.
Speech goes about this scheme and this trio.
Capacitor, diode FR207 and resistance.
Here earlier in video clip you saw 5.1 Ohm, now I here use 22 Ohm.
Here can vary this resistance.
No error in arrangement of details here, this done by me consciously.
And I watched oscillograms of key work and what here happens.
Most often accustomed to see such schemes when diode at drain of FET key and connects directly to capacitor.
And parallel to capacitor is resistance.
Here system works so.
When happens key closure, forms surge that cut off by capacity charge of this capacitor.
Surge goes through diode FR207.
See that with one plate capacitor connected to plus power and accordingly to one of leads of primary winding 9 turns.
So to it applied amplitude of this surge.
When surge amplitude reached maximum, then capacitor at us charges to this amplitude.
Further happens its fall.
And capacitor starts discharging through current-limiting resistance 22 Ohm on primary winding.
Thereby increasing time of this surge that forms at us at key drain.
No error in this.
You can self check, assembling this scheme.
Can naturally change location of details by your discretion.
I consider this optimal scheme solution for low-voltage power of flyback converter.
So, these were answers to questions on penultimate video.
Under last video, theory of free energy origin or where firewood from, came also large quantity of questions.
There will need conduct practical experiment.
This will be in next video clips.
Remind that ask questions should under last video released on my channel with mark question-answer.
Also in description to video clips you can find details of help development of my channel.
Whoever has such possibility, please help.
Well and share video, subscribe to my channel.
Will be much all interesting.
Everyone successful experiments, all good and good mood.