Good time of day, dear viewers.
Today we'll show you, as promised in previous clip, some documents.
Before you now brochure advertising installation Aquator-600, awarded with gold medal.
Originals of documents present.
Now show close up.
Such was gold medal.
Where you got it?
Was exhibition in Omsk city 21-23 March.
International industrial exhibition.
At this exhibition presented 10 manufacturers of drinking water.
And among them was announced competition.
And only to one was given gold medal.
And given medal was precisely to model, precisely Aquator-600 system for water preparation technology.
Naturally, were presented documents additionally.
This not just installation reviewed.
But were presented documents, patents, water analyses.
That is very many documents were presented on first day of exhibition.
And only on third day jury and commission gave assessment to whom.
And here in nomination drinking water this installation for technology was awarded diploma and gold medal.
Excellent.
Further wanted people to look, asked questions.
Any documents, for example, from St. Petersburg station about that your water corresponds to norms.
You said that you have some document.
In each city there's former SES system that controls drinking water.
And there's Vodokanal system.
Vodokanal is separate organization that watches drinking water in Omsk city.
Omsk is million city.
Very powerful system of water intake, filtration, preparation.
At this large organization is lab accredited for drinking water quality research.
I with this lab agreed, paid cost of analyses.
And before trip here, to you to Kuban, got following document.
Called "Protocol of water research in comparison with original and after processing on installation AKVATOR-600".
This was system of enterprise "UAGROPROM".
Already took for approbation this installation.
Having installed at self this installation for production of bottled water, we went to vodokanal.
Presented our installation AKVATOR-600.
Researched first was original drinking water from tap in vodokanal.
Water that came out of installation AKVATOR-600.
And norms.
You observe in this table.
Original water and exited after installation.
Parameters in principle didn't change.
There's slightly changes.
It was more alkaline.
7.7.
At output after installation 7.26.
7.3.
Water remained in range of weakly alkaline.
Can so with stretch say.
But it didn't drop below 7.
And rest all indicators didn't change.
Didn't change.
Remained same as original.
Further.
Most interesting indicator.
What here?
Here also, if look by metals, then changes big we don't observe.
Difference from original.
But it much smaller than by norm.
For example, what we take?
Arsenic.
Arsenic, say, in water 0.05.
And original and water after system 0.005.
That is, such poisonous.
This column — this after...
This column — after aquator.
And most interesting indicator — this toxicity.
Water not toxic.
But original after installation also not toxic.
But most interesting.
Next.
Not detected any microflorine.
Not detected.
This explained about microflora.
This what explained?
This presence of pathogenic flora or any other flora in water.
That is water sterile.
But allowed total microbial number 50.
Allowed.
Here in original 0, after installation 0.
Not detected and other bacteria.
Not detected in water.
But most main indicator.
Distinctive indicator.
This oxidation-reduction potential.
Or we say ORP.
Or by American redox potential.
Original water 584 mV and 0.4.
And at output after installation AKVATOR-600 — 181.3.
This about what speaks?
Water in Omsk now went with addition of chlorine, oxidizers.
That is went flood waters.
And water need to...
Vodokanal system throws disinfectant some components.
At first place naturally goes...
What goes?
Chlorine.
Water after installation, came out of installation AKVATOR-600, became negatively charged.
It saturated with oxygen, hydrogen.
It disinfected because indicators completely don't give any microflorine.
Water, by indicators, became, as people say, living.
That is we revived water, removed components of oxidizers.
Such water drink can, but undesirable.
Water after installation AKVATOR-600 became living.
It became with ORP minus 181.3.
This excellent indicator.
Installation very well processed water in Omsk.
Here in your stanitsa, water rarely chlorinated.
Less in it oxidizers.
We showed in past that original water by this number about 200.
And water at output almost minus 300.
We today got minus 400 millivolt.
Show after documents.
Next page.
This protocol additionally that it has acceptable degree of toxicity.
Speaks that water not toxic.
When needed water not toxic?
This when we can in aquarium pour, animals give.
And most main indicator — this water can be allowed for children's intake.
At children, if required water give to children contingent, then one of indicators, besides all listed earlier, is non-toxicity of water.
Here this installation makes water non-toxic.
Because applied unique electrodes that don't introduce in water any component.
We here specially, we want to focus attention, we glued because going now patent search because assumed patenting.
We composition of electrodes, but for vodokanal I should have said that we use.
Otherwise they wouldn't undertake give me conclusion on researched water.
And here see that this was all 12.04.18.
That is literally 10 days ago was conducted this research.
That is fresh research?
Yes.
And I can do scans if ask to provide?
Yes, please.
Excellent, because during video clip, I think, will be those who want to read all this, look.
Good.
Especially who familiar.
Will provide.
Good.
Now read some questions under video that we filmed 3 days ago.
Watched it for today practically 2000 people.
199 people rated positively, 9 negatively.
But rest, as they say, abstained.
And most often asked question.
Here, for example, from Viktor Rudenko.
Good day, Sergey.
Tell please, where to buy this device?
Or more precisely, will you be able to make it to order?
Since most likely in series it didn't go.
Will be grateful if you can answer me.
Thanks for video.
People already, I look, start to fear that technology will be closed.
And they won't be able to acquire this product.
I think will be interesting to know approximate cost price of such device.
Small-series now.
Week ago in Omsk came out newspaper.
It called "Commercial news.
Omsk".
Where was published article.
With me met correspondent Anastasia.
And asked questions.
And first question was naturally cost price of installation.
I presented documents that calculations were presented.
With them agreed in editorial office.
And sum of cost price of installation for today 30 thousand rubles.
What's today this installation?
This small-series production.
This not large series.
This 10 installations per week.
Big for now I had no orders.
This my close circle.
And yes, to someone I cost price gave.
Because helped me this all do.
Someone got.
Maximum price was sales at me about 2-3 installations.
Total so went 45 thousand.
So was some profitability.
So was for what.
For example, with these money I came here.
With these money I tomorrow will tell, show in Stanitsa Dostogaevsky this installation.
There interest showed.
There goes cottage construction.
There go in Anapa city also construction, apartments.
And interest showed in entrance, in apartment.
And especially in cottage villages.
Especially where there are pools.
Small pools, actually, of private use.
This installation will allow make water useful and disinfected.
So can answer by cost price.
That is, I understand, this small-series production.
If production goes to series, then price will be cheaper.
Well, I think, above 25 thousand it won't be.
But this series, it will be called.
Thousand per month.
Then will it pay off.
And so it piece goods.
This all lathe work, welding.
Preparation of electrode itself, most main.
This all for today still costs very expensive.
You plan to release, for example, this device.
As I understand, from it can successfully get and drinking water, and also fill baths.
And if, for example, people will ask you, so you released purely for drinking some small device, so could drink quality water.
This possible?
Yes, this possible.
But should remember about other.
Here very strongly tied time of passage between electrodes.
So very small device may not give those indicators that required for today.
And we think that, if so count in internet, minus 250 — this optimal ORP that necessary for drinking water.
Minus 250 lower may already start to live through microflora.
Uncomfortable state for microflora starts from minus 200 millivolts.
That is installation should be.
Can do that we now show.
You showed in first clips size.
Can reduce to smaller size.
But it to what size attached?
We know in store.
I use standard case for water filtration.
Case from filter.
And here is cartridge less twice this.
Then can do also in case twice less.
Water.
We already such model tested.
It gives minus 250, minus 300 maximum.
Then can speak about reducing price and size.
Many were calls.
Read one from user with nickname.
Time rus collect.
Give formulas to masses.
That is there are people, craftsmen who'd want to know system formula and embody it further.
Plan you after getting patents, after system goes to series, to publish structure of your device?
Yes.
First.
After getting patent.
Patent will what restrict?
People won't be able to produce for sale, that is deal in commercial activity on making this installation.
This will be considered with acquiring license for right of using technology.
For own needs all craftsmen will be able to repeat, possibly even improve installation.
Possibly will appear more new, but principle itself, technology itself, it will be patented and remain at my name.
Produce each for self can, but won't be able deal with this installation, manifest it as with commercial purpose.
I think fair since you inventor and want get financial reward for your many-year work.
Yes, I with this deal from 1986.
On this topic at me written candidate, doctoral.
I very much conducted research, very much was researched various electrodes, differently they self behave.
Now not need search any pairs, here something guessing, this all done nature.
Nothing new by me invented, I took ready variants that nature presented to us.
Simply yourselves think how water spring prepared in nature.
All repeated one to one, nothing new.
Well, naturally, power supply.
Yes, in power supply will be self-determined frequency, that'll be also named, to it will need then tune power supplies precisely at this frequency.
But first goes patenting.
Read one more question from Nikolay Strizhev.
Usual device for living and dead water produces living water with ORP in range minus 500 mV.
This precisely question from that series why buy such device if there are already devices that not flow-through and make such indicator.
Excuse.
So, return to protocol that made in vodokanal.
This protocol speaks that in water no single additive, no single component that would self-negatively affect.
That is stainless, all other metals that'll be subjected to electrochemical impact will leave trace in this water.
Such water will be toxic.
Such water will be called heavy metal salts.
So stainless fully rejected.
No stainless.
Yes, devices were similar to our device.
But get analysis in best lab located near with you.
If you such document get, flag to you.
I'll read result.
Results of water sample research before and after processing on installation EKVATOR-600 don't exceed hygienic norms SANPIN.
Drinking water.
Hygienic requirements for water quality of centralized drinking equipment system.
Control of quality of maximally allowed concentration of chemical substances in water, in water objects, in water-economic field, in cultural field by listed above indicators in norm.
And next.
Toxicity done in some lab and confirmed that water not toxic.
These records should be at craftsmen if someone tries to repeat past 70s years.
Two electrodes in water, two stainless and one diode.
Well, may be, bridge do.
This not enough.
On this went years.
On this went candidate, written doctoral.
Next question interesting.
From Anatol Zelitis.
Probably not from Russia person.
Sergey, if will be possibility deepen into this topic, then look under microscope spring, analog, say, baikal, and compare water after this device.
Will be difference of structure?
People ask, changes structure, conducted such research, or will be conducted further?
By microscopy of clean water for this need not just microscope.
Need electron microscopes.
Need research state of hydrogen relative to oxygen.
Need look angle between two oxygens, between two hydrogens.
Need look how changes.
Yes, this looked.
Yes, changes small after electrolysis.
Small, but they are.
But I about other will say.
So, we'll look slightly in other perspective.
Need look effect of this water on biosystem of our organism.
And most important that'll answer, useful water or not useful, this dark-field microscope.
This blood before water and after water in dark-field microscope, and we'll look formed blood elements.
I immediately say forward.
I as doctor these research conduct already not one year.
And see, before water use at person erythrocytes clustered, gathered in coin stacks.
After taking liter of water, after five minutes after next sample take blood, erythrocytes dispersed.
They become more active.
Rheological properties of blood significantly improved.
We'll look how this water responds on biosystem of our organism.
And it responds positively.
System our responds to water positively.
We such research conduct.
We'll show.
They already conducted, simply I to such volume of material wasn't ready.
First meeting.
If people will interest, I'll be able further illuminate on my channel.
Big thanks to you, Vladimir Nikolaevich, for spent time, answers to questions of my viewers, of my YouTube channel.
Documents that were shown during this video overview, I'll place links to them in description.
And each can look at this protocol that conducted in Omsk city on research of their water, of vodokanal.
And this same water that passed through your flow-through module.
Continue experiment number 2.
Passed 3 days.
Date and time.
Now we'll open 5 liter canister.
Here seal on it.
All in sealed state.
For start we check device readings on control liquid.
Electrodes in it lowered.
Liquid yellow color.
What's this liquid?
This red and yellow blood salt in certain concentration, in certain proportion.
This buffer solution for control of platinum and chlor-silver electrodes.
Readings should be in range 220-230.
Then this device will show correct numbers by ORP.
Excellent.
That is we convinced that device now at us serviceable.
And now we wash electrodes.
Napkins here.
Wind at us blows away, so we won't hide them.
Today so windy.
In Anapa area today windy.
So, here seal.
All filled, glued fully.
Now we'll remove solution because it oxidizes, changes.
It should so wasn't access of free air, I understand.
Good.
Open.
Well filled will.
Oh!
Carefully.
Hand will tear off.
Well dissolve all.
All.
I'm joking.
So, all.
Opening successfully conducted.
Almost without loss of fingers.
Yes.
Pour, rinse.
Once more rinse for control.
And collect.
Now most interesting, what indicator after three days.
Readings went down.
Not bad indicator.
Wonderful.
Minus 266 already.
267.
This wonderful.
Three days water preserves negative ORP.
This speaks that this most likely not structure of water change.
This not influence of some salts, something we did.
This most likely in water after this system appeared some negatively charged particles.
There are assumptions.
We for now won't speak about them.
But simply activated water for today.
Here same American systems called hydrogen generators for making quality negatively charged ORP.
Preserve this indicator from eight hours to day.
We today see.
What day?
Third.
Third, full day.
Today exactly three days.
At 12 hours will be exactly three days.
And negativeness of water almost remained in same limits.
At us it was...
Need look at record.
It was in range 300.
There 280 was.
Yes, 280.
We slightly lost.
But nevertheless, this excellent indicator.
It stably holds in this water.
That is, this speaks about good activation of water.
This speaks that water preserved initially acquired properties.
This not in plan of preserving it.
This in plan that it maximally active.
That is, it falls into organism.
And even better if in this water take baths.
I in past my appearance not once said very important, interesting word.
Water passing through PEM system, flow-through electrochemical module, gets disinfected.
For what?
In process of electrochemical activation of water forms short-living ozone.
Ozone sterilizes water.
We now show you documents.
We show documents that confirm that analysis of water, seeding of water after this system, no single microflorine, zero.
Total microbial number.
That is water at output from this system sterile.
About what this speaks?
This water can pour in pool, in mini-pool.
In this water can bathe newborn, not fearing that this water has some bad properties.
And it sterile.
Here need about what still additionally speak.
We past time spoke about its activity.
And slightly missed word.
Water disinfected.
This most main.
We don't need chlorine.
We don't need boil.
That is, this water can use raw.
We now this show.
Here, for example, water that we measured.
It I, not fearing, can this glass drink.
And there are questions.
And water useful.
And do you yourself drink it.
Please.
It soft.
It tasty.
It drinks pleasantly.
Sufficient quantity of it can drink.
Two liters per day need such water drink.
Every one and half-two hours at least by glass.
We see that water suitable for drinking.
From self say, I face neutral, uninterested.
Simply person at me stopped on way to coast.
There he'll offer these systems, as I understand, for implementation.
Now at you goes process of patenting this device.
So people asked questions about device, all rest.
That is we'll be able this probably announce only after you get documents.
Now at this moment goes patent search.
Assumed application for patent.
Now, at end of April, returning to Omsk, me will provide documents of patent search.
Is such device?
No plagiarism?
Didn't I repeat something of other authors?
I believe that repeat can't be.
This all done by me.
This all done by me on conclusion that I came to very long ago.
And those research that I conducted...
But wasn't need then of publication.
Moreover, when I defended candidate on these electrodes, it went under DSP until 90s, until Union collapse.
Some interesting works that could be coupled with Soviet Union state, weren't allowed to publish, weren't allowed to defend openly.
And all those works that I wrote, didn't publish, they went with DSP stamp.
For official use.
After 90s, in 2000s, this became all property.
We could calmly speak and tell.
Now we can't name only for one reason that goes patent search, and prematurely name what electrodes we at this moment use.
Also as third experiment we decided to conduct such experiment.
Filled bath old, even didn't wash it normally, nothing, simply I on it patches made so water didn't leave, with water.
It day stood in open air, this activated.
And now will conduct also its measurement by ORP, preserves its property, suitable such technology for open pools.
Electrodes in water.
Readings also go to minus.
Filled it yesterday, 290 indicator was.
Excellent, in day and continues to fall.
And imagine, if this system will work continuously on pool, there'll be cleanest water suitable for swimming, without any chemistry.
We speak about what?
That in this water with such indicator microflora doesn't live, it uncomfortable.
That is we can refuse from chemical disinfectants with which wash, sterilize, process, more precisely, disinfect pool water.
Can now speak that such water will replace whole chemistry, moreover that most main chemistry this chlorine.
We can without chlorine.
Why?
Why water such?
Because it in PEM system, flow-through electrochemical module, without membrane, without membrane.
There formed ozone, this ozone sterilized, disinfected water.
Water arrived disinfected, in it no microflora, it stood night on open surface and remained in good minus.
This speaks much.
This speaks about wonderful perspective, precisely such membrane-less PEMs.
It may be any productivity.
This system that we showed to you, PEM, it, can say, average, average.
Its productivity about, approaches 500 liters per hour.
500 liters per hour.
We can produce installation, make twice less, purely drinking, up to 200 liters per hour, twice reduce.
Can increase and will be not 500, but 1000 liters per hour.
This already for industrial, this already can be, this can be animal husbandry, this can be irrigation some systems.
But perspective of such useful water with such indicator, huge.
Now system works, launched.
We want to show fourth experiment.
Collect water in three-liter jar and look gas release.
Gas that'll release is hydrogen.
Look how much hydrogen turns out at us at system work in flow.
Gas release will be visible by forming bubbles and by how liquid filled with fine dispersion of hydrogen gas mixture.
I thought initially that this'll be as in electrolysis process.
Yesterday checked, but no, turned out this practically pure hydrogen.
Now well visible that during work happens gas release, and water inside jar filled with fine dispersion of gas mixture.
That is system produces at such minimal consumption also quite large quantity of pure hydrogen practically.
Hydrogen burning need also fix.
Pull out tube and I'll film now in light jar.
Well visible how it filled with hydrogen bubbles that rise up.
Large quantity of gas actually.
Now happens hydrogen exit from liquid, water lightens,
and forms clean drinking water.
You decided to do measurement now of water that we collected.
Yes, here collect.
Collect flow-through.
System already worked several days at me, adapted to our local water.
Can do measurement.
Indicator even higher.
Noticed such moment that system should several days work on local water, and its indicators by ORP grow.
In comments people wrote that non-flow systems that produce water with membrane on cathode and anode, so-called living and dead water, indicator may be minus 500.
Maybe we now try such water demonstrate that this system also capable of making it.
Here hydrogen exited from jar, and visible that this not some dust, not contamination, but this clean drinking water.
So, fix if we catch moment.
Well, 400 this already good.
Now once more look.
Well, 400 we can do.
400 in flow.
This not bad.
Yes, I think, if as you announced, that blood minus 150, then this indicator approaches...
From minus 70 to minus 150 depending on organism state.
Many in comments write, blood minus 70.
Yes, yes, this again indicator of organism activity.
This not constant minus 70.
This number...
I now with speed changed.
Improving speed, increasing time of water activation, we can get and minus 400, and minus 500.
By idea, if this system close-loop, kind of do several passes, then possibly increase of this indicator...
At second cycle may come number different.
Or put two such devices in series one after other.
One through one, yes, one through one.
Can tune device, can get and bigger numbers.